<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="static/style.xsl"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-06-08T16:55:56Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" resumptionToken="oai_dc////17000">https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/oai/request/</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15108</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-02T07:58:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Produktwerbung von Valserwasser - eine Globalisierungsgeschichte?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Demarmels, Sascha</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Textlinguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Werbung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bildlinguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-02-06T14:16:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-06T14:16:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15108</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15108</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15108</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-631-56621-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3631566212</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Werbung grenzenlos : multimodale Werbetexte im interkulturellen Vergleich</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Sprache im Kontext</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Peter Lang</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3217</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-22T12:56:32Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Neue Ausbildungsniveaus im Pflegebereich : Auswirkungen von Rollenunklarheiten und dem Einsetzen-Können von Fähigkeiten auf die berufliche Zufriedenheit</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schaffert, René</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Trede, Ines</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Fachkräftemangel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Rollenklarheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Berufszufriedenheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wandel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ausbildungsniveaus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Im Zuge von Veränderungen im Gesundheitswesen entstehen auch neue Ausbildungen und Berufsprofile. Dies kann zu unklaren Berufsrollen führen, wie eine Mixed-Methods Studie zum Berufseinstieg von Absolventinnen und Absolventen von drei, neuen oder umgestalteten, Ausbildungen im Pflegeberich in der Schweiz zeigt.  Unklare Berufsrollen sowie fehlende Möglichkeiten erlernte Fähigkeiten im Arbeitsalltag einzusetzen wirken negativ auf die Zufriedenheit mit der beruflichen Situation.&#13;
&#13;
Einleitung: Ähnlich wie in anderen Ländern erfolgte in der Schweiz ein Wandel der Versorgung im Pflegebereich mit der Schaffung von neuen Ausbildungsniveaus. Ein Diplom in Pflege kann in einer traditionellen, überarbeiteten Ausbildung an höheren Fachschulen (HF) oder neu über ein Bachelorstudium (BSc) erworben werden. Zusätzlich wurde auf Sekundarstufe II ein neuer Berufsabschluss Fachfrau/Fachmann Gesundheit (FaGe) geschaffen. In der Folge mussten die Arbeitsteilung und&#13;
Berufsprofile angepasst werden.&#13;
&#13;
Zielsetzung: Angesichts dessen soll untersucht werden, inwiefern neue Ausbildungsniveaus zu unklaren Berufsrollen führen und ob dies Auswirkungen auf die berufliche Zufriedenheit hat.&#13;
&#13;
Methoden: Dies erfolgte in einem explorativen sequentiellen Mixed-Methods-Ansatz auf der Grundlage von Studien aus der Deutschschweiz zum Berufseinstieg nach einem der drei Ausbildungsniveaus. Im qualitativen Studienteil wurden 53 teilstrukturierte Interviews Inhaltsanalytisch ausgewertet. Die dort gewonnenen Erkenntnisse wurden anhand von Daten zu 671 Berufseinsteigenden quantitativ überprüft, indem mittels Mittelwert vergleichen sowie multivariaten linearen Regressionen auf der Ebene der drei Ausbildungsniveaus untersucht wurde, ob sich die Rollenklarheit nach Ausbildungsniveau unterscheidet und inwiefern sich Rollenunklarheiten und das Einsetzen-Können von Fähigkeiten unter Kontrolle von Alter, Geschlecht und Arbeitsfeld auf die berufliche Zufriedenheit auswirken.&#13;
&#13;
Ergebnisse: In den Interviews berichten FaGe und BSc-Pflegende von Unklarheiten in den Berufsrollen und in diesem Zusammenhang auch davon, ihre Fähigkeiten nicht einsetzen zu können. Dabei wird auch Unzufriedenheit geäussert. HF- Pflegende hingegen beschreiben ihre Berufsrolle als klar. Die quantitativen Resultate zeigen, dass FaGe etwas unzufriedener mit der beruflichen Situation sind als Pflegende mit HF- oder BSc-Abschluss. Die berufliche Zufriedenheit wird bei FaGe von der Rollenklarheit und dem Einsetzen-Können von Fähigkeiten beeinflusst. Bei den HF- oder BSc-Pflegenden zeigt sich beim Einsetzen-Können von Fähigkeiten ein signifikanter Einfluss. Das Modell hat bei den BSc mit 22% erklärter Varianz die stärkste Erklärungskraft, gefolgt von 15% bei FaGe und 14% bei HF-Pflegenden.&#13;
&#13;
Schlussfolgerung: Wenn neue Ausbildungen im Gesundheitswesen geschaffen werden, sollte in der Praxis besonders auf die Rollenklarheit sowie die Passung der Fähigkeiten der Berufseinsteigenden geachtet werden, um Unzufriedenheit im Beruf zu vermeiden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-27T13:31:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-27T13:31:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-09-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3217</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3217</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3217</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>VFWG Kongress: Gesundheitsberufe - Wege in die Zukunft, Wien, Österreich, 28.-29. September 2017</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>FH Campus Wien</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10952</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T11:47:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kompost, Humus und Pflanzenkohle in der Substratentwicklung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Saluz, Andrea Gion</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Kompost</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pflanzenkohle</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Substratentwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>630: Landwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-09-21T11:58:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-21T11:58:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://www.kompost.ch/fileadmin/user_upload/www.kompost.ch/publikationen/compost_1-2017.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10952</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Compostmagazine</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Kompostforum</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11719</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-20T09:51:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Programmed ribosomal frameshifting and codon usage bias</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Garcia, Victor</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zoller, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Anisimova, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Codon usage bias</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Programmed ribosomal frameshifting</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>mRNA translation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Genetics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>572: Biochemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Experimental evidence shows that synonymous mutations can have important consequences on genetic fitness. Many organisms display codon usage bias (CUB), where synonymous codons that are translated into the same amino acid appear with distinct frequency. Within genomes, CUB is thought to arise from selection for translational efficiency and accuracy, termed the translational efficiency hypothesis (TEH). Indeed, CUB indices correlate with protein expression levels, which is widely interpreted as evidence for translational selection. However, these tests neglect -1 programmed ribosomal frameshifting (-1 PRF), an important translational disruption effect found across all organisms of the tree of life. Genes that contain -1 PRF signals should cost more to express than genes without. Thus, CUB indices that do not consider -1 PRF may overestimate genes’ true adaptation to translational efficiency and accuracy constraints. Here, we first investigate whether -1 PRF signals do indeed carry such translational cost. We then propose two corrections for CUB indices for genes containing -1 PRF signals. We retest the TEH in Saccharomyces cerevisiae under these corrections. We find that the correlation between corrected CUB index and protein expression remains intact for most levels of uniform -1 PRF efficiencies, and tends to increase when these efficiencies decline with protein expression. We conclude that the TEH is strengthened and that -1 PRF events constitute a promising and useful tool to examine the relationships between CUB and selection for translation efficiency and accuracy.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-11T14:51:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-11T14:51:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4023</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4023</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11719</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11719</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11719</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Life in Numbers 4.0</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Life in Numbers 4, Wädenswil, 4 October 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21423</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-29T04:01:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Are there epigenetic oxytocin-mediated effects on the mother and infant during physiological childbirth?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Uvnäs-Moberg, Kerstin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gross, Mechthild M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Agius, Andee</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Downe, Soo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Calleja-Agius, Jean</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Caesarian section</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Effect of oxytocin</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Epigenetics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Longterm effect</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Oxytocin</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Oxytocin receptor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Polymorphisms</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Skin-to-skin contact</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vaginal birth</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618.4: Geburt</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Introduction: &#13;
Studies have shown that long-term positive behavioural and physiological changes are induced in connection with vaginal, physiological birth, and skin-to-skin contact after birth in mothers and babies. Some of these effects are consistent with the effect profile of oxytocin. This scoping review explores whether epigenetic changes of the oxytocin gene and of the oxytocin receptor gene (OTR) are involved in these effects. &#13;
&#13;
Methods: &#13;
We searched Pubmed, Medline, BioMed Central, Cochrane Library, OVID, and Web of Science for evidence of epigenetic changes in connection with childbirth in humans, with a particular focus on the oxytocin system. Results: There were no published studies identified that were related to epigenetic changes of oxytocin and its receptor in connection with labour, birth, and skin-to-skin contact after birth in mothers and babies. However, some studies were identified that showed polymorphisms of the oxytocin receptor influenced the progress of labour. We also identified studies in which the level of global methylation was measured in vaginal birth and caesarean section, with conflicting results. Some studies identified differences in the level of methylation of single genes linked to various effects, for example, immune response, metabolism, and inflammation. In some of these cases, the level of methylation was associated with the duration of labour or mode of birth. We also identified some studies that demonstrated long-term effects of mode of birth and of skin-to-skin contact linked to changes in oxytocin function. &#13;
&#13;
Conclusion: &#13;
There were no studies identified that showed epigenetic changes of the oxytocin system in connection with physiological birth. The lack of evidence, so far, regarding epigenetic changes did not exclude future demonstrations of such effects, as there was a definite role of oxytocin in creating long-term effects during the perinatal period. Such studies may not have been performed. Alternatively, the oxytocin linked effects might be indirectly mediated via other receptors and signalling systems. We conclude that there is a significant lack of research examining long-term changes of oxytocin function and long-term oxytocin mediated adaptive effects induced during physiological birth and skin-to-skin contact after birth in mothers and their infants</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-01-28T09:33:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-01-28T09:33:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms21249503</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-21423</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.3390/ijms21249503</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-21423</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21423</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21423</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21423</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1422-0067</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1661-6596</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>33327490</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>MDPI</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17710</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-07-24T09:39:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Konzept Reconciliation : Friedensarbeit und Konfliktbewältigung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schürch, Barbara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eser Davolio, Miryam</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Friedensarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Reconciliation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Konfliktbewältigung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>303: Soziale Prozesse</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-07-24T09:39:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-07-24T09:39:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17710</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17710</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17710</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-906129-72-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Reconciliation</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Edition Gesowip</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17501</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T14:06:12Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Career counseling within three paradigms: guiding, coaching, and designing : thoughts towards career services</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schreiber, Marc</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>331: Arbeitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-07-17T08:53:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-07-17T08:53:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-06-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17501</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17501</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17501</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Annual Meeting - Career Services Network Switzerland, Winterthur, 5. Juni 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18596</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-08-11T13:36:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Comment on Osler et al : misinterpretation of pre‐post‐differences invalidate the authors’ conclusions</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Volkmann, Constantin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Plöderl, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hengartner, Michael Pascal</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>616.89: Psychische Störungen, klinische Psychologie und Psychiatrie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>This is the peer reviewed version which has been published in final form at 10.1111/acps.13110. This article may be used for non-commercial purposes in accordance with Wiley Terms and Conditions for Use of Self-Archived Versions.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Osler and colleagues published a cohort study investigating antidepressant medication and suicidal behaviour and violent crime in patients and conscripts. They report an increased incidence rate for both events before and after treatment initiation when compared to the follow‐up period. They conclude that there is likely no causal effect of antidepressants on either of the two endpoints, because the rates between treated and untreated individuals did not differ substantially at each time‐point and the rates of both events did not increase in the antidepressant group after treatment initiation as compared to the pre‐treatment time period.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-10-31T13:56:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-10-31T13:56:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1111/acps.13110</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-18596</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1111/acps.13110</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-18596</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18596</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18596</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18596</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0001-690X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1600-0447</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>31610010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Wiley</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4912</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T12:55:56Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Versprechen Sie nie zu viel!</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Coenen, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Zufriedenheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Spital</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Qualität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Patient</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.11: Krankenhäuser und verwandte Einrichtungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-06T11:27:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-06T11:27:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4912</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4912</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4912</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Solothurner Spitäler Magazin</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Solothurner Spitäler</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21662</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-11T15:35:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Gültige Kündigung trotz Krankheit</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stohwasser, Stephanie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>344: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Arbeits-, Sozial-, Bildungs- und Kulturrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-02-11T15:35:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-02-11T15:35:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21662</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21662</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21662</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1663-8549</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1663-2702</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>ius.focus</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Helbing &amp; Lichtenhahn</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20747</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-10-30T04:01:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_53</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Dunkle Flecken : bedürfnisgerechte Schwangerschaftsbetreuung durch die Hebamme bei von häuslicher Gewalt betroffenen Frauen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brunner, Julia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Krättli, Andrina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Häusliche Gewalt</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Intimate partner violence (IPV)</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hebammenbetreuung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schwangerschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bedürfnisse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Schwangere Frauen sind einem erhöhten Risiko ausgesetzt, von körperlicher, sexueller und psychischer Gewalt betroffen zu sein. Damit eine bedürfnisgerechte Betreuung gewaltbetroffener schwangerer Frauen gewährleistet werden kann, muss das Fachpersonal jedoch an eine standardisierte und bedürfnisgerechte Betreuung herangeführt werden.&#13;
&#13;
Ziel&#13;
Ziel dieser Arbeit ist es, herauszufinden, welche Bedürfnisse von häuslicher Gewalt betroffene Frauen bezüglich ihrer Hebammenbetreuung während der Schwangerschaft haben. Es soll ausserdem dargestellt werden, wie die Betreuung in Fällen von häuslicher Gewalt optimiert werden muss.&#13;
&#13;
Methode&#13;
Anhand fünf qualitativer Studien aus drei verschiedenen Datenbanken wurde ein Literaturreview verfasst.&#13;
&#13;
Relevante Ergebnisse&#13;
Aus den analysierten Studien kristallisierten sich fünf Hauptbedürfnisse von gewalt-betroffenen schwangeren Frauen bezüglich der Hebammenbetreuung während der Schwangerschaft heraus: eine kontinuierliche Betreuung durch die Hebamme ist gewünscht, der Schutz für das ungeborene Kind soll ermöglicht werden, Hebammen sollen beraten, das Thema «häusliche Gewalt» soll während Vorsorgeuntersuchungen direkt angesprochen werden und das Gesundheitsfachpersonal soll regelmässig zur Thematik geschult werden.&#13;
&#13;
Schlussfolgerung&#13;
Von häuslicher Gewalt betroffene Frauen müssen während der Schwangerschaft durch eine Hebamme bedürfnisorientiert betreut werden. Dafür braucht es zukünftig ein einheitliches Vorgehen, um den Schutz der Frau und des Kindes in Zusammenarbeit mit anderen Fachstellen ermöglichen zu können.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-10-29T14:40:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-10-29T14:40:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-20747</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-20747</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20747</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20747</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20747</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>93 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3213</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-22T12:56:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Evaluation eines Online-Tutorials zum Prostatakarzinom</dc:title>
          <dc:title>Evaluation of a prostate cancer e-health-tutorial</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schaffert, René</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dahinden, U.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hess, T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bänziger, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kuntschik, P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Odoni, F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Spörri, P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Strebel, R. T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kamradt, J.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tenti, G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mattei, A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Müntener, M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Subotic, S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schmid, H.-P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rüesch, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Decision making</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Health service research</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Internet</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Patient education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Prostate cancer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616: Innere Medizin und Krankheiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Hintergrund: Angesichts verschiedener Behandlungsoptionen ist die Information und Therapieentscheidung beim lokalisierten Prostatakarzinom eine Herausforderung. Die digitale Informationstechnologie bietet im Vergleich zu gedruckten Informationen mehr Möglichkeiten, die Information und die Patientenkommunikation bedarfsgerecht zu gestalten.

Ziele: Zur Unterstützung der Therapieentscheidung und der Kommunikation mit Patienten ist in der deutschsprachigen Schweiz ein Online-Tutorial in einem systematischen Prozess entwickelt und in einer Pilotstudie getestet worden. In der Evaluation interessierten die Nutzerzufriedenheit, die Erfüllung der Informationsbedürfnisse, die Vorbereitung auf die Therapieentscheidung und deren subjektive Qualität. 

Material und Methoden: Die Plattform wurde in einem iterativen Prozess mittels Fokusgruppen mit Ärzten und Patienten auf der Grundlage von Informationen aus bestehenden Broschüren entwickelt. Für den Test der Plattform wurden in 8 urologischen Kliniken 87 Patienten zur Teilnahme eingeladen. Die 56 Nutzer wurden 4 Wochen nach dem Login und 3 Monate nach dem Therapieentscheid online befragt, 48 Nutzer füllten beide Befragungen aus. Eingesetzte Instrumente waren die Preparation for Decision Making Scale (PDMS), die Decisional Conflict Scale (DCS) und die Decisional Regret Scale (DRS).

Ergebnisse und Diskussion: Die Nutzenden sind mit der Plattform sehr zufrieden und finden ihre Informationsbedürfnisse gut erfüllt. Sie zeigen 3 Monate nach dem Entscheid eine gute Vorbereitung auf die Entscheidung (MW PDMS 75, SD 23) und berichten über niedrigen Entscheidungskonflikt (MW DCS 9.6, SD 11) und kaum Bedauern über die Entscheidung (MW DRS 6.4, SD 9.6). Basierend auf diesen Erkenntnissen kann die Plattform zur weiteren Nutzung empfohlen werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Background: Due to the multitude of therapy options the treatment decision after diagnosis of a localised prostate cancer is challenging. Compared to printed booklets, web based information technology offers more possibilities to tailor information to patients’ individual needs.

Objectives: To support the decision making process as well as the communication with patients we developed an online tutorial in a systematic process in the German speaking part of Switzerland and then tested it in a pilot study. The study investigated users’ satisfaction, the coverage of information needs, the preparation for decision making and the subjective quality of the decision. 

Materials and methods: Based on already existing information material the online tutorial was developed in an iterative process using focus groups with patients and urologists. For the following evaluation in eight clinics a total of 87 patients were invited to access the platform and participate in the study. From these patients 56 used the tutorial and 48 answered both surveys (the first one 4 weeks after the first login and the second one 3 months after treatment decision). The surveys used the Preparation for Decision Making Scale (PDMS), the Decisional Conflict Scale (DCS), and the Decisional Regret Scale (DRS).

Results and Conclusion: Satisfaction with the tutorial is very high among patients with newly diagnosed localized prostate cancer. Users find their information needs sufficiently covered. Three months after the decision they felt that they were well prepared for the decision making (Mean PDMS 75, SD 23), they had low decisional conflict (Mean DCS 9.6, SD 11) and almost no decisional regret (Mean DRS 6.4, SD 9.6). Based on these findings the further use of the tutorial can be recommended.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-27T13:27:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-27T13:27:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4199</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00120-017-0552-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4199</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/s00120-017-0552-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3213</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3213</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3213</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0340-2592</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1433-0563</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>29209755</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Der Urologe</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21588</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-04-14T09:29:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Abnabeln und die Erstuntersuchung durchführen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Putscher, Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oberndörfer, Petra Katrin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Neugeborenenpflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Geburtshilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Neugeborenes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nabelpflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-02-10T11:29:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-02-10T11:29:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21588</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21588</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21588</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-0355-1842-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Skills für Hebammen 3 : Neugeborenes</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>hep</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18196</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-22T12:56:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Erste Absolvierende des BSc Gesundheitsförderung und Prävention in der Schweiz : eine Studie zur Entwicklung deren Berufsidentität</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Biehl, Verena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Page, Julie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wieber, Frank</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>378: Hochschulbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610: Medizin und Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-09-19T08:25:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-09-19T08:25:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18196</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18196</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18196</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Swiss Public Health Conference 2019, Winterthur, 28.-29. August 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5032</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T10:53:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Comprehensibility and comprehensiveness of financial analysts' reports</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Whitehouse, Marlies</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Perrin, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>332: Finanzwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>400: Sprache und Linguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Financial analysts and their texts play a key role in the financial community. Despite their importance, both the analysts as writers and the texts themselves are widely under-researched, as a review of the literature in the field reveals. This is the gap that our large research project on financial analysts’ written communication aims to close. Based on a context-annotated corpus of roughly 1500 financial analysts’ company reviews (in German, English, and Japanese), we investigate the cultural, organizational, and individual variety of the texts’ communicative potential for investors. The final goal of the entire research project is to identify critical situations and situative good practices of cross-disciplinary communication in the financial community.&#13;
&#13;
In the present paper, we focus on one specific genre, a small qualitative sample, a product-only approach, and on one specific research question from the financial communication project: why do equity analysts’ company updates for investors fail to reach their communicative potential? We start by systematically contextualizing the genre in the light of the research question (Section 1). Based on a qualitative English sub-corpus (Section 2), we then explain how we used pragmatic text analysis to investigate the texts’ comprehensibility and comprehensiveness in cross-disciplinary communication (Section 3). The results suggest that these texts bear the risk of partial communicative failure (Section 4) and what actions can improve their communicative potential (Section 5).</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-10T15:31:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-10T15:31:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scoms.2015.03.007</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.scoms.2015.03.007</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5032</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5032</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5032</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-4896</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Studies in Communication Sciences</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Seimso</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20838</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-11-19T09:53:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Using impact orientation for effective climate communication</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bättig-Frey, Petra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jäger, Monica Ursina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Impact</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Narrative environment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Outcome</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Climate change communication</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Target group</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>302.2: Kommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333.7: Landflächen, Naturerholungsgebiete</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Communication on climate change usually goes beyond the mere transfer of factual knowledge: sustainable climate communication motivates the audience to reflect their own lifestyle and to adapt it to make more climate-friendly choices in everyday life. The research group Sustainability Communication and Environmental Education presents a selection of four vivid project examples, which communicate knowledge more effectively, efficiently, and sustainably. Each presented project illustrates an innovative communication strategy to foster an engaged, informed, and long-lasting relationship to climate-related topics such as nutrition, CO2-footprint, landscape, and soil.&#13;
&#13;
The starting point of each project is a precise impact orientation, defining the key messages and recommendations for action. Based on the impact orientation, an analysis of the relevant target groups is conducted, before defining the means for communication. This method results in specific approaches for targeting different groups. The first example uses a scientainment approach. The 'Zombie Mission', a digital outdoor game, attempts to communicate facts about sustainable nutrition to a young adult target group that is not environmentally aware. The second example is an interactive exhibition which provides personalized tips for reducing the individual footprint based on a lifestyle analysis. The third project uses targeted storytelling and immersion to achieve long-term and reproducible storage of knowledge (Dahlstrom 2014) The educational panorama trail “Zwischenhalt Zukunft”, is a multi-media interpretive environment (Paraizo 2011) where scientific visions of the future are brought to life with images overlaying the existing landscape and with audio installations. The last example is the narrative environment  “Erdreich” (Bättig-Frey et al 2018). It operates with the same methodology as “Zwischenhalt Zukunft” but focuses on soil. By using this more tangible subject, information on climate change can be communicated without overwhelming – and putting off - visitors with the complexity of the politically charged debate around climate change. &#13;
&#13;
All these projects are developed in an interdisciplinary team, where natural and social scientists, communication experts, artists, landscape architects and graphic designers work together during the whole project. The team creates outdoor spaces with interactive exhibits and garden elements, that invite visitors to immerse themselves in a landscape of visual impressions, sounds and stories. Instead of a purely factual information transfer, these “narrative environments” tell a story that convey scientific content in a playful, affective way. Facts and complex correlations become meaningful and tangible, and visitors create their individual relationship with the topics. Attractive settings and immersive experiences create positive emotions that make visitors more receptive (Friedman 2013). They absorb information and are more motivated to think about changes in their own lives. Using these tools thus can help improve the transfer of knowledge from scientists to the public, resulting in a more meaningful debate and ultimately help to establish new sustainable habits, leading to a more resilient society.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-11-19T09:53:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-11-19T09:53:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-11-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://geoscience-meeting.ch/sgm2020/wp-content/uploads/abstract_volumes/SGM_2020_Symposium_19.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20838</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>SGM 2020 Symposium, Abstract booklet Session 19 (Tackling the Climate Crisis)</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>18th Swiss Geoscience Meeting 2020, Zurich (Switzerland), 6-7 November 2020</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Swiss Academy of Science : Platform Geosciences</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14266</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-04T12:56:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Heterogene Strategieteams : Moderationsmethoden für Strategieworkshops</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lüthi, Erika</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pichel, Kerstin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Moderationsmethode</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Strategieteam</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Regionalreffen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Workshop</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-01-09T13:13:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-09T13:13:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14266</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14266</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14266</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>14. BSO Regionaltreffen, Bern, 4. Juni 2013</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13903</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-08T13:01:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Disability insurance benefits and labor supply decisions : evidence from a discontinuity in benefit awards</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Tobias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Boes, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Disability insurance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Labor market participation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Maximum simulated likelihood</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>360: Soziale Probleme und Sozialversicherungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenzen.ch)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>The effect of disability insurance (DI) benefits on the labor supply of individuals is a disputed topic in both academia and policy. We identify the impact of DI benefits on working full-time, working part-time or being out of the labor force by exploiting a discontinuity in the DI benefit award rate in Switzerland above the age of 56. Using rich survey data and a discrete endogenous switching model, we find that DI benefit receipt increases the probability of working part-time by approximately 32% points, decreases the probability of working full-time by approximately 35% points and has little effect on the probability of being out of the labor force for the average beneficiary. Looking at the treatment effect distribution, we find that male, middle- to high-income and relatively healthy DI beneficiaries are more likely to adjust their labor supply from full-time to part-time, whereas women, low-income and ill beneficiaries tend to drop out of the labor market. Our results shed new light on the mechanisms explaining low DI outflow rates and may help better target interventions.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-12-17T09:06:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-17T09:06:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3447</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00181-018-1587-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3447</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/s00181-018-1587-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13903</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13903</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13903</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0377-7332</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1435-8921</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Empirical Economics</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11590</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-10-10T11:40:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>"The common agricultural policy in the 21st century" with a link to Switzerland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Flückiger, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>338: Produktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Colleagues and collaborators of Professor Hofreither have written articles with a focus on the European agricultural policy, the political decision-making process, and multi-sectoral modelling. These issues, among others, played the main part in the broad research curriculum of Professor Hofreither at the University of Natural Resources and Life Sciences, Vienna (BOKU) over the last 25 years. During this time he has helped explain European agricultural economics to a Swiss audience from an Austrian point of view by writing from the perspective of alpine and small country farming culture, structures and practices. As such, the Festschrift edited by Schmid and Vogel contains valuable material for Switzerland. This review discusses each of the nine contributions to the book in turn, finally drawing out particular questions and lessons for Switzerland.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-10T11:40:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-10T11:40:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Rezension</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11590</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11590</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11590</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1023-3938</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Jahrbuch Agrarwirtschaft und Agrarsoziologie 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>SGA - SSE - SSA</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24540</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-10T15:34:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Whistleblowing-System : eine Bauanleitung für Schweizer Unternehmen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Drenckhan, Helke</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>341: Völkerrecht und Europarecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Bis zum 17. Dezember 2021 war die EU-Whistleblower-Richtlinie (WB-RL 2019/1937) in nationales Recht umzusetzen. Diese Richtlinie will Whistleblower in den Mitgliedstaaten besser schützen. Einigen Mitgliedstaaten ist die fristgemässe Umsetzung gelungen, aber bei weitem nicht allen. Voraussichtlich in diesem Jahr werden die nationalen Gesetze in der EU nach und nach in Kraft treten. Auch Schweizer Unternehmen sind dann gefordert, Whistleblower in ihren EU-Töchtern besser zu schützen. Gefragt ist ein Whistleblowing-System und das schon in Unternehmen mit 50 Mitarbeitenden. Lesen Sie hier, was eine solche Meldestelle bedeutet und wie Sie diese implementieren.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-03-10T15:34:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-03-10T15:34:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-02-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.38023/85e6a760-cc91-4948-a5e6-8764cb2d91e7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.38023/85e6a760-cc91-4948-a5e6-8764cb2d91e7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24540</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24540</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24540</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-7410</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Jusletter</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Weblaw</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21866</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-25T11:01:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The impact of the Swiss climate policy instruments on the energy consumption and greenhous gas emissions in the industry and the service sector : evidence from an ex-post evaluation of microdata</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Leu, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Carbon Tax</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Emission Target</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Energy Consumption</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Greenhouse Gas Emission</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Policy Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333.79: Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-02-25T11:01:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-02-25T11:01:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21866</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21866</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21866</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>The 5th European Conference on Behaviour and Energy Efficiency, Zurich, 5-7 September 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6258</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T08:08:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wage differential between the public and private sector in Hungary between 2002 and 2008 : the long term effect of wage increase</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Altwicker-Hámori, Szilvia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lovász, Anna</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>331: Arbeitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-30T11:46:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-30T11:46:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://econ.core.hu/file/download/HLM2014/TheHungarianLabourMarket_2014_onefile.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6258</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>The Hungarian labour market 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Centre for Economic and Regional Studies, Hungarian Academy of Sciences</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21489</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-06-03T08:16:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Evaluation of potential co-benefits of air pollution control and climate mitigation policies for China's electricity sector</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wei, Xinyang</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tong, Qing</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Magill, Iain</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vithayasrichareon, Peerapat</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Betz, Regina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Air pollution</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>China</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Co-benefits</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Electricity sector</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>363: Umwelt- und Sicherheitsprobleme</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Since the rapid industrialisation, local air pollution has become one of China's most important environmental issues. In consequence, increasingly stringent air pollution control policies have been established by the Chinese government. These policies will inevitably affect China's future electric power investment given the key contribution of this sector to air pollution. This sector is also a key contributor to China’s greenhouse gas emissions and hence climate policy efforts. We present a study exploring what impacts of potential interactions and combinations of different policy efforts for local air pollutant control and carbon mitigation have on China's future electricity generation mix. The study utilises a novel generation portfolio model that explicitly incorporates key uncertainties in future technology costs and different policy approaches including carbon pricing and air emissions control. The findings highlight that China can achieve significant reductions for both greenhouse gas and local air pollutant emissions through a combination of climate change and air pollution control policies. Furthermore, there are potentially significant co-benefits from the perspectives of both air pollutant control and carbon mitigation and, notably, that the co-benefit from a sufficient carbon pricing policy to air pollution emission reductions is much stronger than that from stringent air pollutant control policies to carbon mitigation. Specifically, in order to achieve substantial local air pollution and greenhouse gas mitigation from China's electricity sector, it is necessary to close coal-fired power plants rather than merely seeking to clean their air pollution emissions up.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-01-28T13:35:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-01-28T13:35:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eneco.2020.104917</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-21489</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.eneco.2020.104917</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-21489</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21489</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21489</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21489</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0140-9883</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1873-6181</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Energy Economics</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24023</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-05-06T16:23:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Association of multiprofessional preoperative assessment and information for patients with head and neck cancer with postoperative outcomes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schmid, Manuela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Giger, Roland</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nisa, Lluís</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mueller, Simon Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schubert, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schubert, Adrian Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>616: Innere Medizin und Krankheiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Importance: Multidisciplinary perioperative assessment for patients undergoing complex oncologic head and neck cancer (HNC) surgery is widely implemented. However, to our knowledge, the association of multiprofessional preoperative assessment, information, and briefing with postoperative outcomes has not been evaluated.&#13;
&#13;
Objective: To compare postoperative complications, length of hospital stay (LOS), readmissions, mortality, and costs per case among patients undergoing complex oncologic HNC surgery before and after the implementation of a comprehensive preoperative multiprofessional assessment and information day (MUPAID).&#13;
&#13;
Design, Setting, and Participants: This retrospective, single-center case-control study was conducted at a tertiary referral head and neck anticancer center/university cancer institute and compared patients with HNC who were undergoing complex oncological surgeries between January 2012 and July 2018 before (control group) and after (intervention group) implementation of the institutional MUPAID. Data analysis was conducted between 2019 and 2020. The intervention group comprised patients who participated in the MUPAID beginning in February 2015. These patients were assessed by a multiprofessional team and provided with structured and comprehensive information on the surgical procedure and its functional, social, financial, and psychological effects, as well as the postoperative care, rehabilitation, and follow-up period. Patients in the control group had also undergone complex oncologic HNC surgery and were selected through surgical procedure codes.&#13;
&#13;
Main Outcomes and Measures: The end points were postoperative rate and severity of complications, LOS, readmissions, mortality, and costs per case.&#13;
&#13;
Results: The study included 161 patients, 81 in the intervention (25 women [30.9%]) and 80 in the control group (18 women [22.5%]). The groups showed no relevant differences in sociodemographic, disease, and procedural characteristics. The intervention cohort presented with fewer major local and systemic complications (Clavien-Dindo score, III-V: 34.6% vs 52.5%; difference proportion, −0.179; 95% CI, −0.33 to −0.03), shorter median LOS (12 days [IQR, 10-16 days] vs 16 days [IQR, 11-20] days; effect size, 0.482; 95% CI Cohen d, 0.152-0.812) and decreased median charge per case ($50 848 [IQR, $42 510-$63 479] vs $69 602 [IQR, $45 631-$96 280]; effect size, 0.534; 95% CI Cohen d, 0.22-0.85).&#13;
&#13;
Conclusions and Relevance: The results of this case-control study suggest that MUPAID for patients who are undergoing complex oncologic HNC surgery is associated with shortened LOS and costs per case as well as decreased complications severity. These results are promising on a patient level in the potential to minimize individual treatment burden, as well as on an institutional and health care system level in the potential significant optimization of surgical outcomes and financial aspects.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-01-27T15:54:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-01-27T15:54:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-01-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2021.4048</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1001/jamaoto.2021.4048</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24023</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24023</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24023</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2168-6181</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2168-619X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>35050322</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp; Neck Surgery</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>American Medical Association</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5136</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T12:14:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Writing by primary school children</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gnach, Aleksandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T14:18:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T14:18:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006-06-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5136</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5136</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5136</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>10th International Conference on Language and Social Psychology (ICLASP 10), Bonn, 15-17 June 2006</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20707</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-10-22T11:59:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Geschlechtsneutrale Prämien für die Motorfahrzeughaftpflichtversicherung?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Frei, Marco</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Geschlecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Motorfahrzeugversicherung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Während in der EU geschlechterspezifische Prämien bei Versicherungsverträgen unzulässig sind, geniessen Schweizer Versicherungsunternehmen den Schutz der Wirtschaftsfreiheit. Die geschlechtsbezogen-unterschiedliche Tarifierung in der Motorfahrzeughaftpflichtversicherung benachteiligt junge Männer und ältere Frauen. Rechtfertigen lässt sich dies in der Privatautonomie des Zivilrechts mit der durch den Vertragsschluss erteilten Zustimmung der Versicherten. Doch auch diese Freiheit hat Schranken, die es der Versicherungsaufsicht ermöglichen, die Versicherten vor nicht begründbaren und erheblichen Ungleichbehandlungen durch die Versicherungsunternehmen zu bewahren.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-10-22T11:59:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-10-22T11:59:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20707</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20707</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20707</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-926X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>HAVE: Haftung und Versicherung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schulthess</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14897</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-14T15:13:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Gesamtsprachenkonzeptionen und Sprachkompetenzen in Lehramtsstudiengängen - das Studium Europa-Lehramt</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Werlen, Erika</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Haunss, J.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>378: Hochschulbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418: Gebrauch der Standardsprache</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-02-01T14:07:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-01T14:07:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14897</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14897</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14897</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3-89528-414-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:9783895284144</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Www.germanistik2001.de : Vorträge des Erlanger Germanistentags</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Deutscher Germanistentag, Erlangen, Deutschland, 30. September - 3. Oktober 2001</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Aisthesis</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22089</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-15T14:11:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1075</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1074</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1076</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wege aus der Lärmschutz-Sackgasse</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fehlmann, Deborah</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Lärm</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lärmschutz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Klangraumgestaltung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Innenentwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>344: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Arbeits-, Sozial-, Bildungs- und Kulturrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Zürcher Gerichtsentscheide von 2020 zum Vollzug der Lärmschutzgesetzgebung legen den Bau von qualitätsvollem Wohnraum in städtischen Gebieten praktisch lahm. Die anstehende Gesetzesrevision birgt die Chance, den gordischen Knoten zu lösen. Das gelingt aber nur, wenn sie qualitätssichernde Bedingungen definiert, statt weiterhin Bauverbote mit Ausnahmen auszusprechen. Lärmschutzfachmann Thomas Gastberger und Nationalrat Beat Flach haben mit Deborah Fehlmann über den Stand der Dinge und mögliche Perspektiven diskutiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-03-15T14:11:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-03-15T14:11:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-01-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22089</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22089</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22089</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0005-6529</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0257-9332</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Werk, Bauen + Wohnen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Verlag Werk</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7624</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-07-06T07:16:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Civil society, civic engagement, and peacebuilding</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Paffenholz, Thania</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Spurk, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Entwicklungszusammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Zivilgesellschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Friedensförderung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>320: Politik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The study provides an overview of the concept of civil society, its history and understanding in different contexts. It elaborates an analytical framework of civil society functions derived from democracy theory, development discourse and case study knowledge, which in turn is applied to the context of peacebuilding. Peacebuilding theory and practice is analyzed in terms of its civil society functions and their validity, scope and content. The results show that the mere existence of and support for civil society does not automatically lead to peacebuilding. A good understanding of civil society?s roles and potential for peacebuilding is required. It is also important to recognize that certain roles and functions of civil society vary depending on the phases of conflict and may not all be equally relevant and effective in all conflict phases.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-06T07:16:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-06T07:16:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://siteresources.worldbank.org/INTCPR/Resources/WP36_web.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7624</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Social Development Papers - Conflict Prevention and Reconstruction</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>46 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>The World Bank</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12457</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-24T12:43:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Reasons why people in Switzerland seek assisted suicide : the view of patients and physicians</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fischer, S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Huber, C.A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Furter, M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Imhof, Lorenz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mahrer Imhof, Romy</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schwarzenegger, C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ziegler, S.J.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bosshard, G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Right-to-die</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Assisted</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Dying</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Suicide</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Background: Assisted suicide is permitted in Switzerland provided that assistance is not motivated by selfish reasons. Suicides are commonly performed with the assistance of right-to-die organisations and the use of a lethal dose of barbiturates prescribed by a participating physician. We examined the reasons physicians provided for writing the prescription and the reasons patients gave for requesting assistance in dying. 

Methods: We analysed all reported cases of assisted suicide that were facilitated by right-to-die organisations between 2001 and 2004 in the city of Zurich, and for which both the medical report and the optional letter written by the decedent providing information on their reasons for seeking assistance in suicide (N = 165). 

Results: The reasons most often reported by physicians (ph), as well as persons who sought help (p), were: pain (ph: 56% of all assisted suicides, p: 58%), need for long-term care (ph: 37%, p: 39%), neurological symptoms (ph: 35%, p: 32%), immobility (ph: 23%, p: 30%) and dyspnoea (ph: 23%, p: 23%). Control of circumstances over death (ph: 12%, p: 39%); loss of dignity (ph: 6%, p: 38%); weakness (ph: 13%, p: 26%); less able to engage in activities that make life enjoyable (ph: 6%, p: 18%); and insomnia and loss of concentration (ph: 4%, p: 13%) were significantly more often mentioned by decedents than by physicians. 

Conclusions: Both prescribing physicians and;patients provided with assistance to die quite often mentioned pain and other concerns, many of which were objectively assessable and related to unbearable suffering or unreasonable disability. Concerns referable to autonomy and individual judgement were more often noted by people seeking help than by the prescribing physicians.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-01T14:59:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-01T14:59:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2741</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.4414/smw.2009.12614</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2741</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.4414/smw.2009.12614</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12457</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12457</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12457</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-7860</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-3997</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0036-7672</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Swiss Medical Weekly</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>EMH Schweizerischer Ärzteverlag</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17261</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T13:39:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wirtschaftsmathematik 2 : Übungen und Lösungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Scherrer, Beat</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hobein, Günter A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stahl, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Renfer, Fritz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>330: Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>510: Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-06-13T15:11:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-06-13T15:11:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17261</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17261</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17261</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7155-9898-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Compendio</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1016</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-18T09:04:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1070</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_11</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The European Writing Survey (EUWRIT): Background, Structure, Implementation, and Some Results</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Chitez, Madalina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kruse, Otto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Castelló, Montserrat</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Akademisches Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Umfrage</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kontrastive Rhetorik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schreibforschung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Academic Writing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Survey</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Contrastive Rhetoric</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Writing Research</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>400: Sprache und Linguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The European Writing Survey (EUWRIT), both the student and faculty versions, reflects the need to systematically gather data on student writing in various institutional and disciplinary contexts. The final version of the survey (status January 2015) includes questions on: personal and demographic data, general questions on writing in the study programme, writing process and feedback, text genres and writing practices, self-evaluation (students) and appreciation (faculty) of the writing skills, conceptions of “good writing”, study competences and writing support. EUWRIT is the result of a long testing and implementation process, which started in 2006. The range of projects in which the survey has been im-plemented is broad and includes assessment of writing skills in study programmes (Environmental Sciences at ETH Zurich; Economics, Journalism and Health at the Zurich University of Applied Sciences), investigations of different stages of student development (Translation Studies at Zurich University of Ap-plied Sciences); comparisons of writing cultures (universities of teacher education in the French, German, and Italian parts of Switzerland); assessments of writing cultures in certain disciplines at different universities (Spain); studies of the writing cultures of a single university (University of Constance, Germany); and comparisons of the genres in different Eastern Europe countries (Macedonia, Romania, Ukraine). The report gives a synthesis of the construction principles of the EUWRIT questionnaire and presents some of the results from the aforementioned studies.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Das European Writing Survey (EUWRIT), in seinen beiden Versionen für Studierende und Lehrende, ist aus der Notwendigkeit zu einer systematischen Sammlung von Daten über studentisches Schreiben in verschiedenen institutionellen und disziplinären Kontexten entstanden. Die letzte Version (Stand Januar 2015) enthält Fragen zu persönlichen und demographischen Variablen, Schreibpraktiken im Studum, Schreibprozess und Feedback, Textgenres, Selbsteinschätzungen (Studierende) und Bedeutsamkeit (Lehrende) studentischer Schreibkompetenz, Vorstellungen von «gutem Schreiben», Selbsteinschätzung (Studierende) von und Bedeutung (Lehrende) allgemeiner Studienkompetenzen, und Bedarf an Unterstützung für das Schreiben. EUWRIT ist Resultat eines langen Test- und Implementierungsprozesses, der im Jahr 2006 begann. Die Spannweite der Projekte, in denen EURWRIT implementiert wurde, ist breit und schliesst ein: Untersuchungen zur Entwicklung von Schreibkompetenzen in Studiengängen (Environmental Sciences, ETH Zurich, Übersetzen und Dolmetschen, ZHAW Winterthur), Vergleich von Studiengängen an einer Hochschule (ZHAW, Studiengänge Management and Law, Journalismus und Gesundheitswissenschaften); Vergleich von Schreibkulturen in unterschiedlichen Sprachregionen (Schreibkulturen an Pädagogischen Hochschulen der französischen, deutschen und italienischen Schweiz); Vergleiche von Schreibkulturen an bestimmten Fakultäten in mehreren Universitäten des Landes (Spanien), Totalerhebungen an einzelnen Hochschulen (Universität Konstanz), und Vergleich von Genrekonzeptionen in geisteswissenschaftlichen Fakultäten osteuropäische Länder (Mazedonien, Rumänien, Ukraine). Der Bericht gibt eine Synthese der Konstruktionsprinzipien des Fragebogens und präsentiert einige zentrale Ergebnisse aus den angesprochenen Studien.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>The European Writing Survey (EUWRIT), both the student and faculty versions, reflects the need to systematically gather data on student writing in various institutional and disciplinary contexts. The final version of the survey (status January 2015) includes questions on: personal and demographic data, general questions on writing in the study programme, writing process and feedback, text genres and writing practices, self-evaluation (students) and appreciation (faculty) of the writing skills, conceptions of “good writing”, study competences and writing support. EUWRIT is the result of a long testing and implementation process, which started in 2006. The range of projects in which the survey has been implemented is broad and includes assessment of writing skills in study programmes (Environmental Sciences at ETH Zurich; Economics, Journalism and Health at the Zurich University of Applied Sciences), investigations of different stages of student development (Translation Studies at Zurich University of Applied Sciences); comparisons of writing cultures (universities of teacher education in the French, German, and Italian parts of Switzerland); assessments of writing cultures in certain disciplines at different universities (Spain); studies of the writing cultures of a single university (University of Constance, Germany); and comparisons of the genres in different Eastern Europe countries (Macedonia, Romania, Ukraine). The report gives a synthesis of the construction principles of the EUWRIT questionnaire and presents some of the results from the aforementioned studies.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2015-09-24T09:20:38Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-09-24T09:20:38Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1016</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1016</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1016</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1016</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1016</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-905745-79-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Working Papers in Applied Linguistics</dc:relation>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/664</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:42:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_53</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Geburt – ein Albtraum : Welche effektiven Therapien bei Tokophobie werden in der evidenzbasierten Literatur beschrieben und welcher Handlungsspielraum kann für die Hebamme diesbezüglich definiert werden?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Friedli, Marianne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:07:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:07:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-664</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-664</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/664</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/664</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/664</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22529</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-28T15:42:37Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Harnessing a hidden power : international corporate communications, translators and translatorial agency</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Massey, Gary</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wieder, Regine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Organization studies</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Translation studies</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Professional translators</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>International corporate communications</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Communicative constituency of organizations (CCO)</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Organizational communication</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Translatorial agency</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Agentic translation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Strategic communication management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Translation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Paraprofessional translators</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.45: Unternehmenskommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Reviewed and adapted presentation of revised paper submitted for cancelled 2020 GEM&amp;L Conference (https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20413).</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Organizations that operate internationally are challenged to manage communication strategically across different cultures and languages. Key competences that help develop and transmit strategic corporate messages aligned with  senders’ intentions and receivers’ cultural embeddedness are not systematically utilized. Translators traditionally possess many of these, but the current mechanistic view of communication management and translation service provision place translators too far downstream in the communication design and production chain.. Recent research from Organization Studies and Translation Studies indicates that translators can be a valuable asset, but they are insufficiently integrated in planning and design. In particular, professional translators’ agency is constrained by self-concept issues and linear, top-down corporate communciation and translation service provision models that inhibit their much-needed iterative, interactive involvement in developing and conveying identities and strategic messages within and for the organizations using theirn services.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-05-27T09:28:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-05-27T09:28:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-05-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-22529</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-22529</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22529</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22529</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22529</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>14th GEM&amp;L International Workshop on Management &amp; Language, Strasbourg (online), 10-12 May 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8988</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:00:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Little red bard : Shakespeare in the realm of animated documentary</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rall, Hannes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Reinhuber, Elke</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Weber, Wibke</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Animated documentary</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Digital animation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Authenticity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Digital journalism</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>800: Literatur und Literaturwissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>This article examines the research and creative process of creating a short animated documentary about the relevance of Shakespeare for digital natives in Singapore. The film mixes animation and live action interviews in various forms to tell its story. The project offers new insights in three ways: First, by uncovering new facts about Shakespeare perception in Singapore. Secondly, by closely examining the specific role of animated layers in the context of adding, enhancing and altering the recorded live action footage for the emerging documentary. Thirdly, by proposing a taxonomy for the animated strategies used.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-15T06:52:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-15T06:52:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8988</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8988</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://confia.ipca.pt/files/confia_2018_proceedings.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8988</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-989-99861-6-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>CONFIA : 2018 International Conference on Illustration and Animation</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>CONFIA 2018 - International Conference on Illustration and Animation, Esposende, Portugal, 13-15 July 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23050</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-03T03:01:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Databooster : ein Katalysator für Serviceinnovation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Meierhofer, Jürg</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Heinatz Bürki, Gundula</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Data science</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Innovation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Data driven services</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Databooster</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die systematische Erfassung und Auswertung von Daten erlaubt es Unternehmen, ihr Dienstleistungsangebot beträchtlich auszubauen; im Maschinenbau beispielsweise im Bereich des vorausschauenden Unterhalts oder der Fernwartung. Damit dies gelingt, brauchen Unternehmen neue Innovationsprozesse. Genau an dieser Stelle setzt der Databooster an.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-09-02T14:02:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-09-02T14:02:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23050</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23050</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23050</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23050</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23050</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1869-3024</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Service Today</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ISB</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7691</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-18T07:15:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Grundlagen, Kompetenzen und Rollen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Negri, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Braun, Birgitta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Werkmann-Karcher, Birgit</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moser, Barbara</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lehren</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lernen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Personalschulung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pädagogische Theorien</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Systemtheorie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lerntheorie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Psychologische Theorien</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Erwachsenenbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pädagogische Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Personalentwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>158: Angewandte Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.3: Personalmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Dieser Abschnitt gibt eine Begriff sklärung und einen Einblick in die lerntheoretische Didaktik, die als Grundlage für das Lernverständnis am IAP Institut für Angewandte Psychologie Zürich dient. Weitere grundlegende didaktische Modelle und wichtige didaktische Prinzipien werden kurz dargestellt. Im zweiten Teil des Abschnitts wird unser Lern- und Bildungsverständnis beschrieben. Unter Didaktik verstehen wir, wie auch Götz &amp; Häfner (2005), die Wissenschaft vom Lehren und Lernen. Inhaltlich sind damit alle für die Organisation von Lehr- und Lernprozessen bestimmenden Faktoren gemeint, unabhängig davon, ob es um schulisches Lernen, Lernen in der Berufsaus- und Weiterbildung oder um Lernen in anderen organisierten Formen geht. Neuere Modelle beschränken sich im Didaktikverständnis nicht auf die Lehr- und Lernprozesse selbst, sondern erweitern dies in Richtung Mikrodidaktik (Durchführung von Lehr- und Lernprozessen) und Makrodidaktik (Planung und Evaluierung von Lehrund Lernprozessen), vgl. Menck &amp; Thoma, 1975; Luhmann, 2002; Götz &amp; Häfner, 2005.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-06T14:01:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-06T14:01:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-12625-3_2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-642-12625-3_2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7691</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7691</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7691</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-642-12624-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-642-12625-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Angewandte Psychologie für die Personalentwicklung : Konzepte und Methoden für Bildungsmanagement, betriebliche Aus- und Weiterbildung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3481</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T10:12:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>A highly available generic billing architecture for heterogenous mobile cloud services</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Harsh, Piyush</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Benz, Konstantin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Trajkovska, Irena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Edmonds, Andrew</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Comi, Paolo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bohnert, Thomas Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Cloud</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Billing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Architecture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Accounting</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Rating, Charging, Billing (RCB) is the fundamental activity that enables a business to generate revenue stream depending on the resource consumption by their consumers. Traditionally, telecom operators have used custom designed, vertically integrated solution for RCB which often results in a complex system that is difficult to adapt to new service offerings. With telecom operator’s desire to capitalize on cloud computing by using their vast amount of infrastructure, the need for a RCB solution that serves the needs of cloudified telcos is needed.&#13;
In this paper we present an approach to implement a generic rating, charging, and billing engine that serves the business and technical needs of both cloudified telecom services and those of cloud service providers. Key to this is a generic accounting process to drive the design of the generic RCB architecture. We show how RCB as a service can be offered catering to not only traditional telco services, the new cloud services they wish and will offer, but packaged cloudified services to the consumers and application developers as well. Finally, we detail how our architecture can be distributed and key services replicated to ensure high-availability.&#13;
The end result of this paper is a solution that can enable telecom service providers to leverage the rapidly growing and accelerating cloud service market.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-03-07T14:11:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-07T14:11:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3481</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3481</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3481</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>World Congress in Computer Science, Computer Engineering, and Applied Computing, Las Vegas, USA, 21-24 July 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22126</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-19T08:04:37Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Integration of biogas systems into the energy system : technical aspects of flexible plant operation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Liebetrau, Jan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kornatz, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Baier, Urs</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wall, David</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Murphy, Jerry</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Murphy, Jerry</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Bioenergy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Biogas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Flexibilisation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Energy system</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333.79: Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Biogas is a versatile energy carrier which can be used to produce electricity, heat and after upgrading serve all functions of natural gas, including transport. Biogas systems are highly scalable in their energy output according to the demand from the particular energy sector. The flexibility of biogas systems can facilitate electricity production at a dynamic schedule to match an electricity demand profile, while facilitating voltage and grid stability. As a decentralised component of the overall energy system biogas systems can function as an infrastructure hub for local energy consumers in rural areas. Biogas can play an essential role (together with PV and wind) as part of a virtual power plant in local distribution energy grids. Biogas systems can operate as a biological battery in coupling the electricity and gas grids using surplus electricity to produce hydrogen to react with biogenic CO2 in biogas producing biomethane and increasing the output of biomethane (typically by 70 %). Innovation and ingenuity will be required of biogas operators in future energy systems. This report highlights how the operator can match biogas supply and demand for energy as electricity, heat or transport biofuel across the larger future energy system.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-03-19T08:04:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-03-19T08:04:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://task37.ieabioenergy.com/technical-brochures.html</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22126</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-910154-76-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-910154-77-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>35 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>IEA Bioenergy</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19167</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-23T14:48:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Architektur : ein partizipatives Stück Theater</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Muri Koller, Gabriela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>720: Architektur</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-01-23T14:48:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-01-23T14:48:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:101:1-2018092513402445277804</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19167</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-95749-133-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Rimini Protokoll: Staat 1–4 : Phänomene der Postdemokratie</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Verlag Theater der Zeit</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6120</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T10:32:39Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Peercoaching</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Steinebach, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schrenk, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Kebabplus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>PPC</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Peerkultur</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>158: Angewandte Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>303: Soziale Prozesse</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-25T12:55:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-25T12:55:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013-11-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6120</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6120</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6120</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Jahrestagung Kebab+, Zürich, 28. November 2013</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/475</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:42:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_52</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Aktiv gegen Diabetes : Einfluss von körperlicher Aktivität bei Kindern und Jugendlichen auf die glykämische Kontrolle, gemessen am HbA1c-Wert</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Geiger, Damaris</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:05:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:05:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-475</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-475</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/475</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/475</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/475</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10075</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-24T14:12:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Seven dimensions of corporate identity</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Melewar, T.C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Karaosmanoglu, Elif</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Corporate identity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Corporate image</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Corporate strategy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>IMM</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>659: Werbung und Öffentlichkeitsarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Purpose: This paper investigates what organisations perceive as the essential components of corporate identity concept and their contents. It proposes an operational definition of corporate identity on the basis of the practitioners' views.

Design/methodology/approach: The information was gathered through 32 in‐depth interviews with managers from different organisations (mainly multinational companies) and an analysis of corporate literature and web sites. The initial analysis is based on a multidisciplinary categorisation developed by the first author, which facilitated the systematic analysis of a wide range of components (e.g. corporate communication, corporate design, corporate culture etc.) associated with corporate identity.

Findings: The study shows that there is a considerable divergence in opinions concerning the fundamental components of corporate identity among practitioners. Most interviewees heavily associated identity with the areas of corporate design, communication, behaviour and strategy whereas there was no unanimous agreement as to whether or not corporate culture was a product or determinant of corporate identity.

Research limitations/implications: Developing sub‐items and their measures for each dimension presented in the proposed definition and examining the possible relationships between them might be the further step. Also additional empirical research which considers consequences of corporate identity management in relation to company performance indicators could enhance overall understanding of the concept.

Practical implications: Senior company management can use the categorisation discussed in this paper as a starting point for development of corporate identity management strategies.

Originality/value: Recategorisation of Melewar's corporate identity dimensions, which help define corporate identity concept in measurable terms.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-04T11:48:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-04T11:48:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1108/03090560610670025</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1108/03090560610670025</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10075</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10075</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10075</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0309-0566</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>European Journal of Marketing</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Emerald</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14283</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-01-10T13:22:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Generalversammlung (Art. 698-706b)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tanner, Brigitte</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Vergütungsverordnung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gesellschaftsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Rechnungslegung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Aktienrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-01-10T13:22:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-10T13:22:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14283</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14283</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14283</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7255-7302-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Personengesellschaften und Aktiengesellschaft : Vergütungsverordnung : Art. 530-771 OR</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Handkommentar zum Schweizer Privatrecht</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schulthess</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21376</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-04T12:56:32Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Digital competence revolution and human resource development in the United Kingdom and Switzerland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hubschmid-Vierheilig, Elena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rohrer, Monika</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mitsakis, Fotios</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Digital Competence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>HRD</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>UK</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Switzerland</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.3: Personalmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In today’s digitalised world, the number of routine/low-skilled jobs has been reduced with rising demand for digitally equipped graduates/employees. Technological advancements heavily impact the way people work while most recent socio-political and demographic changes (e.g. ‘Brexit’, economic instability, higher education reforms, generation attitude changes and a pandemic crisis) increase the need for critical insights on how digital competences of the workforce can improve and sustain business competitiveness. While some organisations remain reluctant to foster their workforce’s digital qualifications, many view digitalisation as an opportunity to enhance employees’ skillsets with company-specific competences for competitive advantage, further being supported by educational institutions which offer tailored human resource development (HRD) programmes (Gartner Co, Gartner identifies three megatrends that will drive digital business into the next decade, 2017). As the UK and Switzerland are non-EU members they are not in charge of implementing the European Digital Strategy; therefore, the chapter aims to describe and compare their ‘special way’ regarding HRD education provision in the era of digitalisation to inform HRD professionals and policymakers on possible future actions.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-01-21T13:41:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-01-21T13:41:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-52410-4_3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-030-52410-4_3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21376</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21376</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21376</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-030-52409-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-030-52410-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>The Future of HRD, Volume I : Innovation and Technology</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Palgrave Macmillan</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9220</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-20T06:25:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Gesamte Materialanalytik unter einem Dach</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Peikert, Gregor</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Composites</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>620.11: Werkstoffe</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-08-17T13:20:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-17T13:20:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2366-8024</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Carbon Composites Magazin</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Carbon Composites</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7320</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-02-21T12:27:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Tagungsband Internationales Forum Mechatronik 2007</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>van de Venn, Hans Wernher</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>620: Ingenieurwesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-26T13:01:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-26T13:01:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Proceedings</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7320</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7320</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7320</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-033-01192-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Internationales Forum Mechatronik 2007, Winterthur, 12.-13. September 2007</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>60 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14487</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-20T09:51:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Genomes reveal marked differences in the adaptive evolution between orangutan species</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mattle-Greminger, Maja P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bilgin Sonay, Tugce</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nater, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pybus, Marc</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Desai, Tariq</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>de Valles, Guillem</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Casals, Ferran</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Scally, Aylwyn</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bertranpetit, Jaume</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marques-Bonet, Tomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>van Schaik, Carel P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Anisimova, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Krützen, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Cognitive evolution</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Demographic history</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Great apes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Local adaptation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pleistocene glaciations</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pongo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>572: Biochemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Integrating demography and adaptive evolution is pivotal to understanding the evolutionary history and conservation of great apes. However, little is known about the adaptive evolution of our closest relatives, in particular if and to what extent adaptions to environmental differences have occurred. Here, we used whole-genome sequencing data from critically endangered orangutans from North Sumatra (Pongo abelii) and Borneo (P. pygmaeus) to investigate adaptive responses of each species to environmental differences during the Pleistocene.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-01-22T14:42:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-22T14:42:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4776</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1186/s13059-018-1562-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4776</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1186/s13059-018-1562-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14487</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14487</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14487</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1465-6906</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1474-760X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1465-6914</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>30428903</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Genome Biology</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>BioMed Central</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24764</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-04-09T03:03:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_51</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Voneinander lernen –  Peer-Interventionen bei Kindern mit Autismus-Spektrum-Störung : verschiedene Ansätze zur Peer-Schulung und deren Umsetzung in der Ergotherapie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mönch, Cécile</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zgraggen, Larissa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Autism spectrum disorder</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Partnering for Change Model</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Social participation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Children occupational therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Peer-intervention</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615.8515: Ergotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618.92: Pädiatrie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Darstellung des Themas: Kinder mit einer Autismus-Spektrum-Störung (ASS) sind oft in ihrer sozialen Partizipation eingeschränkt. Die Effektivität von Peer-Interventionen, um Kinder mit ASS bei Interaktionen zu unterstützen, wurde mehrfach bewiesen. Deren Umsetzung im Alltag und wie die Zusammenarbeit der verschiedenen Akteure sichergestellt werden soll, ist jedoch in der schweizerischen Praxis der Ergotherapie noch kaum verankert.&#13;
&#13;
Ziel: Die Bachelorarbeit zeigt auf, wie Peers angeleitet werden können, die soziale Partizipation eines Kindes mit ASS zu fördern, und wie Ergotherapeuten und Ergotherapeutinnen die Zusammenarbeit zwischen Kindern, Lehrpersonen und Eltern dabei unterstützen können.&#13;
&#13;
Methode: Mit einer systematischen Literaturrecherche wurden sechs Hauptstudien ausgewählt und kritisch gewürdigt. Relevante Ergebnisse wurden einander gegenübergestellt und zwecks Umsetzung in die Ergotherapie in das Modell Partnering for Change eingebettet sowie mit weiterer Literatur diskutiert.&#13;
&#13;
Relevante Ergebnisse: Die Arten von Peer-Interventionen sind vielfältig und es kommen verschiedene Ansätze zum Einsatz, um Peers zu schulen. Es werden unterschiedliche Auswahlkriterien für Peers festgelegt, deren Einfluss umstritten bleibt. &#13;
&#13;
Schlussfolgerung: Einzelne Ansätze lassen sich kombinieren. Die Zusammenarbeit zwischen den beteiligten Akteuren ist essenziell, um längerfristig positive Effekte zu erreichen. Dabei kann der Ergotherapeut oder die Ergotherapeutin die Koordination und Schulung übernehmen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-04-08T10:38:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-04-08T10:38:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-24764</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-24764</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24764</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24764</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24764</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>146 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1263</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T13:56:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_22</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1238</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Der Einfluss islamistischer Terroranschläge auf Tourismus und Wirtschaft in betroffenen Staaten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wüthrich, Pascal</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>338: Produktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Angesichts des Aufstiegs des „Islamischen Staates“ und der Terroranschläge von Paris im vergangenen Jahr gewinnt der islamistische Terrorismus an Aktualität wie seit 9/11 nicht mehr. Die mediale Berichterstattung nimmt immer grössere Ausmasse an, wovon hauptsächlich die Terrororganisationen profitieren. Wiederholt wurden in den vergangen Jahren auch Touristen als Terrorziele ausgewählt und angegriffen, weil dies eine besonders hohe Aufmerksamkeit der Medien und der Weltöffentlichkeit garantiert. Zusätzlich sollen Tourismus und Wirtschaft in den betroffenen Staaten, meist Schwellenländer, nachhaltig geschädigt werden, was gemäss Medienberichten auch gelingt.
In der vorliegenden Bachelorarbeit wird deshalb untersucht, ob sich islamistische Terroranschläge tatsächlich auf Tourismus und Wirtschaft in betroffenen Staaten auswirken. Als Grundlage für die Untersuchung dienen elf Terrorattacken in Ägypten, Indonesien und Tunesien, welche sich explizit gegen die jeweilige Tourismusindustrie richteten. Um die Folgen der Anschläge für diese Staaten beurteilen zu können, werden die internationalen Touristenankünfte, die Tourismuseinnahmen, die ausländischen Direktinvestitionen, das Bruttoinlandsprodukt und die Arbeitslosigkeit zwischen 1994 und 2016 analysiert. Zur statistischen Überprüfung der Auswirkungen werden bei Jahreszahlen Korrelationsanalysen durchgeführt, bei Monatszahlen werden Mittelwertvergleiche (T-Tests) und Regressionsanalysen herangezogen.
Es hat sich gezeigt, dass sich die internationalen Touristenankünfte in den drei bis sechs Monaten nach den Anschlägen in allen untersuchten Fällen negativer entwickelten als in den Vergleichsjahren zuvor und danach. Im Gegensatz zum Vorgehen in anderen Studien wurden in dieser Arbeit für die Feststellung des negativen Effekts einzelne Terroranschläge anstelle von Durchschnittswerten betrachtet. Dies ist wesentlich aussagekräftiger, da Durchschnittswerte aufgrund der langen Betrachtungsperioden stärker durch andere wirtschaftliche und politische Ereignisse beeinflusst werden. In den eigenen Untersuchungen wurde mehrmals beobachtet, dass solche nichtterroristischen Ereignisse zu einer negativen Entwicklung der Touristenankünfte führten. Die vorliegende Arbeit ist wohl auch die erste, welche Veränderungen der Ankünfte gegenüber Vergleichsjahren bei den Berechnungen berücksichtigte und auf diese Weise saisonale Einflüsse eliminierte.
Im Unterschied zu den Touristenankünften war es aufgrund fehlender Monatsdaten unmöglich, potenzielle Auswirkungen der Terroranschläge auf die Tourismuseinnahmen und die Wirtschaftsindikatoren (ausländische Direktinvestitionen, BIP, Arbeitslosigkeit) mittels Regressionsmodellen statistisch zu belegen.
Für zukünftige Studien wird empfohlen, sich auf einzelne Terrorereignisse zu beschränken und keine Durchschnittswerte zu berechnen, da sich die Folgen je nach Zeitpunkt, Art und Schwere eines Anschlags stark unterscheiden. Um aussagekräftige Resultate zu erhalten, sind möglichst kurze Betrachtungshorizonte und Berechnungen mit Monatszahlen anzustreben. Zudem sollten Terroranschläge stets im Kontext der Zeit und von nichtterroristischen Ereignissen untersucht werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2017-04-10T09:48:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-04-10T09:48:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1261</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1261</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1263</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1263</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1263</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>94 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15308</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-24T14:10:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Glaciimonas frigoris sp. nov., a psychrophilic bacterium isolated from ancient Siberian permafrost sediment, and emended description of the genus Glaciimonas</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Margesin, Rosa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zhang, De-Chao</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Frasson, David</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brouchkov, Anatoli</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Glaciimonas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Siberian permafrost sediment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>New species</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Psychrophilic bacterium</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>570: Biologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The bacterial strain N1-38T was isolated from ancient Siberian permafrost sediment. The strain was Gram-reaction-negative, motile by gliding, rod-shaped and psychrophilic, and showed good growth over a temperature range of - 5 to 25 °C. Phylogenetic analysis of 16S rRNA gene sequences revealed that strain N1-38T was most closely related to members of the genus Glaciimonas and shared the highest 16S rRNA gene sequence similarities with the type strains of Glaciimonas alpina (99.3 %), Glaciimonas immobilis (98.9 %) and Glaciimonas singularis (96.5 %). The predominant cellular fatty acids of strain N1-38T were summed feature 3 (C16 : 1ω7c and/or iso-C15 : 0 2-OH), C16 : 0 and C18 : 1ω7c. The major respiratory quinone was ubiquinone 8 and the major polar lipids were phosphatidylethanolamine and diphosphatidylglycerol. The genomic DNA G+C content was 53.0 mol%. Combined data of phenotypic, phylogenetic and DNA–DNA relatedness studies demonstrated that strain N1-38T represents a novel species of the genus Glaciimonas, for which the name Glaciimonas frigoris sp. nov. is proposed. The type strain is N1-38T ( = LMG 28868T = CCOS 838T). An emended description of the genus Glaciimonas is also provided.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-13T14:45:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-13T14:45:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1099/ijsem.0.000783</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1099/ijsem.0.000783</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15308</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15308</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15308</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1466-5026</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1466-5034</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>26597157</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>International Journal of Systematic and Evolutionary Microbiology</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Microbiology Society</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18310</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-28T09:51:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1075</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1074</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1076</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Vertiefung der Demokratie? Warum Schweizer Gemeinden neue Formen der Bürgerbeteiligung einführen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kübler, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rochat, Philippe E.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Koch, Philippe</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>van der Heiden, Nico</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>320: Politik</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-09-28T09:51:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-09-28T09:51:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18310</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18310</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18310</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7255-7206-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Demokratie in der Gemeinde</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Schriften zur Demokratieforschung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schulthess</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16679</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T11:00:56Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Passive Sensoren : drahtlos versorgt und abgefragt</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Küng, Roland</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Philipp, Sarah</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>RFID</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sensoren</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kopplung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Magnetfeld</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>006: Spezielle Computerverfahren</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Sensoren, die ohne eigene Stromversorgung Messungen vornehmen und berührungslos ihre Daten an eine Auswertestation übermitteln, werden dort eingesetzt, wo es nach dem Einbau keinen Zugang zum Sensor mehr gibt oder eine Verkabelung ausgeschlossen ist. Der Artikel beschreibt eine Sensorsystem, indem die Energie induktiv bei der RFID-Frequenz 13,56 MHz mit wenigen Zentimeter grossen Loop-Antennen übertragen wird.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-04-17T14:43:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-17T14:43:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.elektroniknet.de/elektronik/automation/drahtlos-versorgt-und-abgefragt-28383.html</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16679</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0013-5658</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Elektronik - Fachmedium für industrielle Anwender und Entwickler</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>WEKA</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7715</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-11T07:31:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Talent tauschen : von der Nachbarschaftshilfe zur überregionalen Währung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Baur, Nicole Anja</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Tauschen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gemeinschaftszentrum</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gemeinwesenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>361: Sozialarbeit und Sozialhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-07-09T11:59:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-09T11:59:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3846</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3846</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7715</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7715</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7715</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1422-8432</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>SozialAktuell</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>AvenirSocial</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13015</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-11-19T10:02:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Analyse der Leistungsfelder des Zentrums Inselhof</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gavez, Silvia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Redmann, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stohler, Renate</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-11-19T10:02:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-19T10:02:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13015</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13015</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13015</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Zentrum Inselhof</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/404</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:43:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_52</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Der Vergleich verschiedener Mobilisationstechniken bei der Behandlung von Patienten mit Frozen Shoulder</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Meier, Désirée</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:04:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:04:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-404</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-404</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/404</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/404</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/404</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3786</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T15:30:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1075</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1074</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1076</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Komplexe Einheit : das Einfamilienhaus im periurbanen Umfeld</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kurath, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Einfamilienhaus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Masterstudio</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nachhaltigkeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Urban landscape</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>728: Wohnbauten</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-14T13:00:21Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-14T13:00:21Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3786</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3786</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3786</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1010-4089</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Archithese</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Niggli</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16011</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-04T12:57:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Personalentwicklung für Hochschule und Forschung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fisch, Rudolf</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.3: Personalmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-03-13T13:22:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-13T13:22:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16011</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16011</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16011</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3932306716</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Human Resources in Hochschule und Forschung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Lemmens</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11673</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T10:12:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Der Klang der Landschaft</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Christ, Yvonne Therese</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Landschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Zug</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>712: Landschaftsgestaltung (Landschaftsdesign)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-10-11T13:31:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-11T13:31:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.anthos.ch/app/download/5144659010/4.10_Klang+der+Landschaft.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11673</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0003-5424</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Anthos - Zeitschrift für Landschaftsarchitektur</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Bund Schweizer Landschaftsarchitekten und Landschaftsarchitektinnen</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6333</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-13T15:06:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Erfolgskriterien für Public Storytelling in der Prävention</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stücheli-Herlach, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Politische Kommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Public Storytelling</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>320: Politik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Kommunikation leistet mehr als „Sachinformation“: Publika knüpfen Zusammenhänge, wenn sie wahrnehmen, beurteilen, bewerten und vermitteln. Diese Sinnproduktion heisst Public Storytelling. In letzter Zeit war Prävention in der Schweiz eine „institutionelle Politikgeschichte“. Sie muss zu einer Schweizer Erfolgsgeschichte werden. Solche Strategien entstehen in organisierten mehrstufigen Entwicklungsprozessen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-05-31T14:10:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-31T14:10:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6333</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6333</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6333</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Mit Prävention überzeugen, Präventionstag des Fachverband Sucht, Aarau, 5. September 2013</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20348</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-29T13:28:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Schädlich für Beziehungsaufbau oder wichtiger Draht zur Aussenwelt?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Koch, Ramona</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gemperle, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>von Wyl, Agnes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Braune-Krickau, Katrin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schneebeli, Larissa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pehlke-Milde, Jessica</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Das Smartphone ist für viele im Alltag ein ständiger Begleiter. Es ermöglicht schnellen Zugang zu Informationen, vereinfacht die Kontaktpflege mit Freunden und Familie und erleichtert durch unzählige Anwendungen die Alltagsorganisation. Doch wie verändert sich die Smartphone-Nutzung der Frauen, wenn sie Mütter werden? Hebammen und Psychologinnen der Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften forschten nach und deckten Beratungsbedarf auf.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-08-17T08:01:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-08-17T08:01:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-20348</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-20348</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20348</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20348</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20348</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Obstetrica</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Schweizerischer Hebammenverband</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3503</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T13:10:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>In vitro, in vivo, in silico : Modellbildung und Computersimulation als komplementäre Labormethode</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Scheidegger, Stephan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Füchslin, Rudolf Marcel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>000: Allgemeines und Wissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-07T14:57:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-07T14:57:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3503</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3503</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3503</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0379-2722</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Mitteilungen der Aargauischen Naturforschenden Gesellschaft</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Aargauische Naturforschende Gesellschaft</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24436</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-02T14:31:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>A multi-component intervention (NEXpro) reduces neck pain-related work productivity loss : an RCT among Swiss office workers</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Aegerter, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Deforth, Manja</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Volken, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Johnston, Venerina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Luomajoki, Hannu</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dressel, Holger</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dratva, Julia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ernst, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Distler, Oliver</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brunner, Beatrice</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sjøgaard, Gisela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Melloh, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Elfering, Achim</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>331: Arbeitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>613: Persönliche Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Oral presentation</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Background: Neck pain is common among office workers and negatively influences productivity. This study aimed to investigate the effect of a multi-component intervention, combining current best evidence interventions, on neck pain-related work productivity loss among Swiss office workers.&#13;
&#13;
Methods: In this cluster randomized controlled trial, office workers aged 18-65 years and without serious neck-related health problems were recruited from two organisations. A biostatistician randomly assigned participants to the intervention cluster. The 12-week multi-component intervention included neck exercises, health-promotion information, and workstation ergonomics. The primary outcome of neck pain-related work productivity loss (absenteeism, presenteeism) was measured using the Work Productivity and Activity Impairment Questionnaire and expressed as percentages of working time. Additionally, we reported the weekly monetary value of neck pain-related work productivity loss. Data was analysed on an intention-to-treat basis using a generalized linear mixed-effects model.&#13;
&#13;
Results: Participants were recruited between Oct 28, 2019, and Dec 20, 2019. Data from 120 participants were analysed with 517 observations. At baseline, the mean age was 43.7 years (SD 9.8 years), 71.7 % of participants were female (N = 86), about 80 % (N = 95) reported mild to moderate neck pain, and neck pain-related work productivity loss was 12 % of working time (absenteeism: 1.2 %, presenteeism: 10.8 %). We found an effect of our multi-component intervention on neck pain-related work productivity loss, with a marginal predicted mean reduction of 2.8 percentage points (-0.27; 95 % CI: -0.54 to -0.001, p = 0.049). Weekly saved costs were CHF 27.40 per participant. One adverse event occurred.&#13;
&#13;
Interpretation: Our study provides evidence for the effectiveness of a multi-component intervention to reduce neck pain-related work productivity loss with implications for health care providers, employers, employees, and policymakers.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-03-02T14:31:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-03-02T14:31:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-02-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24436</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24436</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24436</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>7th International Conference "Work an Health", virtual, 10-11 February, 2022</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4499</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T10:36:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Black box evaluation for operational information retrieval applications</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Braschler, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Imhof, Melanie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rietberger, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>IE</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>INIT</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>020: Bibliotheks- und Informationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The black box application evaluation methodology described in this tutorial is applicable to a broad range of operational information retrieval (IR) applications. Contrary to popular, traditional IR evaluation approaches that are limited to measure the IR system performance on a test collection, the black box evaluation methodology considers an IR application in its entirety: the underlying system, the corresponding document collection, and its configuration/application layer. A comprehensive set of quality criteria is used to estimate the user’s perception of the application. Scores are assigned as a weighted average of results from tests that evaluate individual aspects. The methodology was validated in a small evaluation campaign. An analysis of this campaign shows a correlation between the testers’ perception of the applications and the evaluation scores. Moreover, functional weaknesses of the tested IR applications can be identified and then systematically targeted.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-03-29T08:33:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-29T08:33:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-54798-0_9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-642-54798-0_9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4499</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4499</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4499</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-642-54797-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Bridging between information retrieval and databases</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Lecture Notes in Computer Science</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20225</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-08T06:36:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Von der Bank überrascht ...</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hohgardt, Holger</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Grimm, Selina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cong, Tra Mi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>332.1: Banken</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-07-03T20:22:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-07-03T20:22:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20225</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20225</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20225</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Der Schweizerische Hauseigentümer</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>HEV Schweiz</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24539</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-11T04:03:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Extraction of transforming sequences and sentence histories from writing process data : a first step towards linguistic modeling of writing</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mahlow, Cerstin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ulasik, Malgorzata Anna</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tuggener, Don</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Writing process</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Keystroke-logging</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Transforming sequence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Text history</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sentence history</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Written text production</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Linguistic modeling</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Online first, part of special issue "Methods for understanding writing process by analysis of writing timecourse"&#13;
&#13;
Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenzen.ch)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Producing written texts is a non-linear process: in contrast to speech, writers are free to change already written text at any place at any point in time. Linguistic considerations are likely to play an important role, but so far, no linguistic models of the writing process exist. We present an approach for the analysis of writing processes with a focus on linguistic structures based on the novel concepts of transforming sequences, text history, and sentence history. The processing of raw keystroke logging data and the application of natural language processing tools allows for the extraction and filtering of product and process data to be stored in a hierarchical data structure. This structure is used to re-create and visualize the genesis and history for a text and its individual sentences. Focusing on sentences as primary building blocks of written language and full texts, we aim to complement established writing process analyses and, ultimately, to interpret writing timecourse data with respect to linguistic structures. To enable researchers to explore this view, we provide a fully functional implementation of our approach as an open-source software tool and visualizations of the results. We report on a small scale exploratory study in German where we used our tool. The results indicate both the feasibility of the approach and that writers actually revise on a linguistic level. The latter confirms the need for modeling written text production from the perspective of linguistic structures beyond the word level.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-03-10T15:28:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-03-10T15:28:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-01-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11145-021-10234-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-24539</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/s11145-021-10234-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-24539</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24539</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24539</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24539</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0922-4777</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1573-0905</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Reading and Writing</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23304</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-12T11:03:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Video production and distribution platform in Swiss sports teams : an analysis of acceptance and willingness to pay</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hüttermann, Marcel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Haefliger, Fabian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stallone, Valerio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Acceptance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Distribution platform</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Video production</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Willingness-to-Pay</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>700: Künste und Unterhaltung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Swisscom Asport (“Asport”) has set itself the target of covering the entire video process from production to distribution. Its services should be affordable not only for professional sports clubs but also for their amateur counterparts. Despite limited resources, clubs want to increase their attractiveness through new technologies and meet members' needs. This paper examines the factors that lead to the acceptance of Asport services by sports clubs. In addition, the willingness to pay for these services is evaluated. Pricing is critical to success in innovation and also because of the limited financial resources of sports clubs. Based on the literature research, a conceptual model was developed based on the unified theory of acceptance and use of technology model (UTAUT), tested using an online survey of Swiss amateur football clubs, and evaluated using regression analysis. The study findings show that social environment exerts the strongest influence on behavioral intention, defined as “acceptance” in this paper. Furthermore, the two independent variables, performance expectancy and effort expectancy, have a significant effect on user acceptance. In contrast to the original model (UTAUT), this paper demonstrates the direct influence of attitude to use. Of the independent variables, facilitating conditions have an additional effect on attitude to use. The results demonstrate that it is not acceptance but attitude to use that influences willingness to pay. An in-depth evaluation of willingness to pay shows that the optimal price point is 83.3% lower than the price offered by the company; however, there are budget-dependent variations in the assessment.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-10-14T16:19:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-10-14T16:19:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-09-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.3389/fspor.2021.722043</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23304</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.3389/fspor.2021.722043</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23304</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23304</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23304</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23304</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2624-9367</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Frontiers in Sports and Active Living</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Frontiers Research Foundation</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19320</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-30T13:21:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Systems for coupling and sampling</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schirmer, Cedric</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rothe, Sebastian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jenness, Ernest</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eibl, Dieter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>660.6: Biotechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-01-30T13:21:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-01-30T13:21:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1002/9781119477891.ch5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1002/9781119477891.ch5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19320</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19320</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19320</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-119-47783-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-119-47777-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Single-use technology in biopharmaceutical manufacture</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Wiley</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3664</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-07T13:26:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Customer-oriented prosocial service behaviors and their role in influencing perceived service quality</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Coenen, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>IFM</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-09T08:54:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-09T08:54:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2001</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3664</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3664</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3664</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Arizona State University</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6220</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T12:56:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>«Qualifizierte Services in Geldwerte umsetzen?!?»</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Honegger, Franziska</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hofer, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Hospital</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.11: Krankenhäuser und verwandte Einrichtungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-29T14:06:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-29T14:06:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>4. Fachkonferenz - Strukturen des Spitals der Zukunft, Luzern, 16.-18. Oktober 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7542</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-26T07:17:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Genetische Vielfalt in Wildpflanzen-Samenmischungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Aavik, Tsipe</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bosshard, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Edwards, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Holderegger, Rolf</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Billeter, Regula</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>630: Landwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-07-03T14:05:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-03T14:05:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.agrarforschungschweiz.ch/archiv_11de.php?id_artikel=1942</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7542</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1663-7909</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1663-7852</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Agrarforschung Schweiz</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Agroscope</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17329</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T14:06:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>We don't need no statusfaction?!</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hari, Jürg J.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rawitzer, Heike</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Status</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Satisfaction</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Marketing Conference</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Statusfaction</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Non-conscious, automatic and unobserved processes in memory have a high impact in the field of the status and conspicuous consumption, especially in the prestige-seeking consumer behaviour. There is little willingness of the consumers to admit that their purchase is motivated by personal status considerations. This study demonstrates that implicit measures in the field of status consumption add incremental value beyond explicit measures.&#13;
Our participants were selected for their presumed very strong need for status, or their strong rejection of status. The selection bias makes the explicit results much less useful and they only confirm the selection. The strong IAT effects make this study however interesting. In the present study the IAT scores have a mean of 0.49 ± 0.46 seconds. This is a surprisingly high level indicating a very strong preference for high status and prestige. It is not surprising that males in the financial service sector prefer status and prestige both implicitly and explicitly. And so do their female counterparts. But also females working in the social sector that explicitly rejected status symbols (such as expensive cars), implicitly preferred status and prestige (but not the males).</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-06-19T13:44:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-06-19T13:44:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17329</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17329</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17329</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Academy of Marketing Conference 2013, Cardiff, Wales, 8-11 July 2013</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15621</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-18T07:15:51Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Uses of corporate blogs</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hallier, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Onlinemarketing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Blog</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-02-22T14:03:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-22T14:03:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15621</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15621</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15621</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-0-415-96500-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-0-203-93316-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-0-415-96501-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Marketing the e-Business</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Routledge e-business series</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Routledge</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21345</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-21T08:43:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>"Flex Office" in Spitälern : flexible Arbeitsumgebungen in Spitälern umzusetzen ist herausfordernd, aber notwendig</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lange, Stefanie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Arbeitsplätze im Spital</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Workplaces in Healthcare</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.11: Krankenhäuser und verwandte Einrichtungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.3: Personalmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-01-21T08:43:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-01-21T08:43:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.heimeundspitaeler.ch/archiv-redaktion/2017/04-oktober/flex-office-in-spitaelern</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21345</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2296-3979</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Heime und Spitäler</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>B2B Swiss Medien</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16731</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:00:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Erlesenes aus der Schweiz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Keller Paul, Jörg</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Paul, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Weiterbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Landeskunde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>DACHL</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>DaF/DaZ</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418: Gebrauch der Standardsprache</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>430: Deutsch</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-04-18T06:50:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-18T06:50:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16731</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16731</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16731</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>DACHL-Seminar 2015, Winterthur 09. Juli 2015 und Leipzig, 27. Juli 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/74</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-20T09:49:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Mehrsprachigkeit an universitären Bildungsinstitutionen: Arbeitssprache Englisch im Hochschulfachunterricht</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Studer, Patrick</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pelli-Ehrensperger, Annabarbara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kelly, Paul</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Hochschulunterricht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Emi-Unterricht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Englisch</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sprachplanung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>English</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>English-Medium Instruction</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Higher Education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Language Planning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>420: Englisch</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Dieser Artikel bietet einen Überblick zur Einführung von englischsprachigem Fachunterricht an Hochschulen (English-Medium Instruction, EMI). Die Rundschau ist eingebettet in Erläuterungen zu bildungs- und sprachpolitischen Entwicklungen in Europa. In einem Exkurs werden Erkenntnisse zum positiven Potenzial integrierten Sachfach- und Fremdsprachenlernens auf Primar- und Sekundarstufe vorgestellt. Das Hauptaugenmerk gilt der Tertiärstufe. Herausforderungen an alle Beteiligten werden aufgegriffen und auf der Basis von Ergebnissen bisheriger Studien diskutiert.&#13;
&#13;
Die tertiäre Stufe mit ihren spezifischen Anforderungen und Unterrichtsformen im Zusammenhang mit englischsprachigem Fachunterricht (EMI) steht für die Autoren im Fokus. Der Artikel zeichnet die Verbreitung und Tendenzen der Einführung von EMI im nicht-anglophonen Europa und in der Schweiz nach und zeigt auf, welche Probleme sich bei einer Umstellung auf EMI-Unterricht stellen. Differenziert wird dabei zwischen Ansprüchen an Dozierende und Anforderungen an Studierende. Im Zusammenhang mit den Dozierenden stehen vor allem folgende Themen zur Diskussion: ihr Kompetenzprofil, die Lernendenorientierung und Interaktivität im Unterrichtsverhalten als Schlüsselgrössen im EMI-Unterricht; des Weiteren der disziplinenspezifische EMI-Unterricht und die Zusammenarbeit von Sprach- und Fachdozierenden. Im Hinblick auf die Studierenden werden folgende Punkte kritisch beleuchtet: Ihre Englischkompetenzen beim Studieneintritt und, als Folge davon, Auswirkungen auf das Fachlernen. Abschliessend werden in vier Zielfeldern Hypothesen im Bezug auf EMI im Schweizer Hochschulkontext formuliert: 1) Kompetenzentwicklung Studierende, 2) Kompetenzprofil Dozierende, 3) Lehr-Lerndiskurse und 4) Hochschulentwicklung und Sprachplanung. Für eine erfolgreiche Einführung wie auch bei der Beforschung von EMI-Unterricht gilt es diese Zielfelder zu berücksichtigen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2015-07-10T12:02:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-07-10T12:02:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-74</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-74</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/74</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/74</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/74</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-905745-28</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>ISBB Working Papers</dc:relation>
          <dc:format>38 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2272</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-15T04:00:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Relationship between personality and psychopathology in a longitudinal community study : a test of the predisposition model</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hengartner, Michael Pascal</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ajdacic-Gross, Vladeta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wyss, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Angst, Jules</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rössler, Wulf</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Aetiopathology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Epidemiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Neuroticism</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Personality</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Psychopathology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>155: Differentielle Psychologie und Entwicklungspsychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616.89: Psychische Störungen, klinische Psychologie und Psychiatrie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenzen.ch)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Mounting evidence supports the notion that personality is crucial in the aetiopathology of common mental disorders, but studies that allow for aetiological conclusions are lacking. The aim of the present study was thus to provide a test of the predisposition model. We analysed data from the Zurich Cohort Study, a 30-year longitudinal epidemiological community study of an adult cohort (n = 591) from 1979 to 2008. Personality was assessed in 1988 with an established personality questionnaire, and psychopathology through seven semi-structured interviews between 1979 and 2008. On the basis of personality assessment from 1988, used as predictor of subsequent psychopathology (1993-2008), while adjusting for sex and prior mental disorders (1979–1988), neuroticism related significantly with future major depression episodes [odds ratio (OR) = 1.41], anxiety disorders (OR = 1.32) and depression treatment use (OR = 1.41). When participants with a past 10-year history (i.e. 1979-1988) of either major depression, anxiety disorder or depression treatment use were excluded, neuroticism in 1988 still significantly predicted first incidence (i.e. 1993-2008) of major depression episodes (OR = 1.53) and depression treatment use (OR = 1.84). The present study provides compelling evidence that the personality trait of neuroticism constitutes an independent risk factor for subsequent major depression episodes and use of respective professional treatments, which serves as a proxy for particularly severe and impairing depression episodes. We therefore advocate that personality traits could provide clinically useful prognostic information when considered carefully.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-01-30T13:17:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-30T13:17:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291716000210</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2272</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1017/S0033291716000210</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2272</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2272</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2272</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2272</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0033-2917</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1469-8978</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Psychological Medicine</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Cambridge University Press</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5950</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-18T08:36:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Schlank in den Frühling, was tun?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brombach, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>610: Medizin und Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-17T14:10:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-17T14:10:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3669</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3669</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>WädiInfo</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Verkehrsverein Wädenswil</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10652</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T13:39:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Reconstruction of solar UV irradiance since 1974</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Krivova, N. A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Solanki, S. K.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wenzler, T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Podlipnik, B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>500: Naturwissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Variations of the solar UV irradiance are an important driver of chemical and physical processes in the Earth's upper atmosphere and may also influence global climate. Here we reconstruct solar UV irradiance in the range 115–400 nm over the period 1974–2007 by making use of the recently developed empirical extension of the Spectral And Total Irradiance Reconstruction (SATIRE) models employing Solar Ultraviolet Spectral Irradiance Monitor (SUSIM) data. The evolution of the solar photospheric magnetic flux, which is a central input to the model, is described by the magnetograms and continuum images recorded at the Kitt Peak National Solar Observatory between 1974 and 2003 and by the Michelson Doppler Imager instrument on SOHO since 1996. The reconstruction extends the available observational record by 1.5 solar cycles. The reconstructed Ly-α irradiance agrees well with the composite time series by Woods et al. (2000). The amplitude of the irradiance variations grows with decreasing wavelength and in the wavelength regions of special interest for studies of the Earth's climate (Ly-α and oxygen absorption continuum and bands between 130 and 350 nm) is 1–2 orders of magnitude stronger than in the visible or if integrated over all wavelengths (total solar irradiance). </dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-17T12:44:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-17T12:44:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1029/2009JD012375</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1029/2009JD012375</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10652</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10652</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10652</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2169-897X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of Geophysical Research: Atmospheres</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Wiley</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5248</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-05-12T12:56:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>„Quantified seniors“ : technisch unterstützte Selbstvermessung bei älteren Personen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Seifert, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meidert, Ursula</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Self-measurement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Selbstvermessung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Senior</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wearables</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Smartphone</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gesundheits-App</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610: Medizin und Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenz.ch)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Hintergrund: Bewegungs- und Vitalwerte werden heute meist digital mit Aktivitätssensoren, Wearables und Apps auf dem Smartphone gemessen. Es gibt jedoch kaum Studien, welche die alltägliche Nutzung dieser Selbstvermessungstechnologien bei älteren Personen empirisch untersuchen.&#13;
Ziel der Arbeit: Der vorliegende Bericht untersucht die Nutzung von mobilen digitalen Selbstvermessungsanwendungen bei Personen ab 50 Jahren. Gefragt wird nach beeinflussenden Faktoren, gemessenen Parametern und Beweggründen der Nutzung.&#13;
Material und Methoden: Zur Beantwortung der Forschungsfragen wurden zwei Stichproben aus der Schweiz für eine Sekundäranalyse herangezogen. Hierbei wurden 2502 Personen befragt, wobei sich die Analyse auf Personen ab 50 Jahren fokussiert (n= 1227). Die Daten wurden deskriptiv ausgewertet und Gruppenunterschiedemittels Cramers V sowie binäre logistische Regressionen überprüft.&#13;
Ergebnisse: Fast die Hälfte der befragten Personen vermessen sich mithilfe von Selbstvermessungstechnologien. Rund ein Drittel derjenigen, die ein Smartphone besitzen, nutzen Apps zur gesundheitsbezogenen Selbstvermessung. Das Messen mithilfe von Smartphone und Apps ist die beliebteste Art der Selbstvermessung, gefolgt von Fitnesstracker und Smartwatch. Die Nutzung hängt wesentlich vom Alter und der Technikaffinität ab. Gemessen werden vorwiegend physische Aktivtäten, aber auch Vitaldaten wie der Puls. Gründe für die Selbstvermessung sind die Motivation gesund zu bleiben, die eigene Leistung zu optimieren, aber auch der Anreiz, einmal etwas Neues auszuprobieren. &#13;
Schlussfolgerung. Wearables und Gesundheits-Apps werden eher von jüngeren und technikaffinen Personen genutzt. Das Präventions- und Interventionspotenzial ist bei Personen ab 50 Jahren noch nicht ausgeschöpft.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T13:41:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T13:41:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11553-018-0646-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3578</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/s11553-018-0646-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3578</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5248</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5248</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5248</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1861-6755</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1861-6763</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Prävention und Gesundheitsförderung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8357</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T09:26:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wertorientierungen bei Jugendlichen : ein Prädiktor für Problemverhalten?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wegel, Melanie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stroezel, Holger</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kerner, Hans-Jürgen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Kriminalität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Werteforschung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kriminalprävention</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>364: Kriminologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Werteforschung leistet einen Beitrag zur Erklärung von Einstellungen und Werthaltungen mit Blick auf bestimmte Personengruppen und soziale Milieus. In der Kriminologie werden kriminogene Werte mit Problemverhalten in einen Zusammenhang gebracht. Im Aufsatz wird untersucht inwieweit eine Präferenz kriminogener Werte als Prädiktor für künftiges Problemverhalten aussagekräftig sein könnte.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-20T07:07:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-20T07:07:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5771/9783845271842-184</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.5771/9783845271842-184</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8357</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8357</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8357</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-8487-2806-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-8452-7184-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Kriminalsoziologie : Handbuch für Wissenschaft und Praxis</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Nomos</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14558</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T14:11:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wirkungsanalyse von Mutter-Kind-Angeboten im Kanton Zürich : Schlussbericht</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gabriel, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Keller, Samuel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bombach, Clara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stohler, Renate</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ibrahimi, Bujare</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Mutter-Kind-Einrichtungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wirkungsanalyse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Auftraggeber Forschungsprojekt: Bildungsdirektion des Kantons Zürich, Amt für Jugend und Berufsberatung</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-01-23T13:42:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-23T13:42:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2766</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2766</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14558</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14558</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14558</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>107 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13790</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-04-07T14:53:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Qualitätsbericht 2017 : ausserklinische Geburtshilfe in Deutschland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Loytved, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Geburt</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618.4: Geburt</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-12-13T13:03:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-13T13:03:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4931</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4931</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://quag.de/downloads/QUAG_bericht2017.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13790</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-95735-093-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>74 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Verlag Wissenschaftliche Scripten</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16598</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-25T16:53:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Funktionen und Kontrolle der Gewalten : Tagungsbericht zu der 40. Assistierendentagung öffentliches Recht in Giessen vom 14. – 17. März 2000</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wiederkehr, René</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>349: Rechtsvergleichung und ausländisches Recht</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-04-15T10:04:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-15T10:04:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2000</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16598</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16598</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16598</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1422-0709</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Schweizerisches Zentralblatt für Staats- und Verwaltungsrecht</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schulthess</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17290</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-07-23T11:13:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Entwicklungstrends der Jugendgewalt in Deutschland im Hell- und Dunkelfeld</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Baier, Dirk</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kliem, Sören</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Gewalt</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Raub</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Körperverletzung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kriminalstatistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Befragung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>364: Kriminologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Entwicklung der Jugendgewalt ist von besonderem gesellschaftlichem Interesse. In den zurückliegenden Jahren hat es einen deutlichen Rückgang der Jugendgewalt gegeben; jüngste Zahlen hingegen deuten auf einen leichten Anstieg hin. Unter Rückgriff auf die Polizeiliche Kriminalstatistik und wiederholt durchgeführte Jugendbefragungen im Bundesland Niedersachsen werden zentrale Erkenntnisse zu Entwicklungstrends und möglichen Hintergrundfaktoren präsentiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-06-19T09:30:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-06-19T09:30:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17290</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17290</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17290</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1612-1864</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Zeitschrift für Jugendkriminalrecht und Jugendhilfe</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Deutsche Vereinigung für Jugendgerichte und Jugendgerichtshilfen</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1060</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-11-15T13:26:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_236</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1055</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Verwertung von Schulzeugnissen in Erstausbildungsberatungen : Wie Berufsberatende Schulzeugnisse einschätzen und verwenden</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Djelili, Amet</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Der Umgang der Berufsberater mit Schulzeugnissen in Erstausbildungsberatungen ist ein für die Forschung noch gänzlich unbekanntes Terrain. Der Berufsberatung kommt dabei an der Schnittstelle zwischen der Schule als ausstellende Institution und den Lehrbetrieben als Empfänger des Zeugnisses im Rahmen des Auswahlverfahrens eine nicht unwichtige Rolle zu, orientiert die Berufsberatung doch die Schüler nicht nur in Bezug auf ihre Interessen, sondern, oft auf Aufforderung der Schüler oder deren Eltern, auch bezüglich ihrer Chancen. Die Befragung von 7 Berufsberatern aus dem Kanton Zürich zur Einschätzung und Verwertung der Schulzeugnisse in Erstausbildungsberatungen zeigt eine beeindruckend grosse und anregende Palette von Funktionen der Schulzeugnisse. Es werden aber auch grosse Unterschiede in der Gewichtung der Schulzeugnisse sichtbar. Zudem kann z.T. eine Diskrepanz zwischen der Sicht der Berufsberater und der gut erforschten Perspektive der Betriebe festgestellt werden. Schliesslich erwiesen sich die Ergebnisse der vorliegenden Arbeit als höchst brauchbar und nützlich für die Beratungspraxis des Autors selbst, der dadurch zahlreiche eigene blinde Flecken und Fehlannahmen aufdecken konnte.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2016-03-22T15:35:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-03-22T15:35:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Master</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24582</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-18T04:03:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_22</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_6874</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Cashback : ein neues Instrument für Preispromotionen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sterba, Natalie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>338: Produktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Preispromotionen werden eingesetzt, um den Absatz kurzfristig zu steigern und haben somit einen Einfluss auf die Kaufentscheidung von Konsumenten. Eine Gefahr ist jedoch, dass Preispromotionen den internen Referenzpreis der Konsumenten dauerhaft senken können und somit die Kunden nicht mehr bereit sind, reguläre Preise zu bezahlen. Aus diesem Grund ist es von Relevanz zu verstehen, wie Preispromotionen auf den Konsumenten wirken.&#13;
Nebst klassischen Rabattaktionen oder Coupon Aktionen finden auch zwei Arten von Cashback Promotionen ihren Einsatz, nämlich dezentrale und zentralisierte Cashback Promotionen. Bei dezentralen Cashback Promotionen hat der Kunde die Möglichkeit Geld zurück zu erhalten, indem ein Beweis des Produkterwerbs an den Hersteller gesendet wird. Zentralisierte Cashback Promotionen beziehen sich auf Plattformen, bei denen man über zur Verfügung gestellte Links online einkaufen kann und so Cashback sammelt. Die Forschung zu Cashback Promotionen ist jedoch rudimentär und bezieht sich auf zentralisierte Cashback Promotionen. Deswegen hat sich diese Arbeit auf dezentrale Cashback Promotionen fokussiert und untersucht, wie Cashback Promotionen zurzeit in der Praxis durchgeführt werden, welche Vor- und Nachteile für den Konsumenten respektive das Unternehmen entstehen, wie dezentrale Cashback Promotionen auf den Konsumenten wirken, welche Faktoren einen Einfluss haben und wie diese im Vergleich zu anderen Preispromotionen wirken.&#13;
Hierfür wurde zunächst eine Voruntersuchung gemacht, wie Cashback Promotionen in der Praxis durchgeführt werden. Es zeigt sich, dass Cashback Promotionen mit einem Aufwand für den Konsumenten und das Unternehmen verbunden sind, dadurch, dass ein Antrag auf die Cashback Erstattung getätigt werden muss und das Unternehmen die Anträge auf ihre Echtheit überprüfen muss. Auf Basis der Mental Accounting Theorie wurde der Gesamtnutzen von klassischen Rabattaktionen und dezentralen Cashback Promotionen konzeptionell hergeleitet und im Hinblick auf die Kaufbereitschaft und die Senkung des internen Referenzpreises in einem nicht faktoriellen Between-Subject-Design untersucht.&#13;
In der Hauptuntersuchung mit n = 320 Probanden konnten keine signifikanten Unterschiede zwischen den Experimentalgruppen festgestellt werden. Trotz fehlender Signifikanz zeigt sich die Tendenz, dass dezentrale Cashback Promotionen den internen Referenzpreis weniger stark senken als klassische Rabattaktionen und weisen gleichzeitig eine geringere Kaufbereitschaft als klassische Rabattaktionen auf. Dies ist unabhängig von der Preisnachlasshöhe oder dem Aufwand, der getätigt werden muss, um den Cashback Betrag zu erhalten.&#13;
Mit dieser Arbeit konnte ein Grundstein für die weitere Forschung zu dezentralen Cashback Promotionen gelegt werden. Insbesondere leistet diese Arbeit einen Beitrag zur Erweiterung der Mental Accounting Theorie, indem die Theorie um nicht monetäre Elemente ergänzt wurde. Marketing Manager müssen vor dem Einsatz von dezentralen Cashback Promotionen den genauen Nutzen abwägen, da diese Art von Promotion teilweise mit einem grossen Aufwand verbunden ist und die Kaufbereitschaft nicht zwingend gesteigert wird.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-03-16T11:33:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-03-16T11:33:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Master</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-24582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-24582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>95 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5703</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T12:32:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Sprache, Geld und gutes Leben</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Whitehouse, Marlies</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Perrin, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>400: Sprache und Linguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-02T09:10:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-02T09:10:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5703</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5703</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5703</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>SRG im Dialog mit … Medienwissenschaft, Winterthur, 25. April 2017</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23334</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-10-30T03:03:44Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>English in Swiss higher education : the pragmatic way</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Studer, Patrick</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Siddiqa, Aisha</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Internationalisation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Englishization</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Higher education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Language policy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>378: Hochschulbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>This chapter reviews the current discourses surrounding English in higher education, focusing on the impact Englishization has had on education and language policy-planning in Switzerland. While English is in direct competition with national languages at the obligatory school levels, and the debate about the status of English is evident in national language policymaking, higher education institutes (henceforth HEIs) have taken a pragmatic approach, broadening their educational offerings to include English-medium courses and programmes at all levels. Taking legal, strategy and policy documents as its basis, this chapter discusses themes that impact thinking about language in higher education in a small multilingual nation and reviews how the language question has been addressed by policymakers at the national and institutional levels.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-10-29T08:49:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-10-29T08:49:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-10-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5117/9789463727358</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23334</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.5117/9789463727358</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23334</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23334</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23334</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23334</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-94-6372-735-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-90-4855-391-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>The Englishization of Higher Education in Europe</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Amsterdam University Press</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7655</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-11-21T08:14:56Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Development of antioxidant food packaging materials containing eugenol for extending display life of fresh beef</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Navikaite-Snipaitiene, Vesta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ivanauskas, Liudas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jakstas, Valdas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rüegg, Nadine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rutkaite, Ramune</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wolfram, Evelyn</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Yildirim, Selçuk</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Antioxidant packaging</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Beef</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Clove essential oil</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Eugenol</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vapour phase DPPH assay</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>664: Lebensmitteltechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In this study, clove essential oil (CL) or eugenol (EU) containing cellulose acetate (CA) or acrylic component/hydrophobically modified starch (AC/S) coatings on corona treated oriented polypropylene film (OPP) were designed and investigated for their possible applications as antioxidant packaging materials for fresh meat. The antioxidant properties of the coatings were investigated by Vapour Phase-DPPH (2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl) assay. The CA coatings containing CL or EU showed 43-92% and 43-94% inhibition against DPPH free radicals through the vapour phase, respectively, whereas AC/S/CL and AC/S/EU coatings resulted in DPPH inhibition of 21-65% and 25-84%, respectively. AC/S/EU and CA/EU coatings on OPP containing from 0.32 ± 0.03 to 6.40 ± 0.14 g/m2 of EU were used to prepare packaging for fresh beef (Longissimus thoracis). After 14 days, the lipid oxidation in beef steaks kept in control and antioxidant packages was 3.33 and 1.00-1.22 mg of malondialdehyde per kilogram of meat, respectively. Moreover, red colour of beef in antioxidant packages was retained.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-06T11:20:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-06T11:20:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meatsci.2018.05.015</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.meatsci.2018.05.015</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7655</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7655</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7655</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0309-1740</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1873-4138</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>29859422</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Meat Science</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5566</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T13:18:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Sustainability code / load index for the semi-quantitative assessment of analytical methods in a research environment : proof of concept</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Petrozzi, Sergio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Yeretzian, Chahan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Green analytical chemistry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Teaching laboratory classes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Green metrics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sustainability studies</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>540: Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The aim of this project was to develop a general concept to assess the laboratory experiments in the instrumental analysis laboratory, at the Institute of Chemistry and Biological Chemistry (ICBC) at the Zurich University of Applied Sciences (ZHAW), in terms of their sustainability and, where possible, to improve the sustainability rating of the laboratory experiments. Hence, the primary objective was to implement an empirical assessment methodology, including the “Sustainability Code” that was composed of four parts and a “Sustainability Load Index”. During the spring semester 2015, 105 different experimental projects were performed in the ICBC’s analytical chemistry practical course. These were carried out on 18 different instrumental workspaces, encompassing 12 different analytical methodologies. For the development of the first and second parts of the Sustainability Code, information concerning the chemical substances (in any state- solid, liquid or gas) used and the energy consumption of the apparatus was recorded. The third and fourth parts contain (approximate) information on the use of consumables and the sustainability of the method with reference to the apparatus used. The Load Index (LI) consists of an aggregation (summary) of the direct causality indicators ‘substances’ and ‘energy’ into a single figure. The experiments were classified on a 3-level Load Index Scale into ‘ideal’ analysis methods (LI&gt; 20), ‘sustainable’ methods of analysis (LI 20-200), and analysis methods ‘with potential for optimization’ (LI &lt;200). The assessment criteria described here, specifically designed for an analytical process in a university environment, may also serve as a useful guide for semi-quantitative assessment of both familiar and new methods in analytical chemistry practical courses and in laboratory practice. It may also be useful in general research laboratory environments.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-25T13:45:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-25T13:45:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4222</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.13189/eer.2015.030603</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4222</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.13189/eer.2015.030603</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5566</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5566</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5566</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2331-625X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2331-6268</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Environment and Ecology Research</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Horizon Research</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24130</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-14T09:55:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Gerber &amp; le Grelle : die Doc.coach Startup Story</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Angerer, Alfred</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gerber, Andre</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Angerer, Alfred</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Adhärenz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Compliance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Digitale-Versorgungs-Gesetz (DVG)</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Erfolgsfaktor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Jens Spahn</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Marktpositionierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Meta-Coach</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Risikobereitschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Transformation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Trial and Error</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Unternehmensfokus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>User Journey</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.1: Organisation und Finanzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Andre Gerber kommt aus der Gesundheits- und Pharmabranche und ist Präsident der Firma Doc.coach. Unterstützung in der Kommunikation erhält er von Sophia le Grelle, welche schon seit über 10 Jahren im Gesundheitswesen arbeitet. Gemeinsam mit Alfred Angerer sprechen sie über ihr Startup, womit sie medizinisches Fachpersonal und Apotheke vor Ort unterstützen wollen. Dafür nutzen sie ein multimodales Netzwerk aus analogen und digitalen Instrumenten, um die Prognose, Diagnose und Therapie der Patientinnen und Patienten zu verbessern.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-02-02T15:28:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-02-02T15:28:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-02-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Weiteres (nicht-textuelles Material)</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Ton</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://gesundheitswesen.org/12-gerber-le-grelle-die-doc-coach-startup-story</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24130</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Podcast Marktplatz Gesundheitswesen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>00:52:04 S.</dc:format>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6280</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-14T13:37:37Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Plädoyer für politische Bildung : Kommunizieren Behörden an der Jugend vorbei?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stücheli-Herlach, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Behördenkommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Jugend</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>SIKOV</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>320: Politik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Kommunizieren Behörden an der Jugend vorbei? In einem Referat vor der Schweizerischen Informations-Konferenz öffentlicher Verwaltungen (SIKOV) in Winterthur hat Dr. Peter Stücheli-Herlach, Leiter Beratung IAM und Dozent für Politische Kommunikation, zu dieser Frage Stellung bezogen. Er zeigte die Grenzen der Kommunikation zwischen Behörden und Jugendlichen auf und plädierte dafür, Anstrengungen für eine lebenslange politische Bildung zu verstärken. Dies sei die wichtigste staatliche Aufgabe, um die Kommunikationsprobleme zwischen Behörden und Jugendlichen anzugehen. Die Schweizerische Informations-Konferenz öffentlicher Verwaltungen (SIKOV) ist ein Zusammenschluss von Informationsbeauftragten und -diensten aus der Schweiz und dem Fürstentum Liechtenstein.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-05-30T14:46:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-30T14:46:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6280</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6280</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6280</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Schweizerische Informations-Konferenz öffentlicher Verwaltungen (SIKOV), Winterthur, 2008</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12150</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-10-25T15:55:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kompetenzen in der Welt der Sicherheit</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hardegger, Simon Carl</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Boss, Patrick</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-10-25T15:55:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-25T15:55:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12150</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12150</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12150</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>KMU Business World</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Swisscom</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19652</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T14:05:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Stirred bioreactors : current state and developments, with special emphasis on biopharmaceutical production processes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jossen, Valentin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eibl-Schindler, Regine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pörtner, Ralf</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kraume, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eibl, Dieter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Bioreactor mode</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Key engineering issue</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mammalian cell</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Microorganism</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Reusable</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Single use</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Transport phenomenom</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>660: Technische Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>It is undisputed that stirred bioreactors are the most common type of bioreactors for submerged bioprocesses. Stirred bioreactors for biopharmaceuticals, which represent the strongest-growing branch of modern biotechnological products, are the focus of our chapter. They are available in working volumes from milliliters up to 70 m3 and are used for a wide range of expression systems that require aseptic conditions. Based on a brief summary of some basic rules for the construction and operation of stirred bioreactors, this chapter will review key engineering issues that affect the design of aseptic stirred bioreactors. We will also provide readers with some general information on transport phenomena in stirred bioreactors before discussing special design aspects and performance parameters for expression systems (mammalian and microbial cells) that prevail in commercial biopharmaceutical production processes. Special attention will be paid to single-use stirred bioreactors, which may have advantages over their reusable counterparts and have become widely accepted over the past years.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-03-05T14:05:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-03-05T14:05:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-444-63663-8.00007-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/B978-0-444-63663-8.00007-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19652</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19652</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19652</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:9780444636638</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Current Developments in Biotechnology and Bioengineering</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4572</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T10:17:44Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>ACTUS : a mathematically rigorous, technical language to describe all financial contracts?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Breymann, Wolfgang</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Standardization</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Data</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Financial risk</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332: Finanzwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-03T12:16:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-03T12:16:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4572</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4572</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4572</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Foundational Building Blocks for a 21st Century Financial Data Infrastructure, Frankfurt, Germany, 10 November 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/637</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:42:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_53</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Fetale Programmierung : warum wir dicke Kinder haben; ein Erklärungsversuch</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gebhart, Cecilia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jürgensen, Swantje</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:07:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:07:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-637</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-637</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/637</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/637</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/637</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11081</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T14:05:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Requirements to concepts and practice of mother-child-institutions in Switzerland : results of an evaluation study</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stohler, Renate</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Keller, Samuel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bombach, Clara</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-09-26T14:06:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-26T14:06:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-04-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11081</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11081</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11081</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>6th European Conference for Social Work Research : Book of Abstracts and Programme Book</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>6th European Conference for Social Work Research, Lisbon, Portugal, 30 March - 1 April 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ESWRA European Social Work Research Association</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2974</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T10:11:56Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Academic writing at a glance : techniques used by L2 writers to capture and hold their readers' attention at a poster session</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Barnett, Penelope</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ehrensberger-Dow, Maureen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Genre</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Criteria</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Poster</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Academic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418: Gebrauch der Standardsprache</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Many Swiss universities offer their students courses on writing research articles in English. Other academic genres, for example posters, are rarely taught, even though students are often required to prepare posters in English. For guidance, novice researchers rely on their supervisors or the lists of "dos and don'ts" they find in style guides. Although some of the conventions suggested in style guides are adopted by many poster writers, the final products differ greatly in their visual impact. In this study, we investigated 30 posters created, displayed and peer-evaluated by L2 PhD students at an ecology conference, to identify ways in which visual elements combine with academic language and the organisation of ideas to capture and hold the attention of potential readers. Using criteria that define semiotic force, we analysed (1) the posters that were rated most highly by the conference participants, and (2) a selection of posters that received no positive ratings. We suggest that the interaction of visual, linguistic and organisational elements may have been overlooked or taken for granted by the L1 writers of style guides. Our findings offer insights into the conference poster as a multimodal genre and supplement existing guidelines on creating posters.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-23T07:46:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-23T07:46:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2974</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2974</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2974</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Tagung des Forums Wissenschaftliches Schreiben, Winterthur, 9-10 June 2006</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2766</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T10:53:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Why perovskite solar cells with high efficiency show small IV-curve hysteresis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Neukom, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Züfle, Simon</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Knapp, Evelyne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Makha, Mohammed</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hany, Roland</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ruhstaller, Beat</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>There is increasing evidence that the presence of mobile ions in perovskite solar cells can cause a current-voltage curve hysteresis. However, it is still subject of ongoing debates how exactly mobile ions influence the device operation. We use drift-diffusion simulations incorporating mobile ions to describe IV-curves of preconditioned methylammonium lead iodide perovskite solar cells and compare them with experimental results.&#13;
&#13;
Our simulation results show that the hysteresis depends on the extent of surface recombination and on the diffusion length of charge carriers. We provide a detailed explanation for the reduced hysteresis of perovskite solar cells with high power conversion efficiencies. We find that in high-efficiency solar cells ion migration is still present, but does not cause a hysteresis effect. In these devices charge extraction is mainly driven by diffusion of free electrons and holes.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-14T08:09:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-14T08:09:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.solmat.2017.05.021</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.solmat.2017.05.021</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2766</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2766</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2766</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0927-0248</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Solar Energy Materials &amp; Solar Cells</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken completeListSize="24863" cursor="170">oai_dc////17100</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
