<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="static/style.xsl"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-06-08T16:56:16Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" resumptionToken="oai_dc////19500">https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/oai/request/</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/491</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:43:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_52</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Präoperatives sensomotorisches Training : Einfluss auf die postoperative Gleichgewichts- und körperliche Funktionsfähigkeit</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Meier, Franziska</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:05:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:05:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20998</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-10T12:45:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Angebote für armutsbetroffene Familien mit Vorschulkindern : zur Schnittstelle von materieller Sicherung, frühkindlicher Bildung und Frühen Hilfen in der Schweiz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Eberitzsch, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brink, Ida Ofelia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lätsch, David Cyrill</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Sozialhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kindesschutz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Frühe Förderung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Frühe Hilfen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>FBBE</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kinder- und Jugendhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Grundsicherung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>361: Sozialarbeit und Sozialhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.7: Jugendhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Im ISA-Jahrbuch 2020 „Kinderschutz? Lebenswelten gestalten – Gefahren abwehren“ wird eine fachpolitische, facettenreiche Diskussion aufgegriffen, die Expert*innen in vielfältigen Arbeitsfeldern auf kommunaler, Landes- und Bundesebene betrifft.&#13;
Auf der einen Seite besteht ein großer Handlungsbedarf, um Rahmungen und infrastrukturelle Bedingungen für ein gelingendes Aufwachsen für alle zu gestalten. So zeigen z. B. die Folgen der Armutsentwicklung bei Kindern und Jugendlichen, wie groß die kompensatorischen Herausforderungen in Erziehung und Bildung sind. Auf der anderen Seite braucht es verlässliche Kriseninterventionen und passgenaue Hilfen, um Kinder zu schützen und zu unterstützen. Wie fließend müssen die Übergänge zwischen der Gestaltung einer sozialen Infrastruktur hin zu intensiveren, einzelfallbezogenen Hilfen für Kinder, Jugendliche und Familien sein? Ist dann alles Kinderschutz oder braucht es genauere Definitionen und Abgrenzungen, damit Kinder zuverlässig vor Gefahren für ihr Wohl geschützt werden können?&#13;
Mit diesen Fragestellungen befassen sich die Autor*innen, um zu einer Klärung und Weiterentwicklung der fachlichen Ausrichtungen beizutragen, die Kinder und Jugendliche stärken und sie in den Mittelpunkt ihrer Arbeit stellen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Die frühe Kindheit steht international im Fokus sozial- und gesellschaftspolitischer Debatten. So wird die Lebensphase zunehmend als ein Investitionsfeld zur gesamtgesellschaftlichen Wohlstandssicherung thematisiert (Marope/Kaga 2015), und es wird auf langfristige soziale Folgekosten verwiesen, die von einer Geringschätzung dieses Politikfeldes ausgehen können (Barnett 2011). Ein hoher Stellenwert kommt in diesen Debatten der Förderung junger Menschen in prekären oder sozial benachteiligten Lebenslagen zu. Insbesondere Kinder aus Familien in Armutslagen sind einem deutlich erhöhten Risiko ausgesetzt, im weiteren Verlauf ihres Lebens selbst von Armut, geringen Bildungsressourcen und gesellschaftlicher Ausgrenzung betroffen zu sein (Laubstein u. a. 2016). &#13;
Die deutsche wie auch die schweizerische Politik begegnet den genannten Entwicklungsrisiken auf mehreren Ebenen. Eine wichtige Rolle zur Eindämmung materieller Armut spielt die Grundsicherung in Form des Arbeitslosengeldes II (Deutschland) bzw. der materiellen Sozialhilfe (Schweiz/Deutschland). Daneben werden psychosoziale Risiken, die mit Armut assoziiert sind, durch Leistungen, Hilfen und Maßnahmen aus dem breiten Spektrum der frühkindlichen Bildung und Erziehung, den Frühen Hilfen bis hin zu den Hilfen zur Erziehung adressiert. Im vorliegenden Artikel liegt der Fokus auf den beiden erstgenannten Feldern. &#13;
Armutslagen von Familien stellen ein komplexes und vielschichtiges soziales Problem dar. Mit der hier vorgestellten Studie wird ein spezifischer Ausschnitt davon beleuchtet, nämlich Angebote und Beratung für Familien mit Vorschulkindern, die materielle Grundsicherung beziehen. Dabei geht es insbesondere um die bisher wenig erforschte Frage, wie im Schweizer System der Sozialhilfe die Situation von Vorschulkindern berücksichtigt wird, die in prekären Lebenslagen aufwachsen. Dazu werden – aus einem noch frühen Stadium der Datenauswertung – erste Erkenntnisse einer Befragung von 265 Fachpersonen der Sozialhilfe aus acht Deutschschweizer Kantonen vorgestellt und mit Blick auch auf den Stand der Entwicklung in Deutschland erörtert. Zunächst werden die institutionellen Schnittstellen zwischen materieller Grundsicherung und Angeboten in der frühen Kindheit in beiden Ländern eingeführt. Der Schwerpunkt liegt auf der Schweizer Situation.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-12-09T15:09:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-12-09T15:09:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-20998</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-20998</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20998</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20998</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20998</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-8309-4309-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>ISA-Jahrbuch zur Sozialen Arbeit 2020</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Waxman</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7837</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T07:22:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Evaluating marketing efforts of the European Journalism Observatory as a dissemination network : a practical showcase of empirical data</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dingerkus, Filip</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wyss, Vinzenz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>070: Nachrichtenmedien, Journalismus und Verlagswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Referat</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-10T14:13:38Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-10T14:13:38Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014-07-18</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7837</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7837</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7837</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>International Association for Media and Communication Research (IAMCR) Conference, Hyderabad, India, 18 July 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14174</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-26T11:22:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Merkmale von Justizvollzugsanstalten als Einflussfaktoren von Gewalt und Drogenkonsum : eine explorative Studie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Klatt, Thimna</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Suhling, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bergmann, Marie Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Baier, Dirk</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>365: Justizvollzugsanstalten</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-01-04T15:09:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-04T15:09:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14174</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14174</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14174</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2366-1968</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0026-9301</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Monatsschrift für Kriminologie und Strafrechtsreform</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>De Gruyter</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2518</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T11:10:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The multifunctional aquaponic system at ZHAW used as research and training lab</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Graber, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Antenen, Nadine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Junge, Ranka</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Aquaponics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Urban farming</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>630: Landwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Aquaponics plays a part in promoting sustainable development on different levels in society, and its use is becoming ever more widespread. However, there are not enough trained specialists yet to build and operate such systems. The aim of this paper is to highlight the role of institutions of higher education – like ZHAW – can play to mitigate this deficit. ZHAW has the ability to execute applied research, teaching on BSc and MSc level, and is aiming to increase societal added value concerning education and health. Each of these levels has different demands on the aquaponic system concerning a multitude of factors, such as access, size, construction, climate control, diversity of production methods, recycling and closed loop systems, provision of energy from renewable sources and rainwater harvesting, treatment and use. To evaluate how these objectives are reached, the requirements on the system originating from each level are defined. These are used to evaluate the aquaponic system that was built and operated at ZHAW. Other aquaponic systems in use are compared to the ZHAW system, using the same evaluation criteria. The results show that the ZHAW Aquaponics Lab can reach all target levels, if the aquaponic farm of its spin-off company UrbanFarmers is viewed as an extension of it.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-01T09:47:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-01T09:47:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1613</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1613</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2518</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2518</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2518</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:9789619356432</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Prenos inovacij, znanja in izkušenj v vsakdanjo rabo : zbornik izvlečkov = transmission of innovations, knowledge and practical experience into everyday practice : book of abstracts</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>3rd Conference VIVUS, Conference on Agriculture, Environmentalism, Horticulture, Floristics, Food Production and Processing, Strahinj, Slovenia, 14–15 November 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Biotehniški center Naklo</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12828</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-24T14:09:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Impact evaluation of Swiss Medical Board reports on routine care in Switzerland : a case study of PSA screening and treatment for rupture of anterior cruciate ligament</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Eichler, Klaus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hess, Sascha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riguzzi, Marco</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Can, Ünal</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brügger, Urs</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Anterior cruciate ligament</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Anterior cruciate ligament repair</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Evidence-Based Medicine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Impact evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Prostate-Specific Antigen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Swiss Medical Board</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Questions under Study: Evidence-based recommendations play an important role in medical decision-making, but barriers to adherence are common. In Switzerland, the Swiss Medical Board (SMB) publishes evidence reports that conclude with recommendations. We assessed the impact of two SMB reports on service provision (2009: Recommendation of conservative treatment as first option for rupture of the anterior cruciate ligament of the knee; 2011: Recommendation against PSA screening for prostate cancer).

Methods: We performed an observational study and assessed quantitative data over time via interrupted times series analyses. The primary outcome was the quarterly number of performed prostate-specific antigen (PSA) tests and the annual rates of surgical ACL repair in patients with ACL rupture. Data were adjusted for time trends and relevant confounders. 

Results: We analysed PSA tests in 662,874 outpatients from 2005-2013 and treatment data in 101,737 patients with knee injury from 1990-2011. For the number of PSA tests, the secular trend before the intervention showed a continuous but diminishing increase over time. A statistically significant reduction in tests was estimated immediately after the intervention, but a later return to the trend before the intervention cannot be ruled out. The rate of surgical ACL repair had already declined after the late 1990s to about 55% in 2009. No relevant additional change emerged in this secular trend after the intervention.

Conclusions: Despite some evidence of a possible change, we did not find a sustained and significant impact of SMB recommendations in our case study. Further monitoring is needed to confirm or refute these findings.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-15T14:16:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-15T14:16:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4884</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.4414/smw.2015.14140</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4884</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.4414/smw.2015.14140</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12828</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12828</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12828</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-7860</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-3997</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0036-7672</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>26024476</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Swiss Medical Weekly</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>EMH Schweizerischer Ärzteverlag</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17925</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T10:33:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>New methodological answers to the new normal in risk and investment management</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schwendner, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.1: Organisation und Finanzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-08-14T12:45:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-08-14T12:45:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17925</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17925</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17925</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>PRMIA Chapter Event, Frankfurt, Germany, 4-5 November 2013</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Professional Risk Managers' International Association (PRMIA)</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10201</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T14:34:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Business Process Management 2011 : Hype, Hoffung oder Realität?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Minonne, Clemente</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Process management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Prozessmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Business process management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>ZWI</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.5: Produktionssteuerung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Ausgestaltung und der Automatisierungsgrad von Geschäftsprozessen bestimmen die Produktivität, Qualität und Innovationsfähigkeit einer Organisation in hohem Masse. Doch das Potenzial, das moderne Konzepte bieten, wird noch nicht ausgeschöpft.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-05T11:00:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-05T11:00:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011-07-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10201</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10201</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10201</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-2397</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Netzwoche</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Netzmedien</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9439</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-04-06T09:42:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Normative climates of parenthood across Europe : judging voluntary childlessness and working parents</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Eicher, Véronique</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Settersten, Richard A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Penic, Sandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Glaeser, Stephanie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martenot, Aude</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Spini, Dario</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>306: Kultur</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenzen.ch)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Past research on gender role attitudes has often focused on individual- rather than country-level explanations. Drawing on European Social Survey data from 21 countries, we examine the effect of societal normative climates (i.e., shared perceptions of others’ attitudes) on personal attitudes towards two non-traditional gender roles: Voluntary childlessness and working full-time while children are young. To detect potential gender differences, we analyse disapproval of men and women separately. Findings reveal that there are strong differences in normative climates across countries, and that people generally perceive more disapproval of women than of men for both behaviours. Most importantly, in countries where a higher share of respondents perceives disapproval of these behaviours, respondents themselves disapprove more strongly – even if they do not believe that others disapprove, and even after controlling for other relevant individual- and country-level characteristics. What is more, the independent effect of normative climate explains most of the differences between countries. This robust finding demonstrates the power of country-level normative climates in explaining individuals’ attitudes and between-country differences in attitudes toward gender roles.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-23T06:14:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-23T06:14:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3931</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1093/esr/jcv083</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3931</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1093/esr/jcv083</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9439</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9439</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9439</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0266-7215</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1468-2672</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>European Sociological Review</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Oxford University Press</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6190</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T10:12:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>OpenCL streaming platform on FPGA</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Weiss, Armin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rosenthal, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Streaming</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Altera</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>OpenCL</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>FPGA</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Many embedded applications have to cope with real-time data streams, e.g. video, audio, network, sensor data, etc. Real-time processing of fast data streams with low latency is a hard requirement which is often only achieved using dedicated hardware accelerators. FPGA’s provide an ideal basis for integrating specific hardware blocks, however, their development in VHDL or Verilog is a time consuming process.&#13;
As an alternative, FPGA manufacturers have started to support OpenCL as the programming language for building hardware blocks. OpenCL is ideally suited for implementing streaming algorithms typically on multi-core CPUs or GPUs. On the other hand, using OpenCL on an FPGA requires new concepts for data transfer and real-time control of hardware blocks. In return, a reduced time-to-market can be expected because the OpenCL compiler takes care of time consuming tasks like the timing analysis and the implementation of state machines.&#13;
This paper gives an overview on how OpenCL code is translated into hardware and shows the difference to traditional OpenCL implementations on multi-core CPUs or GPUs. Moreover, a new concept of a generic platform for streaming applications is presented, which allows the user to program own streaming-kernels in hardware using OpenCL. Efficient data input and output is guaranteed because the stream remains in the FPGA and is never transferred to the global memory or to the CPU. Real-time control of streaming-kernels is handled by the platform using the CPU of the SoC.&#13;
The development workflow is demonstrated using the example of a color space converter. The implementation is done on an Altera Cyclone-V SoC. Measurements and limitations are discussed and the usability for general streaming applications is outlined.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-05-29T12:50:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-29T12:50:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-11-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6190</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6190</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6190</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>VISION: Exhibition VDMA, Stuttgart, Deutschland, 8.-10. November 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13279</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T09:10:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>PV installations based on vertically mounted bifacial modules evaluation of energy yield and shading effects</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nussbaumer, Hartmut</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Klenk, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schär, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Baumann, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carigiet, Fabian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Keller, Nico</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Baumgartner, Franz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Bifacial</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>PV Array</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Shading</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>System Performance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Bifacial solar modules promise an increased energy yield, compared to systems with standard, monofacial panels, and also offer new opportunities with regard to the installation. One particular approach is the vertical mounting of PV modules, which is reported to be an effective measure to avoid soiling or dust deposition and is an option to obtain a broadened energy generation profile. In spite of the general interest in this type of installation, the amount of published data is very limited, especially with regard to arrays, for which pronounced shading effects can be expected.&#13;
In this work we present an analysis of the energy yield and the respective losses for arrays of vertically mounted bifacial solar modules with varied installation conditions.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-27T15:23:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-27T15:23:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4894</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.4229/EUPVSEC20152015-5AV.6.34</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4894</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.4229/EUPVSEC20152015-5AV.6.34</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13279</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13279</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13279</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3-936338-39-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the 31st European Photovoltaic Solar Energy Conference and Exhibition</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>31st European Photovoltaic Solar Energy Conference and Exhibition (EUPVSEC), Hamburg, Germany, 14-18 September 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>WIP</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10217</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-18T09:41:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Terminologie in der Fachkommunikation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kriele, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Terminologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fachkommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>401.4: Lexikologie und Terminologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In diesem Beitrag wird anhand eines Beispiels für missverständliche Kommunikation in der Luftfahrt aufgewiesen, welchen Nutzen Terminologiearbeit im Hinblick auf eine klare und eindeutige Kommunikation stiften kann. Die Antwort auf die Frage, wie Studierende zu einer professionellen Kommunikation befähigt werden können, soll dabei lauten: Indem sie zunächst vom Nutzen von Terminologiearbeit überzeugt werden und indem ihnen anschliessend das dafür notwendige Wissen vermittelt wird.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-05T14:41:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-05T14:41:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4090</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110496604-026</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4090</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1515/9783110496604-026</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10217</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10217</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10217</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-11-049660-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Doing applied linguistics : enabling transdisciplinary communication</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>De Gruyter Collection</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>De Gruyter</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12725</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-25T16:53:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>BGE 129 III 702 : die Qualifikation als Bürgschaftsvertrag : Bundesgericht, I. Zivilabteilung, Urteil vom 23. September 2003, i.S. X. AG gegen A.</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Abegg, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Der Inhaber einer im Handelsregister eingetragenen Einzelfirma schloss am 6. März 1996 einen Leasingvertrag über einen Kleinbus für 15 Personen ab und unterzeichnete zugleich mit der Leasinggeberin eine Schuldanerkennung für die Leasingraten. Der Leasingvertrag sowie die Schuldanerkennung wurden einerseits vom Leasingnehmer und andererseits "solidarisch" bzw. als "Solidarschuldner" von dessen Tochter und dessen Ehefrau unterzeichnet. Die Schuldanerkennung gab den Wortlaut der Artikel 143, 144 und 147 OR zur Solidarschuld wieder. Zwei Monate später erlitt der Leasingnehmer mit dem geleasten Fahrzeug einen Unfall. In der Folge unterschrieb er mit seiner Tochter eine Schuldanerkennung gegenüber der Leasinggeberin über Fr. 22’000.-, zahlbar in 48 Monatsraten à Fr. 450.- zuzüglich einer Schlussrate von Fr. 400.-. Die Tochter verweigerte jedoch die entsprechende Zahlung und wurde betrieben. Nach der provisorischen Rechtsöffnung wurde ihre Aberkennungsklage vom Bezirksgericht Baden am 26. Februar 2002 zunächst abgewiesen, jedoch vom Obergericht am 27. Februar 2003 gutgeheissen. Die Berufung hiergegen wies das Bundesgericht mit dem Entscheid BGE 129 III 702 vom 23. September 2003 ab.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-09T15:02:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-09T15:02:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Entscheidanmerkung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12725</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12725</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12725</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1660-3362</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Aktuelle juristische Praxis</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Dike</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11796</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T09:27:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Aufbruch in eine neue Welt</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kley, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ziegler, Suzanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Private Banking</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Weissgeldstrategie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wealth Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332.1: Banken</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Der Schock des Notverkaufs der Bank Wegelin sitzt tief. Bis heute spürt man die Verunsicherung: Keine Bank scheint vor dem Druck aus dem Ausland sicher zu sein. Die Branche hofft auf die Abgeltungssteuer. Genügt dies, oder braucht es einen Paradigmenwechsel?</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-15T10:12:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-15T10:12:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11796</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11796</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.nzz.ch/aufbruch-in-eine-neue-welt-1.17258343</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11796</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0376-6829</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Neue Zürcher Zeitung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Neue Zürcher Zeitung</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5157</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:00:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>„Also, machen wir eine Geschichte.“ Narration in den SRG-Redaktionen Tagesschau, 10vor10 und Journal</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gnach, Aleksandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>070: Nachrichtenmedien, Journalismus und Verlagswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T14:36:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T14:36:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5157</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5157</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5157</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>DGPuk Fachgruppentagung 2012 «Narration und Argumentation», Winterthur, 16.-17. Februar 2012</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1627</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T12:32:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kuchen, Kurven, Karten : von Datenvisualisierungen und Infografiken</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Weber, Wibke</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>000: Allgemeines und Wissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>700: Künste und Unterhaltung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2017-11-30T14:40:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-11-30T14:40:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-04-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1627</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1627</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1627</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>SRG im Dialog mit … Medienwissenschaft, Winterthur, 25. April 2017</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5095</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T10:36:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Redundanz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Perrin, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Media</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Redundancy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Encyclopedia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Communication science</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>401.4: Lexikologie und Terminologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T13:22:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T13:22:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5095</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5095</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5095</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3-531-13535-X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Lexikon Kommunikations- und Medienwissenschaft</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Studienbücher zur Kommunikations- und Medienwissenschaft</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16450</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T07:20:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>CAD/CAM software for an industrial laser manufacturing tool</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stassen Böhlen, Ines</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fieret, Jim</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Holmes, Andrew S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lee, Kin W.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Laser micromachining</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Rapid prototyping</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>UV solid-state laser</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>CAD/CAM laser processing software</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>A facility for rapid prototyping of MEMS devices is crucial for the development of novel miniaturized components in all sectors of high-tech industry, e.g. telecommunications, information technology, micro-optics and aerospace. To overcome the disadvantages of existing techniques in terms of cost and flexibility, a new approach has been taken to provide a tool for rapid prototyping and small-scale production: Complex CAD/CAM software has been developed that automatically generates the tool paths according to a CAD drawing of the MEMS device. As laser ablation is a much more complicated process than mechanical machining, for which such software has already been in use for many years, the generation of these tool paths relies not only on geometric considerations, but also on a sophisticated simulation module taking into account various material and laser parameters and micro-effects. The following laser machining options have been implemented: cutting, hole drilling, slot cutting, 2D area clearing, pocketing and 2½D surface machining. Once the tool paths are available, a post processor translates this information into CNC commands that control a scanner head. This scanner head then guides the beam of a UV solid-state laser to machine the desired structure by direct laser ablation.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-03-29T09:50:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-29T09:50:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1117/12.479533</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1117/12.479533</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16450</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16450</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16450</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0277-786X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Photon Processing in Microelectronics and Photonics II</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>High-Power Lasers and Applications, San Jose, USA, 25-31 January 2003</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings / SPIE</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>International society for optical engineering</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15582</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-14T15:13:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The construction of an autonomously driving automobile</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brom, Charles</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bengtsson, Ola</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Medricky, Petr</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Automotive</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Navigation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mechatronics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>620: Ingenieurwesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In this paper we discuss the modifications made to a standard automobile in order to enable autonomous maneuvering. The configuration is tested by means of a parallel parking procedure. The control architecture consists of an off-line trajectory planner and a real-time motion controller. The generated trajectory to be followed is based on radar range data. The parking trajectory is evaluated by solving the inverse kinematics of the parking procedure. The developed controller and algorithmic is then experimentally verified on an automobile.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-22T11:46:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-22T11:46:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/S1474-6670(17)31079-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/S1474-6670(17)31079-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>3rd IFAC Mechatronics Conference 2004, Sydney, Australia, 6-8 September 2004</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>IFAC Proceedings Volumes</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2896</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T10:17:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Bedeutung des Projektunterrichts und Projektmanagements aus Sicht der Wirtschaft</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Baumann, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Projektunterricht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>371: Schulen und schulische Tätigkeiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Seit den 1930er Jahren ist Projektmanagement bekannt. Doch trotz 80-jähriger Entwicklungsarbeit in dieser Managementdisziplin liegt der Projektmanagementerfolg – also die termin- und budgetgerechte Lieferung eines vereinbarten Projektergebnisses – oft nicht höher als bei 20%. Methoden mit solch mageren Erfolgsquoten haben im Allgemeinen keinen Bestand in der Praxis. Das Referat zeigt auf, weshalb Projektmanagement trotzdem nicht mehr aus dem modernen Management-Repertoire wegzudenken ist.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-21T12:26:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-21T12:26:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4124</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4124</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2896</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2896</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2896</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Projekte und Projektmanagement machen Schule</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Fachtagung der Pädagogischen Hochschule Luzern, Luzern, 5. November 2011</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>PH Luzern</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9636</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-28T13:20:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>How to make scientists agree : an evolutionary betting mechanism</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Slembeck, Tilman</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>330: Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-08-24T13:35:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-24T13:35:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2000</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1111/1467-6435.00135</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1111/1467-6435.00135</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9636</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9636</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9636</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0023-5962</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1467-6435</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Kyklos</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Wiley</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/974</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-04T12:56:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_26</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1094</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_5519</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>KMU-Strategiebarometer 2011</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schuppisser, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kucza, Gunther</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cometta, Claudio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hertach, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>338: Produktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Studie</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Im Jahr 2009 nahmen 238 Unternehmen an der ersten Durchführung des KMU-Strategiebarometers teil und ermöglichten so einen aufschlussreichen Einblick in die Strategiearbeit in Schweizer KMUs. Die Ergebnisse der Studie wurden im Oktober 2009 am Wirtschaftsforum in Winterthur präsentiert und sind auf grosses Interesse gestossen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2015-08-13T09:38:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-13T09:38:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-974</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-974</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/974</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/974</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/974</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18901</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-11T13:00:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Bankangestellte müssen sich mit "neuen Welten" auseinandersetzen : Weiterbildung eröffnet Chancen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Höllerich, Johannes</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>332: Finanzwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.3: Personalmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Der Strukturwandel in der Finanzbranche führt dazu, dass sich die Anforderungen an die Mitarbeitenden verändern. Im Banking sind neue Kompetenzen und interdisziplinäre Zusammenarbeit gefragt. Die SML-Zukunftsstudie «Bankfachspezialisten 2030» zeigt auf, wie sich Angestellte darauf vorbereiten und die sich daraus ergebenden Chancen nutzen können.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-12-11T13:00:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-12-11T13:00:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.zhaw.ch/storage/sml/ueber-uns/sml-magazin-competence-2019.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18901</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2297-6140</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Competence</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24962</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-05-12T11:31:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Deriving monetary values of Nature’s Contributions to People : an extended conceptual framework with an application to Switzerland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zabel, Astrid</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bokusheva, Raushan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bozzola, Martina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Monetary valuation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Exchange value</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>SEEA</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Switzerland</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333.7: Landflächen, Naturerholungsgebiete</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>This paper builds upon the economic valuation suggested in the United Nations System of Environmental Economic Accounting – Ecosystem Accounting (SEEA EA). In particular, we present the conceptual and methodological framework that can be applied in countries with highly regulated use of and access to natural resources. We apply this framework for deriving monetary values for a number of NCPs in the Swiss context and present a selection of estimates.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-05-12T11:31:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-05-12T11:31:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-04-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24962</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24962</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24962</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>96th Annual Conference of the Agricultural Economics Society, Leuven, 4-6 April 2022</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6520</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-26T07:17:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Fäkalindikatoren im Trinkwasser nachweisen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gantenbein-Demarchi, Corinne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kuhn, Roger</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kauf, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schmid, Jürg</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Krapf, Tamara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fieseler, Lars</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Fäkalindikatoren</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Trinkwasser</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>363: Umwelt- und Sicherheitsprobleme</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-04T13:40:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-04T13:40:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6520</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6520</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6520</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1663-9855</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Alimenta</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Publilactis</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23958</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-20T14:12:44Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Was die Bevölkerung unter Datensicherheit und Datenschutz versteht</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pleger, Lyn Ellen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mertes, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Guirguis, Katharina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Auch die Verwaltung wird immer digitaler. Die Gesellschaft verfolgt diese Entwicklung kritisch und hat Vorbehalte hinsichtlich Datensicherheit und Datenschutz. Was diese beiden Begriffe aber genau bedeuten, wissen viele Menschen nicht, wie eine neue Studie zeigt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-01-20T14:12:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-01-20T14:12:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-23</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.higgs.ch/was-die-bevoelkerung-unter-datensicherheit-und-datenschutz-versteht/47418/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23958</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>higgs</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Scitec-Media</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15489</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T10:36:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>§ 38 Sitzungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wiederkehr, René</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>342: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Staats- und Verwaltungsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-02-20T13:27:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-20T13:27:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15489</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15489</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15489</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7272-8725-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Kommentar der Kantonsverfassung Luzern</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Stämpfli</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24285</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-26T04:03:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Studie : Gute Angehörigenarbeit in der stationären und intermediären Betreuung älterer Menschen (2020-2022)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Baumeister, Barbara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Strohmeier Navarro Smith, Rahel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Adili, Kushtrim</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Angehörigenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Betreuung älterer Menschen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Wie kann die Zusammenarbeit mit Angehörigen in stationären und intermediären Einrichtungen für alle Beteiligten gewinnbringend gestaltet werden? Dieser Frage geht ein Forschungsteam des Instituts Vielfalt und gesellschaftliche Teilhabe am Departement Soziale Arbeit der ZHAW nach. Das laufende Projekt wird durch die Paul Schiller Stiftung finanziert. Im folgenden Artikel werden die bisherigen Ergebnisse der Studie basierend auf einer Literaturanalyse, einer quantitativen Befragung sämtlicher Alters- und Pflegezentren im Kanton Zürich sowie einer Diskussion mit Expertinnen und Experten präsentiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-02-25T17:08:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-02-25T17:08:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-24285</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-24285</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://svat.ch/wp-content/uploads/studie.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24285</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Aktiv</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Schweizerischer Berufsverband der Aktivierungsfachfrauen / männer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8227</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T14:10:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Evaluation of restoration and flow interactions on river structure and function : channel widening of the Thur river, Switzerland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Martin, Eduardo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ryo, M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Döring, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Robinson, C. T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Restoration</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Flow regime</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sediment regime</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Respiration</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Macroinvertebrates</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333: Bodenwirtschaft und Ressourcen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>577: Ökologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Removal of lateral constraints to restore rivers has become increasingly common in river resource management, but little is known how the interaction of de-channelization with flow influences ecosystem structure and function. We evaluated the ecosystem effects of river widening to improve sediment relations in the Thur River, Switzerland, 12 years after implementation. We tested if restored and non-restored reaches differed in water physico-chemistry, hyporheic function, primary production, and macroinvertebrate density and composition in relation to the flow regime. Our results showed that (i) spatio-temporal variation in sediment respiration and macroinvertebrate taxonomic richness were driven by interactions between restoration and flow; (ii) riverbed conditions including substrate size, organic matter content, and groundwater–surface water exchange changed due to restoration, but (iii) physico-chemistry, hydraulic conditions, and primary production were not altered by restoration. Importantly, our study revealed that abiotic conditions, except channel morphology, changed only marginally, whereas other ecosystem attributes responded markedly to changes in flow-restoration interactions. These results highlight integrating a more holistic ecosystem perspective in the design and monitoring of restoration projects such as river widening in resource management, preferably in relation to flow-sediment regimes and interactions with the biotic components of the ecosystem.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-17T14:01:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-17T14:01:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.3390/w10040439</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.3390/w10040439</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8227</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8227</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8227</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2073-4441</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Water</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>MDPI</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6599</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T15:30:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ausgaben für Produktionsmittel : Studie des Bauernverbands</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hilber, Urs</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>630: Landwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-06T11:39:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-06T11:39:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1996</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6599</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6599</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6599</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1022-663X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Agrarforschung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Bundesamt für Landwirtschaft</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16582</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T10:31:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>A reference framework to sustainability implement operational excellence in the pharmaceutical industry</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gronauer, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Scherrer, Maike</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Friedli, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Operational excellence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lean production</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Key influencing factor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658: Allgemeines Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>This paper analyzes Operational Excellence Initiatives (OEI) and its Key Influencing Factors (KIF) for sustainable implementation in the context of the pharmaceutical industry. While the interactions between various practices and operational performance had been previously investigated, there are evidences in the literature that site specific KIFs play underestimated roles. To address this issue, 9 different manufacturing sites of one company, facing the same industry challenges and OEI launches, had been investigated to get an in-depth understanding of KIFs for the implementation process on plant level. Our findings revealed 8 different KIFs and a pattern for successful implementation.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-04-15T08:38:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-15T08:38:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>16th EurOMA Conference, Göteborg</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>16th International Annual EurOMA Conference, Goteborg, Sweden, 14-17 June 2009</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>European Operations Management Association</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22765</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-01T10:44:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Linderung von Schmerzen durch Krämpfe oder die Rückbildung der Gebärmutter nach der Geburt (Übersetzung der Zusammenfassung)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Roth, Christina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zelck, M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Nachwehen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schmerzlinderung nach der Geburt</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Uteruskontraktionen postpartum</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Medikation bei Nachwehen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Übersetzung der Zusammenfassung des Cochrane Reviews "Relief of pain due to uterine cramping/involution after birth" (2020) in einfacher Sprache auf Deutsch</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-07-01T10:44:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-07-01T10:44:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Weiteres (textuelles Material)</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.cochranelibrary.com/cdsr/doi/10.1002/14651858.CD004908.pub3/full/de#CD004908-abs-0003</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22765</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Cochrane Deutschland Stiftung</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6996</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:53:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Literature review on meal choice and meal offering</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Frick, Jacqueline</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Literature review</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Meal choice</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Meal offering</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Range of meal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Animal product</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Taste</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Meat reduction</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sustainability</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Food choice</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vegetarian meal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vegan meal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Chef</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Eating behaviour</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Innovation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Intervention</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Eating habit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Haute cuisine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Flexitarian</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Meal production decision</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Healthy meal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Choice</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Choice architecture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>300: Sozialwissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>This review paper aims to summarise literature on relevant influences and effective interventions in the field of meal choice and meal offering, in particular relating to the question of how choice and offering of meals containing few or no animal products can be increased. Studies concerning the motives and decision criteria (e.g. attitudes, values, knowledge or preference of consumers, as well as personal preferences, habits, and professional ambitions of chefs) are summarised. In addition, situational and structural facilitators and constraints (know-how, trends, or social norms, etc.) for choice and range of animal products in meals in away-from-home settings are identified. Furthermore, effective interventions to change meal planning, offering and choice are studied. For this, a non-systematic, explorative literature review was conducted. &#13;
&#13;
With regard to meal choice, it was found that among personal motives, taste and health considerations were most relevant. Knowledge of food was relatively low and many consumers seemed to simply not care to a great extent about nutrition. Furthermore, familiarity was found to be an important component of food choice. Important context influences were availability and convenience. There is potential for meat reduction in about half the population who can be expected to essentially be open to behaviour change. Interventions can make use of heuristics by manipulating proximity, anchoring, labelling or prompts. &#13;
&#13;
With regard to meal offering, chefs’ concerns about health and sustainability and their responsibility to offer an attractive choice of foods is a good starting point for interventions. The top priority among chefs was customer demand, which they associated mainly with taste and familiarity. Chefs believe that meals should look rich and appetising. Chefs also complained about lack of training and storage problems that prevent them from offering more vegetarian or vegan meals with fresh foods. Interventions should also consider chefs’ professional ambitions and curiosity, in particular in haute cuisine. Innovation processes should take feedback into account not only from employees and customers but also from suppliers.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-18T08:18:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-18T08:18:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1402</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1402</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6996</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6996</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6996</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>NOVANIMAL Working Papers</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>45 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11835</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T09:27:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Jetzt absichern! Aber wie?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Papenbrock, Jochen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schwendner, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>332.6: Investition</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Das dritte Top des Aktienmarkts innerhalb von 15 Jahren fühlt sich anders an als die beiden Vorgänger in den Jahren 2000 und 2007. Den niedrigen Volatilitäten zum Trotz trauen die Anleger der ­Situation nicht. Welche Möglichkeiten gibt es zur Absicherung?</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-16T13:48:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-16T13:48:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11835</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11835</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11835</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1613-6772</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Portfolio Institutionell</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Portfolio-Verlags-Gesellschaft</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19232</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-30T04:02:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Schlussbericht : Torfreduzierte Bio-Anzuchtsubstrate für den produzierenden Gemüse- und Beerenanbau</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kunz, Guido</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mathis, Alex</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Keller, Hans-Rudolf</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Gemüsejungpflanzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Erdpresstöpfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Tefa</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Torfersatz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>635: Gartenpflanzen (Gartenbau)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Im Projektbericht werden die Resultate der Anbauversuche mit neuentwickelten torfreduzierten Bio-Anzuchtsubstraten für den produzierenden Gemüsebau zusammengefasst. Durchgeführt wurden Versuche mit Erdpresstöpfen (verschiedene Gemüse)  und mit Topfkräutern. Der Torfanteil lässt sich dabei deutlich reduzieren.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-01-29T09:58:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-01-29T09:58:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-19232</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-19232</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19232</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19232</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19232</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>46 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5859</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T09:47:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1075</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1074</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1076</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Land für das Wasser : Landschaftsgestaltung als Hochwasserschutz anhand des Siegerprojektes Europan 8 für Brezice (Slowenien) von NetGlue, 2006</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jenni, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Landschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hochwasser</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Naturgefahr</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Städtebau</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>712: Landschaftsgestaltung (Landschaftsdesign)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-15T16:46:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-15T16:46:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5859</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5859</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5859</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0005-6529</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0257-9332</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Werk, Bauen + Wohnen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Verlag Werk</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1508</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-02-09T07:23:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Lessons from the radio - text design for the web : guest lecture at Stanford University, USA, (Learning Lab), 20 May 2002</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Weber, Wibke</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>070: Nachrichtenmedien, Journalismus und Verlagswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2017-11-17T10:30:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-11-17T10:30:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2002-05-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Vorlesung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1508</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1508</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1508</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10385</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-28T09:38:13Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Couch Commerce durch Fernsehwerbung fördern</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bétrisey, Michèle</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Seiler, Roger</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Mobile commerce</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fernsehwerbung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Couch commerce</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Betreut durch Dr. Roger Seiler vom Institut Marketing Management der ZHAW, hat Michèle Bétrisey qualitative Forschung zum Einkaufen vom Sofa auf mobilen Endgeräten, dem sogenannten Couch Commerce, durchgeführt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-11T14:08:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-11T14:08:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10385</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10385</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10385</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1023-8913</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0255-7673</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Marketing &amp; Kommunikation</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Galledia</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6693</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:40:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Naturschutz zwischen Agglomeration und Autobahn : erfolgreiche Renaturierung des Flachmoors Hänsiried im Kanton Zürich</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Babbi, Manuel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Krüsi, Bertil</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Vegetationskartierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hänsiried</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Torfstich</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Katzensee</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333.7: Landflächen, Naturerholungsgebiete</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>577: Ökologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Umzingelt von Verkehrsinfrastrukturen und landwirtschaftlich genutzten Flächen ist das rund 13.4 ha grosse Flachmoor Hänsiried eine ökologisch wertvolle Insel inmitten der Agglomeration Zürich. Die mangelnde Pflege der Grossseggenriede, sowie die starke Erholungsnutzung durch die Bevölkerung ab Mitte des 20. Jahrhunderts haben zur Verbuschung und einem für Moore untypischen Landschaftsbild geführt. Erst umfangreiche Renaturierungsmassnahmen und die regelmässige Nutzung der Sumpfwiesen seit den späten 1980er Jahren haben das Gebiet wiederhergestellt und aufgewertet. Im Jahr 2011 wurde die Vegetation im Hänsiried mit dem Kartierungsschlüssel für Nassstandorte im Kanton Zürich erfasst. Die dominierenden Vegetationseinheiten waren Wald (2.68 ha), nicht-bultiges Grossseggenried (Einheit 3b, 1.61 ha) und Schilfröhricht (Einheit 2a, 1.26 ha). Die Waldfläche hat zwischen 1944 und 1985 von 1 ha auf 6.2 ha zugenommen und bis 2011 dank erfolgreichen Pflegemassnahmen wieder auf 2.8 ha abgenommen. Die offene Wasserfläche inklusive Schwimmblattgesellschaften ist im gleichen Zeitraum hingegen von 1.4 auf 0.5 ha geschrumpft. Die starke Verschilfung einiger Torfstiche, sowie der übrigen Flächen ist nach wie vor ein Problem, da dadurch die Verlandung der Torfstiche vorangetrieben wird und die Biodiversität in den Grossseggenriedern sinkt. Damit die Qualität des Hänsirieds weiter verbessert werden kann, ist neben der Pflege ein regelmässiges Monitoring der Vegetation unabdingbar. Nur so können Veränderungen frühzeitig erkannt und situationsgerechte Pflegemassnahmen durchgeführt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-08T12:44:51Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-08T12:44:51Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://www.ngzh.ch/archiv/2013_158/158_3-4/158_22.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6693</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0042-5672</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Vierteljahrsschrift der Naturforschenden Gesellschaft in Zürich</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Koprint</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24068</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-02T13:31:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>A conceptual study customer-centric luxury ecosystems : an innovative strategic approach for luxury customer experience management</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gadgil, Maya</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Guhl, Selina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Björck, Albena</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Business ecosystem</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Customer experience management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Customer-centricity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Innovative strategy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Luxury management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>This study will provide insight into the mechanisms of a luxury ecosystem and its potential to enhance customer experience management. Ecosystems are built in collaboration with various partners that share a common vision. Luxury experiences have to be managed, to ensure that the search of luxury consumers for pleasure, emotions, uniqueness and consid- eration are fullfilled. Preliminary results show that an adapted luxury ecosystem model, based on customer-centricity, epitomizes an innovative strategic approach for customer experience management.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-02-02T13:31:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-02-02T13:31:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.15444/GFMC2021.04.02.01</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.15444/GFMC2021.04.02.01</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24068</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24068</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24068</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2288-825X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the Global Fashion Management Conference 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Global Fashion Management Conference, Seoul, Korea, 5-7 November 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Global Alliance of Marketing &amp; Management Associations</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9665</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-28T06:39:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Computational design of catalytic dyads and oxyanion holes for ester hydrolysis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Richter, Florian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Blomberg, Rebecca</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Khare, Sagar D.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kiss, Gert</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kuzin, Alexandre P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Smith, Adam J. T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gallaher, Jasmine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pianowski, Zbigniew</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Helgeson, Roger C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Grjasnow, Alexej</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Xiao, Rong</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Seetharaman, Jayaraman</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Su, Min</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vorobiev, Sergey</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lew, Scott</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Forouhar, Farhad</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kornhaber, Gregory J.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hunt, John F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Montelione, Gaetano T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tong, Liang</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Houk, K. N.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hilvert, Donald</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Baker, David</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Catalytic domain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Esterases</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Esters</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hydrogen bonding</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hydrolysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kinetics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Biocatalysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Drug design</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Molecular models</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>540: Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Nucleophilic catalysis is a general strategy for accelerating ester and amide hydrolysis. In natural active sites, nucleophilic elements such as catalytic dyads and triads are usually paired with oxyanion holes for substrate activation, but it is difficult to parse out the independent contributions of these elements or to understand how they emerged in the course of evolution. Here we explore the minimal requirements for esterase activity by computationally designing artificial catalysts using catalytic dyads and oxyanion holes. We found much higher success rates using designed oxyanion holes formed by backbone NH groups rather than by side chains or bridging water molecules and obtained four active designs in different scaffolds by combining this motif with a Cys-His dyad. Following active site optimization, the most active of the variants exhibited a catalytic efficiency (k(cat)/K(M)) of 400 M(-1) s(-1) for the cleavage of a p-nitrophenyl ester. Kinetic experiments indicate that the active site cysteines are rapidly acylated as programmed by design, but the subsequent slow hydrolysis of the acyl-enzyme intermediate limits overall catalytic efficiency. Moreover, the Cys-His dyads are not properly formed in crystal structures of the designed enzymes. These results highlight the challenges that computational design must overcome to achieve high levels of activity.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-27T06:47:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-27T06:47:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1021/ja3037367</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1021/ja3037367</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9665</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9665</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9665</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0002-7863</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1520-5126</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>22871159</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of the American Chemical Society</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>American Chemical Society</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17963</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-12T10:28:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Effects of family, social and health characteristics on perceived burden of adult children as caregiver</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hediger, Hannele</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fringer, André</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Naef, Rahel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mahrer Imhof, Romy</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Imhof, Lorenz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-08-23T13:07:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-08-23T13:07:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-08-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17963</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17963</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17963</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>14th International Family Nursing Congress, Washington D.C., USA, 13-16 August 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14236</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T14:06:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>In good hands - around the clock : innovation in SME</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Färber, Andri</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>AAL Forum</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Innovation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>SME</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-01-09T10:23:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-09T10:23:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14236</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14236</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14236</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>AAL Forum Odense 2010, Odense, Denmark, 14-16 September 2010</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7676</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T13:57:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_22</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_6876</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Business process as a service : Konzeption und Realisierung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Boller, Micha Sebastian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.5: Produktionssteuerung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Nebst strukturierten Business-Prozessen existieren in Unternehmen auch unstrukturierte Business-Prozesse. Solche unstrukturierten Business-Prozesse sind schwierig zu modellieren, weil viele Eventualitäten auftreten können. Der Verlauf wird durch einen Knowledge Worker bestimmt und ist somit nur teilweise vorhersehbar. Ein Beispiel eines unstrukturierten Business-Prozesses ist die Behandlung eines Patienten durch einen Arzt.

Zur Unterstützung unstrukturierter Business-Prozesse können keine Process Engines genutzt werden, weil dazu ein Prozess-Modell vorliegen muss. Das ist einer der Gründe, dass sich Unternehmen zur Unterstützung von unstrukturierten Business-Prozessen zum Beispiel E-Mail-Programmen und Dokumenten bedienen. Die Nachvollziehbarkeit wie auch die Übersicht über die laufenden Business-Prozesse und die Automatisierbarkeit sind so eingeschränkt.
Diese Master Thesis erarbeitet ein Konzept und ein Prototyp einer Business Process as a Service (BPaaS) Plattform. Diese Plattform wird in der Cloud betrieben und unterst ützt Unternehmen bei der Abwicklung von unstrukturierten Business-Prozessen. Zentrales Artefakt ist der Ad-Hoc-Prozess. Der Ad-Hoc-Prozess ist ein Ansatz, wie unstrukturierte Business-Prozesse ohne vorangehende Prozess Modellierung unterst ützt werden k önnen. Dabei bedient sich dieser Ansatz so genannten Activity Patterns, welche wiederkehrende Muster in Business-Prozessen darstellen. Beispiele von Activity Patterns sind die Ausf ührung einer Aufgabe oder die Herbeif ührung einer Entscheidung. Zudem wird eine Implementierung des vorgeschlagenen Ansatzes in Form eines lau ff ähigen Prototyps vorgelegt. Dieser Prototyp basiert auf der Camunda BPM Plattform. Nebst der Abwicklung von unstrukturierten Business-Prozessen unterst ützt der Prototyp auch das automatisierte On-Boarding (Erstellen eines Zugangs) eines Unternehmens auf die BPaaS-Plattform.
Die Resultate dieser Master Thesis zeigen auf, dass unstrukturierte Business-Prozesse mit dem erarbeiteten Ad-Hoc-Prozess abgewickelt werden k önnen und damit Unternehmen eine Hilfestellung bei der Ausf ührung von unstrukturierten Business-Prozessen geboten werden kann. Ob sich der erwartete Nutzen durch die Benutzung der BpaaS-Plattform f ür ein Unternehmen einstellt, kann in weiteren Forschungsarbeiten ermittelt werden. Als Basis dazu dienen die erarbeiteten Resultate.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-06T12:55:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-06T12:55:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Master</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2080</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2080</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7676</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7676</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7676</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>89 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22311</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-04-22T08:56:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kommentar zu Art. 50 OR</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fischer, Willi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Iten, Marc’Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-04-22T08:56:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-04-22T08:56:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22311</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22311</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22311</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-03751-685-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Haftpflichtkommentar : Kommentar zu den schweizerischen Haftpflichtbestimmungen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Dike</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23441</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-23T08:22:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Continuous milli-scale reaction calorimeter for direct scale-up of flow chemistry</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Moser, Marlies</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Georg, Alain G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Steinemann, Finn Lorenz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meier, Daniel Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rütti, David</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Continuous fow reactor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Isoperibolic reaction calorimetry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Heat of reaction</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Safety</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Process development</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Scale-up</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>540: Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Reaction calorimetry of flow processes is important for scale-up and safety in flow chemistry. Due to the increasing number of flow processes, corresponding flow calorimeters are required as an alternative or addition to high-precision batch calorimeters. In this work, a milli-scale isoperibol continuous flow calorimeter was used to measure the heat of reaction based on an elaborated heat transfer model. This allows for reaction calorimetry without calibration. The model was tested with a selective, fast and exothermic neutralization reaction of acetic acid and sodium hydroxide at different flow rates, concentrations and viscosities. Deviations of the mean heats of reaction from the literature values were only about 2%. The calorimetric data can further be used for direct scale-up with tube bundle mixer heat exchangers having similar heat transfer characteristics. In addition, a reaction screening at different flow rates allows to find the maximum temperature and maximum heat generation. This data is useful in safety analyses of continuous processes. For these reasons, continuous reaction calorimetry provides a practical scale-up tool for flow processes.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-11-11T11:09:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-11T11:09:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-10-18</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/s41981-021-00204-y</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23441</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/s41981-021-00204-y</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23441</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23441</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23441</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23441</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2062-249X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2063-0212</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of Flow Chemistry</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9399</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-11T09:15:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Im Topmanagement mit Kindern : mit Biss und Bravour</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Streuli, Elisa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Frau</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Karriere</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Familie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Zeitmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Anspruch</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>158: Angewandte Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Samstag im "Tages-Anzeiger" und Sonntag in der "SonntagsZeitung" integriert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-22T15:24:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-22T15:24:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9399</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9399</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9399</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1422-9994</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Alpha: der Kadermarkt der Schweiz</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Tamedia</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24026</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-27T16:00:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ephemeral social media content : remember after seeing instead of burn after reading</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stallone, Valerio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Koller, Sandro</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Ephemeral content</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Online advertising</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Social media</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Ephemeral social media content, a type of Social media content that takes on a central function in social media, refers to content that automatically disappears from social media platforms (like Instagram) after a certain amount of time. Currently, this format is used by more than 500 million users every day. Using Instagram Stories Ads, advertisements can be placed in the same format. The aim of this study is to find out which content and elements of Instagram Stories ads appeal to certain target groups of a large Swiss sporting goods manufacturer along the notorious marketing funnel used by the sporting goods manufacturer. Various Instagram stories ads of a large sporting goods manufacturer were tested by means of an online experiment with regard to their suitability for the different phases of the marketing funnel: Three recommendations for action for the design and area of application of so-called "ephemeral social media content" were derived.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-01-27T16:00:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-01-27T16:00:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://proceedings.emac-online.org/pdfs/A2021-94779.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24026</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the European Marketing Academy</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>50th Annual European Marketing Academy Conference (EMAC), Madrid, Spain (online), 25-28 May 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>European Marketing Academy</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9934</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T10:52:42Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Tail-risk protection trading strategies</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Packham, Natalie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Papenbrock, Jochen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schwendner, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Woebbeking, Fabian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Extreme event</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Tail distribution</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Portfolio protection</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Tail-risk protection</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332: Finanzwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Starting from well-known empirical stylized facts of financial time series, we develop dynamic portfolio protection trading strategies based on econometric methods. As a criterion for riskiness, we consider the evolution of the value-at-risk spread from a GARCH model with normal innovations relative to a GARCH model with generalized innovations. These generalized innovations may for example follow a Student t, a generalized hyperbolic, an alpha-stable or a Generalized Pareto distribution (GPD). Our results indicate that the GPD distribution provides the strongest signals for avoiding tail risks. This is not surprising as the GPD distribution arises as a limit of tail behaviour in extreme value theory and therefore is especially suited to deal with tail risks. Out-of-sample backtests on 11 years of DAX futures data, indicate that the dynamic tail-risk protection strategy effectively reduces the tail risk while outperforming traditional portfolio protection strategies. The results are further validated by calculating the statistical significance of the results obtained using bootstrap methods. A number of robustness tests including application to other assets further underline the effectiveness of the strategy. Finally, by empirically testing for second-order stochastic dominance, we find that risk averse investors would be willing to pay a positive premium to move from a static buy-and-hold investment in the DAX future to the tail-risk protection strategy.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-29T14:44:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-29T14:44:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1080/14697688.2016.1249512</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1080/14697688.2016.1249512</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9934</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9934</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9934</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1469-7688</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1469-7696</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Quantitative Finance</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Routledge</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16835</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:30:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Forecasting non-stationary financial data with OIIR-filters and composed threshold models</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wildi, Marc</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>High pass filter</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Stationary component</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Filter design</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Infinite impulse response</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Amplitude function</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332: Finanzwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>500: Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The paper proposes a forecasting-technique well suited to stationary and non-stationary economic or financial data. Two methods are used which together generalize the Box-Jenkins ARIMA-technique: Optimized-Infinite-Impulse-Response-Filters generalize difference-filters and composed-threshold (piecewise linear) models generalize linear ARMA-models.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-04-24T10:08:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-24T10:08:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1998</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4615-5625-1_31</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-1-4615-5625-1_31</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16835</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16835</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16835</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-0-7923-8309-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-4615-5625-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1388-4301</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Decision technologies for computational finance : proceedings of the Fifth International Conference Computational Finance</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>5th International Conference Computational Finance, London, United Kingdom, 15-17 December 1997</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Advances in computational management science</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2637</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-13T10:12:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Esskultur heute : zwischen Infantilisierung und Selbstbestimmung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brombach, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>300: Sozialwissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>613.2: Diätetik</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-02-05T15:57:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-05T15:57:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2637</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2637</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2637</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Ringvorlesung Umwelt, Technische Universität München, Deutschland, 10. Juni 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18494</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-11T17:29:51Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Das digitale Produktions-Puzzle</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sedding, Helmut</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.5: Produktionssteuerung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>670: Industrielle und handwerkliche Fertigung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-10-23T07:55:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-10-23T07:55:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.technische-rundschau.ch/archiv/2019/07/das-digitale-produktions-puzzle/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18494</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1662-3096</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0040-1498</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Technische Rundschau</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Swiss Professional Media</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13049</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-04T12:57:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Karriere und Geschlecht : eine netzwerktheoretische Analyse</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Scheidegger, Nicoline</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Osterloh, Margit</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Netzwerk</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wissensgesellschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Karriere</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gender</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>300: Sozialwissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-11-19T15:10:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-19T15:10:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13049</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13049</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13049</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3-87988-960-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Jenseits der Geschlechterdifferenz? : Geschlechterverhältnisse in der Informations- und Wissensgesellschaft</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Arbeit, Innovation und Nachhaltigkeit</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Hampp</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1281</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:52:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_53</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Vaginal Seeding : Chance oder Risiko?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Baumann, Fabienne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gianom, Michelle</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Vaginal Seeding</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mikrobiom</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sectio</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Darmkeimbesiedelung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Entscheidend für die Etablierung des menschlichen Mikrobioms ist der fetale Kontakt mit der mütterlichen Vaginalflora bei der Geburt. Da Neugeborene bei einer primären Sectio hauptsächlich mit Haut- und Umgebungsbakterien in Berührung kommen, resultiert daraus eine verzögerte Darmkeimbesiedelung und eine veränderte Darmflorazusammensetzung.&#13;
Zunehmend werden Krankheiten wie Asthma, Zöliakie, Diabetes und Adipositas mit der Sectio-Entbindung in Verbindung gebracht. Einen Zusammenhang zwischen diesen Erkrankungen und der verzögerten Darmkeimbesiedelung scheint gegeben. Das Vaginal Seeding kann dem möglicherweise entgegenwirken. Dabei wird das Neugeborene nach der Sectio mit mütterlichem Vaginalsekret eingerieben.&#13;
In dieser themengeleiteten Bachelorarbeit wird aktuelle Literatur verwendet, um die Darmkeimbesiedelung beim Neugeborenen aufzuzeigen, die Auswirkungen von Vaginal Seeding zu beschrieben sowie dessen Vor- und Nachteile zu diskutieren. Heb-ammenrelevante Inhalte werden herausgearbeitet und Praxisempfehlungen formuliert.&#13;
Die Pionierstudie zeigt eine signifikante Verbesserung der initialen Darmkeimbesiedelung des Neugeborenen durch Vaginal Seeding. Die Ergebnisse sind wegen der kleinen Probandenzahl nicht allgemein übertragbar. Aufgrund der geringen Forschungslage sind Aussagen über Langzeitauswirkungen nicht möglich.&#13;
Weitere Forschung ist notwendig, um evidenzbasierte Praxisempfehlungen abgeben zu können. Die verfügbaren Daten zeigen, dass die Darmkeimbesiedelung ein hochkomplexer Vorgang ist, welcher durch verschiedene Faktoren beeinflusst wird und bereits intrauterin beginnt.&#13;
Vaginal Seeding ist eine kostengünstige und einfache Methode, in welcher die Verfasserinnen Potential sehen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2017-07-19T09:19:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-07-19T09:19:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1274</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1274</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1281</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1281</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1281</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>96 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2392</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-02T07:58:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Fetale Mortalität bei Einlingen ab Termin : eine Analyse bundesdeutscher Perinataldaten 2004-2013</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schwarz, C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Weiss, E.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Loytved, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schäfers, R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>König, T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Heusser, P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Berger, B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-01-31T16:05:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-31T16:05:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1614</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1055/s-0034-1398659</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1614</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1055/s-0034-1398659</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2392</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2392</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2392</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0948-2393</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1439-1651</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Zeitschrift für Geburtshilfe und Neonatologie</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Thieme</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21656</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-11T15:33:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kündigungsfreiheit ein Mythos?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Vögeli Galli, Nicole</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>344: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Arbeits-, Sozial-, Bildungs- und Kulturrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Im Schweizerischen Arbeitsrecht gilt der Grundsatz der Kündigungsfreiheit für beide Parteien (Art. 335 Abs. 1 OR). Allerdings gelten nicht zu vernachlässigende Einschränkungen und Hürden zulasten des Arbeitgebers bei ordentlichen Kündigungen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-02-11T15:33:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-02-11T15:33:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21656</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21656</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21656</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1664-5693</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Personal Schweiz</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>WEKA</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22798</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-12T10:44:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Influence of interfacial force models and population balance models on the kLa value in stirred bioreactors</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Seidel, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eibl, Dieter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Bioreactor characterization</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>CFD simulation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Drag force</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Interfacial force</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>kLa value</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Multiphase modeling</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Oxygen transfer rate</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Population balance model</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>660: Technische Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Optimal oxygen supply is vitally important for the cultivation of aerobically growing cells, as it has a direct influence on cell growth and product formation. A process engineering parameter directly related to oxygen supply is the volumetric oxygen mass transfer coefficient kLa. It is the influences on kLa and computing time of different interfacial force and population balance models in stirred bioreactors that have been evaluated in this study. For this investigation, the OpenFOAM 7 open-source toolbox was utilized. Firstly, the Euler–Euler model with a constant bubble diameter was applied to a 2L scale bioreactor to statistically examine the influence of different interfacial models on the kLa value. It was shown that the kL model and the constant bubble diameter have the greatest influence on the calculated kLa value. To eliminate the problem of a constant bubble diameter and to take effects such as bubble breakup and coalescence into account, the Euler–Euler model was coupled with population balance models (PBM). For this purpose, four coalescence and five bubble breakup models were examined. Ultimately, it was established that, for all of the models tested, coupling computational fluid dynamics (CFD) with PBM resulted in better agreement with the experimental data than using the Euler–Euler model. However, it should be noted that the higher accuracy of the PBM coupled models requires twice the computation time.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-07-09T07:33:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-07-09T07:33:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-07-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.3390/pr9071185</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-22798</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.3390/pr9071185</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-22798</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22798</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22798</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22798</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2227-9717</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Processes</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>MDPI</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14815</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T14:53:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Reporting the unmeasurable : comparing swiss performance budgeting experience to IPSASB’s consultation paper on reporting service performance information</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rauskala, Iris Eliisa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fuchs, Sandro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fuhrimann, Sandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Performance budgeting</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>IPSAS</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>350: Öffentliche Verwaltung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>657: Rechnungswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In the German-speaking countries, the concept of performance budgeting occurred in the mid-1990s as an element of the countries’ broader NPM-concepts, namely the “new steering model” (Neues Steuerungsmodell) in Germany and “outcome-oriented steering” (Wirkungsorientierte Verwaltungsführung) in Switzerland, which also had influences on Austria. The concepts share the shift in focus from resources to results of government activities (Schedler/Summermatter 2009).From an international perspective, there is an ever increasing interest in performance budgeting as documented by the latest OECD study (2007). The best-known, earlier approaches to performance budgets, like the Planning-Programming-Budgeting system (PPBS) in the 1960s, Management by objectives (MBO) and Zero-based budgeting (ZBB) in the 1970s are said to have failed or were unpractical for the one or the other reason, leading Schick (2007) to his famous saying: “Performance budgeting is easy to explain but has been hard to implement.” In October 2011, IPSASB started the consultation process on its paper on Reporting Service Performance Information. The consultation was concluded in April 2012 and received over 30 comments. It is now planned to issue a Recommended Practice Guideline (RPG) for those public sector entities applying IPSAS.In Switzerland, performance budgets are generally referred to as “Globalbudgets”. Especially state (canton) and local governments have long experience with such reforms as they were early birds when they first introduced performance budgeting in the 1990s (Bergmann, 2009). At the moment, 11 out of 26 cantons have adopted performance budgets, covering nearly 65% of the financial volume of all cantons (measured in expenses of the current budget). The earliest experiences (Zurich) are dating back to 1995, with the latest canton (Schwyz) having switched to a new model of budgeting in 2011 (Econcept, 2011). Looking at the state of local financial management, performance budgeting has been implemented within a context of stable public finances. Already in the late 70s of the last century, Swiss cantons and municipalities started adopting a harmonized accounting framework reflecting the characteristics of accrual accounting and budgeting. Debt-brakes and mid-term planning are an issue for all cantons. It seems as if the public households could come out quite unscathed from the recent economic crisis (Doytchinov/Luck, 2012).Given such favourable circumstances, why bother with a new budgeting approach? What are the expected benefits of performance budgeting, and what is then the performance in delivering them? To give some answers on these questions, the paper starts with a brief introduction to the Swiss political and macro-economic setting, before lining out the context of Swiss performance budgeting experiences. Next, this article will analyse the available performance budgeting documents, legislation and evaluation reports to examine approaches towards performance reporting of Swiss German speaking cantons. The findings will then be compared to the Consultation Paper of IPSASB and comments as a benchmark to compare Swiss practice with international experience on performance budgeting.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-01-31T10:27:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-31T10:27:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14815</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14815</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14815</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>XVIII IRSPM Conference, Ottawa, Canada, 9-11 April 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>IRSPM International Research Society for Public Management</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16875</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-04T11:21:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Was ist die digitale Transformation und digitales Marketing?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Klaas, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Marketing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Der Begriff der digitalen Transformation ist seit den 2010er Jahren ein viel genutzter und medial präsenter Begriff, wenn es um die Digitalisierung unterschiedlicher Aspekte des unternehmerischen Handels geht. Das Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) definiert digitale Transformation als die Nutzung digitaler Technologien zur signifikanten Verbesserung des Unternehmens mit Fokus auf neuen Geschäftsmodellen, neuen Formen der Kundeninteraktion oder der Verbesserung der Abläufe im Unternehmen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-04-24T14:09:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-24T14:09:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16875</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16875</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16875</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-03909-346-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Marketing : Konzepte - Instrumente - Aufgaben</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Versus</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15853</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-04T12:57:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Efficient network management in the automotive industry : the DaimlerChrysler case</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kucza, Gunther</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658: Allgemeines Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-03-06T15:59:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-06T15:59:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15853</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15853</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15853</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Final Review Meeting of the European Commission, Athen, Greece, 7. April 2003</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5070</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T10:36:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Rede</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Perrin, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Oral communication</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Speech</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Media linguistics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Communication science</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T12:52:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T12:52:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5070</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5070</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5070</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3-531-13535-X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Lexikon Kommunikations- und Medienwissenschaft</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Studienbücher zur Kommunikations- und Medienwissenschaft</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6094</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-20T06:25:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kosten senken durch Lageroptimierung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hosang, Jürg</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Kosten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lager</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658: Allgemeines Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-25T08:04:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-25T08:04:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6094</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6094</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6094</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>FH-Vision</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>VASI Archimedes</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6408</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-26T07:17:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ethanol als Frostschutzmittel in Erdwärmesonden</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hubbuch, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>620: Ingenieurwesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-01T10:35:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-01T10:35:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6408</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6408</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6408</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1664-1000</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>C2H5OH - Alkohol und Politik</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Eidgenössische Alkoholverwaltung</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10782</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T10:53:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Intense, carrier frequency and bandwidth tunable quasi single-cycle pulses from an organic emitter covering the Terahertz frequency gap</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Vicario, C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Monoszlai, B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jazbinsek, M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lee, S.-H.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kwon, O.-P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hauri, C. P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In Terahertz (THz) science, one of the long-standing challenges has been the formation of spectrally dense, single-cycle pulses with tunable duration and spectrum across the frequency range of 0.1-15 THz (THz gap). This frequency band, lying between the electronically and optically accessible spectra hosts important molecular fingerprints and collective modes which cannot be fully controlled by present strong-field THz sources. We present a method that provides powerful single-cycle THz pulses in the THz gap with a stable absolute phase whose duration can be continuously selected between 68 fs and 1100 fs. The loss-free and chirp-free technique is based on optical rectification of a wavelength-tunable pump pulse in the organic emitter HMQ-TMS that allows for tuning of the spectral bandwidth from 1 to more than 7 octaves over the entire THz gap. The presented source tunability of the temporal carrier frequency and spectrum expands the scope of spectrally dense THz sources to time-resolved nonlinear THz spectroscopy in the entire THz gap. This opens new opportunities towards ultrafast coherent control over matter and light.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-18T14:09:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-18T14:09:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-09-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3987</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1038/srep14394</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3987</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1038/srep14394</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10782</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10782</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10782</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2045-2322</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>26400005</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Scientific Reports</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Nature Publishing Group</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19021</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-08-11T13:36:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The utility of nursing instruments for daily screening for delirium : delirium causes substantial functional impairment</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bode, Leonie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Isler, Florian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fuchs, Simon</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marquetand, Justus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Petry, Heidi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ernst, Jutta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schubert, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Garcia Nuñez, David</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>von Känel, Roland</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Boettger, Soenke</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Assessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Delirium</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Electronic Patient Assessment-Acute Care (ePA-AC)</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Functional impairment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nursing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616.8: Neurologie und Krankheiten des Nervensystems</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenzen.ch)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Nursing assessments have been recommended for the daily screening for delirium; however, the utility of individual items have not yet been tested. In a first step in establishing the potential of the electronic Patient Assessment-Acute Care (ePA-AC) as such, the impact of delirium on the functional domains was assessed.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-01-08T13:58:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-01-08T13:58:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-11-27</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1017/S1478951519001019</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-19021</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1017/S1478951519001019</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-19021</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19021</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19021</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19021</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1478-9515</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1478-9523</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>31771675</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Palliative &amp; Supportive Care</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Cambridge University Press</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16035</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-05-13T13:16:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Debt-sensitive majority rules</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Becker, Johannes Gerd</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Grimm, Oliver</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gersbach, Hans</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Public Good</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Debt restriction</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Debt-sensitive majority rule</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fiscal policy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Public debt</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Simple majority rule</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Voting</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>330: Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>We examine debt-sensitive majority rules. According to such a rule, the higher a planned public debt, the higher the parliamentary majority required to approve it. In a two-period model we compare debt-sensitive majority rules with the simple majority rule when individuals differ regarding their benefits from public-good provision. We establish the existence of Condorcet winners under debt-sensitive majority rules and derive their properties. We find that equilibrium debt-levels are lower under the debt-sensitive majority rule if preferences regarding public goods are sufficiently heterogeneous and if the impact of debt on future public-good provision is sufficiently strong. We illustrate how debt-sensitive majority rules act as political stabilizers in the event of negative macroeconomic shocks.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-03-13T14:49:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-13T14:49:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16035</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16035</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16035</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>CEPR Discussion Paper</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>52 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Centre for Economic Policy Research</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/685</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T10:43:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_236</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_237</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Untersuchung der Bereitschaft zur Inanspruchnahme von psychologischen Angeboten in der Türkei (Ankara) : welche Gründe führen wann und wen in die psychologische Beratung?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ataman, Sevinç</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Psychologische Beratung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Psychotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ankara</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Inanspruchnahme</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:08:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:08:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-685</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-685</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/685</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/685</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/685</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>92 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24995</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-05-19T03:08:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Exploring the potential for sustainable accessibility across settlement types : a Swedish case</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Larsson, Anders</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Elldér, Erik</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vafeiadis, Evangelos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Curtis, Carey</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Steiner, Albert</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Sustainable accessibility</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Daily amenities</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Settlement typology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Small urban area</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Rural area</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Modal accessibility gap</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>307: Gemeinschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>380: Verkehr</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The potential for residents of smaller urban and rural areas to benefit from sustainable accessibility is an under-researched area. This paper explores accessibility to important every-day amenities within short travel times and how this differs across geography and mode of travel. The analysis draws on a combination of novel open-source data of the transport system and official Swedish register data of the total population of individuals and workplaces geocoded at a 100-meter resolution. The findings show considerable variation in accessibility to everyday amenities by travel mode for different settlement types. While the car provides good accessibility, short trips by bicycle are a very competitive alternative in urban and suburban areas. Access to every-day amenities by active travel modes is limited outside urban areas. Employing accessibility analysis by settlement type offers a powerful policy support tool for planners charged with developing measures to address sustainable accessibility for small urban and rural areas.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-05-18T11:58:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-05-18T11:58:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trd.2022.103297</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-24995</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.trd.2022.103297</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-24995</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24995</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24995</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24995</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1361-9209</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1879-2340</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Transportation Research Part D: Transport and Environment</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16977</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-05-02T14:01:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Product Manager : Anwälte der Kundschaft an der Schnittstelle zur Entwicklungsabteilung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Steffen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fuchs, Rainer</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Marketing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Entwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Jobprofil</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Product Manager</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Unterhalten sich Product Manager aus unterschiedlichen Unternehmen über ihre Tätigkeit, stellen sie oftmals grosse Unterschiede fest. Je nach Branche oder Organisationsform ergeben sich unterschiedliche Anforderungen. Lassen sich die Aufgaben der Product Manager also überhaupt einheitlich beschreiben?</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-05-02T14:01:58Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-05-02T14:01:58Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16977</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16977</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16977</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7281-3701-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Jobprofile im Marketing</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>SML essentials</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>vdf Hochschulverlag</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16141</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-04T12:56:51Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Knowledge transfer barriers in manufacturing networks</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Deflorin, Patricia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Scherrer, Maike</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schöbel, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Manufacturing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Transfer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Network</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Knowledge</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Knowledge transfer within a manufacturing network is challenging. However, to unlock the potential of internationally dispersed networks, knowledge transfer is crucial. We add to literature as we not only focus on the coordination mechanism needed to coordinate a network but enhance the framework with plant management behaviour. Based on social-psychological theories we analyse what hinders or enhances knowledge transfer within a manufacturing network. Finally, we present a conceptual framework of manufacturing network coordination which combines macro (coordination mechanism) and micro level (knowledge sharing behaviour) research. In addition, we discuss which results are contradicting, depending on operations management or social psychological theory perspective.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-03-18T15:11:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-18T15:11:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16141</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16141</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16141</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Knowledge Transfer and Cultural Diversity in MNC, Neuchâtel, 1-2 July 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5915</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-12T13:18:32Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Eine Testkonstruktion mit graphologischen Daten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Toggweiler, Stephan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Graphologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>GraphoPro</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>NEO-PI-R</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schriftmerkmal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>155: Differentielle Psychologie und Entwicklungspsychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-16T14:31:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-16T14:31:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5915</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5915</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5915</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Inaugurationsfeier des Instituts für Handschriftwissenschaften IfH, Zürich, 2017</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24225</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-17T15:06:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>DevOps adoption : challenges &amp; barriers</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Krey, Mike</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kabbout, Ahmad</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Osmani, Lavdrim</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Saliji, Armend</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Agile and lean: organization, product and development</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Devops implementation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Devops practice</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Literature review</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>As a modern software engineering paradigm, DevOps has recently gained increasing acceptance in the industry as a set of practices and cultural values to address daily dynamic software demands. While the rising trend of DevOps and its characteristics and challenges have often been characterized by practitioner communities and academic research circles, there is still a lack of a thorough understanding of how to tackle DevOps adoptions. This paper aims to help fill this gap by identifying, discussing, and summarizing current academic and practitioner DevOps adoption &amp; implementation research. Our findings provide a basis for theoretical, empirical, or design-oriented research for IS scholars, that has the potential to be of practical importance. Our goal is to improve understanding of DevOps adoption by uncovering ambiguities in terms, conceptual conflations, and ideas underlying different uses of the concept as well as providing methods to deal with common challenges in the adoption process.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-02-10T15:17:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-02-10T15:17:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.24251/HICSS.2022.877</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-24225</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.24251/HICSS.2022.877</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-24225</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24225</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24225</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24225</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-0-9981331-5-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2572-6853</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the 55th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>55th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS), virtual, 3-7 January 2022</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>University of Hawai'i at Manoa</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5221</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:39:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Squaring the sunny circle? On balancing distributive justice of power grid costs and incentives for solar prosumers</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kubli, Merla</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Self-consumption</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Death spiral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Grid tariff design</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Net purchase and sale</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Net metering</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Grid cost recovery</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333.79: Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>338.927: Umweltökonomie und nachhaltige Entwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Solar prosumers are about to revolutionize the power sector. Utilities are challenged in recovering the costs of distribution grids, as parts of their revenue basis decreases through self-consumption. Adjusting the grid tariff sets off a reinforcing feedback loop that increases the attractiveness of solar investments, but also leads to a distribution effect between solar prosumers and conventional consumers. The question is: How to recover distribution grid costs equitable without hampering the diffusion of solar power? Can the two criteria be fulfilled at the same time, or is do we aim for squaring a circle? To address this question, I present a System Dynamics simulation model designed to understand the interactions and assess these competing goals. The occurring distribution effect under the volumetric grid tariff with net purchase and sale appears to be rather limited. Simulation experiments reveal that grid tariff designs strongly influence investments for solar power. A capacity tariff can reduce deviations from the cost causation principle of solar prosumers and incentivizes investments in decentralized storage solutions to reduce peak demand. Nevertheless, also the capacity tariff causes a distribution effect.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T09:18:58Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T09:18:58Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.enpol.2017.11.054</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.enpol.2017.11.054</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5221</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5221</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5221</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0301-4215</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1873-6777</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Energy Policy</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19444</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-14T09:33:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Organhaftung im Sozialversicherungsrecht</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bärtschi, Harald</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stohwasser, Stephanie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>344: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Arbeits-, Sozial-, Bildungs- und Kulturrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-02-14T09:33:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-02-14T09:33:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19444</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19444</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19444</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1661-7673</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Gesellschafts- und Kapitalmarktrecht</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Dike</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9219</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-07-01T14:29:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Project placement ‘enabling occupation’ in Switzerland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Arbenz-Purt, Dietlinde</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Project placement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615.8515: Ergotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-08-17T13:18:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-17T13:18:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1080/14473828.2016.1151680</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1080/14473828.2016.1151680</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9219</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9219</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9219</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1447-3828</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>World Federation of Occupational Therapists Bulletin</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Taylor &amp; Francis</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1863</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T11:00:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Fully convolutional neural networks for newspaper article segmentation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Meier, Benjamin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stadelmann, Thilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stampfli, Jan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Arnold, Marek</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cieliebak, Mark</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Semantic segmentation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>CNN</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Deep learning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Datalab</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>006: Spezielle Computerverfahren</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Segmenting newspaper pages into articles that semantically belong together is a necessary prerequisite for article-based information retrieval on print media collections like e.g. archives and libraries. It is challenging due to vastly differing&#13;
layouts of papers, various content types and different languages, but commercially very relevant for e.g. media monitoring. &#13;
We present a semantic segmentation approach based on the visual appearance of each page. We apply a fully convolutional neural network (FCN) that we train in an end-to-end fashion to transform the input image into a segmentation mask in one pass. We show experimentally that the FCN performs very well: it outperforms a deep learning-based commercial solution by a large margin in terms of segmentation quality while in addition being computationally two orders of magnitude more efficient.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2017-12-15T07:48:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-12-15T07:48:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1533</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1533</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1863</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1863</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1863</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the 14th IAPR International Conference on Document Analysis and Recognition (ICDAR)</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>14th IAPR International Conference on Document Analysis and Recognition (ICDAR 2017), Kyoto Japan, 13-15 November 2017</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>CPS</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12157</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-27T13:28:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wenn Menschen Unternehmen schaden : wer sind die Täter?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hardegger, Simon Carl</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Boss, Patrick</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.3: Personalmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>LEADERSHIP UND MANAGEMENT - RECRUITING Dunkle Persönlichkeit</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-25T16:07:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-25T16:07:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.hrtoday.ch/de/article/dunkle-persoenlichkeit-mitarbeiter-schadet-unternehmen-teil-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12157</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2235-8471</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>HR Today</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ALMA Medien</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14548</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T09:11:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Implementation of collaborative strategies and multiple mentoring models to facilitate peer learning in clinical education</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hartmeier, Anita</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ernst, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Purpose: The purpose of this project was to introduce new collaborative education models into clinical education in a Swiss hospital setting. It was intended to provide and enhance opportunities of peer assisted learning for physiotherapy students within their clinical placements and facilitate clinical educators to reflect on learning-theory oriented models and methods of the facilitation process of students.

Relevance: Motivation to adopt different approaches for clinical education and facilitation of students´ learning has been triggered by several contextual circumstances. The transition of physiotherapy education from technical colleges to universities of applied sciences led to reflections on respective potential impacts for the clinical education setting. Second, an anticipated shortage of clinical educators, in addition to transitionally higher numbers of PT students raised concerns about scant resources for appropriate facilitation of students. Finally, the changing environment of service delivery in the hospital had to be considered. Furthermore an increasing number of papers from different fields have shown that peer assisted learning and peer collaboration are highly relevant for learning in clinical placements.

Description: In the first phase, five clinical educators reviewed as a group, the literature about clinical education models (Lekkas et al. 2007; Strohschein et al. 2002) and peer assisted learning (Ladyshewsky 2000 &amp; 2006). In a second phase a flexible multiple mentoring model alongside collaborative student sessions with and without support by clinical educators was piloted and adopted in. Feedback from the involved clinical educators led to some ongoing adjustments, and the development of a "tool box" containing a list of different questions, tasks, and instructions of case presentations and discussions.

Evaluation: The newly implemented educational approaches were continuously evaluated by using a semi-structured debriefing interview with each student at the end of their clinical placement. Interview questions cover advantages and problems experienced with the collaborative settings as well as suggestions for improvement. Results led to further improvements of these introduced settings of a respective content analysis will be presented at the conference.

Conclusions: In general, peer learning opportunities were highly appreciated by most students, although some challenging issues were identified, such as questions of group dynamics. However, feedbacks from students support the notion that such collaborative learning approaches are also suitable for students with different levels of studies and from different universities of applied sciences. Furthermore, the "tool box" developed is a helpful means to support variability within facilitation processes and to adjust to variations of group dynamics of students.

Implications: The positive experiences from such a bottom-up and pragmatic approach for introducing innovative educational strategies within a single clinical education setting lead us to believe that such an approach could be considered by other institutions. Organizational and structural changes for clinical education in our institution proved to be a helpful and valuable means for further development of the involved clinical educators, such as moving from a more traditional and teacher-centred approach to a more student-centred one.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-01-23T11:38:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-23T11:38:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14548</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14548</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14548</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>3rd European Congress on Physiotherapy Education, Vienna, Austria, 8 -10 November 2012</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23711</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-14T15:28:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ausgrenzung unter Ausgegrenzten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Leite de Araújo, Erilene</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Herzig, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Marginalisierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Norbert Elias</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sozialarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Alkoholismus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Wer neu zu einer Gruppe stösst, muss sich beweisen. Diese Dynamik beschrieb einst der Soziologe Norbert Elias in England. Sie spielt auch in Mikrokosmen wie in einem Alkoholikertreffpunkt in Zürich.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-12-11T12:42:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-12-11T12:42:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23711</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23711</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23711</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23711</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23711</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Sozial : Magazin der ZHAW Soziale Arbeit</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5116</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:01:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Teaching instrumental competence in an e-learning environment : a Swiss perspective</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Massey, Gary</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riediger, Hellmut</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lenz, Simon</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Translation pedagogy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Instrumental competence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Information literacy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>E-learning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Cognitive models used to identify and evaluate translation competence generally postulate a cluster of interacting, continuously evolving sub-competencies. Such models represent the acquisition and application of translation competence as a dynamic, open-ended process, suggesting that translator training should stress the development of procedural knowledge and skills. Initial research by PACTE (2005) indicates that the acquisition of the instrumental sub-competence, identified as "knowledge related to the use of documentation sources and information technologies applied to translation" (PACTE 2005), is a major feature distinguishing the problem-solving decisions taken by professional translators from those of novices. Trainers and practitioners have long recognised the need to integrate training in instrumental competence into translation curricula. Efficient and effective solutions are offered by the deployment of blended e-learning scenarios, with students receiving authentically situated instruction in an online environment and direct exposure to some or all of the tools and procedures of professional translation practice. This paper will describe e-learning offerings in instrumental competence developed since 2002 for the Degree Programme in Translation and the Bachelor's Programme in Language and Communication at the Zurich University of Applied Sciences, Winterthur. It will consider the process of designing, organising and integrating multilingual entry-level blended-learning courses on research methodology and information management for target groups of up to 200 students, presenting the problems, solutions, results and experiences involved, and focusing on the particular challenges posed by interactivity, collaboration and motivation.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T13:51:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T13:51:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5116</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5116</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5116</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-973-611-521-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Translation technology in translation classes</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>eCoLoTrain Workshop, Lubljana, Slovenia, 31 August - 1 September 2007</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Academica Traductologie</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21744</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-08-11T13:36:47Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Network‐based ionospheric gradient monitoring to support GBAS</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Caamano, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Juan, José Miguel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Felux, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gerbeth, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>González‐Casado, Guillermo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sanz, Jaume</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>GNSS</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ionosphere</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>GBAS</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>629: Luftfahrt- und Fahrzeugtechnik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Large ionospheric gradients acting between a Ground Based Augmentation System (GBAS) reference station and an aircraft on approach could lead to hazardous position errors if undetected. Current GBAS stations provide solutions against this threat that rely on the use of “worst‐case” conservative threat models, which could limit the availability of the system.&#13;
&#13;
This paper presents a methodology capable of detecting ionospheric gradients in real time and estimating the actual threat model parameters based on a network of dual‐frequency and multi‐constellation GNSS monitoring stations. First, we evaluate the performance of our algorithm with synthetic gradients that are simulated over the nominal measurements recorded by a reference network in Alaska. Afterwards, we also assess it with one real ionospheric gradient measured by the same network.&#13;
&#13;
Results with both simulated gradients and a real gradient show the potential to support GBAS by detecting and estimating these gradients instead of always using “worst‐case” models.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-02-18T10:31:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-02-18T10:31:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-02-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1002/navi.411</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-21744</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1002/navi.411</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-21744</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21744</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21744</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21744</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0028-1522</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2161-4296</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Navigation : Journal of the Institute of Navigation</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Wiley</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7780</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-20T09:51:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Forecasting correlation structures</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schüle, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ott, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schwendner, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>510: Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Often the signature of a complex system is a couple of empirically found time series. In many cases the exact processes generating these series are unknown and a merely descriptive data analysis is undertaken. A popular tool to describe the structural behaviour of the complex system is thereby the analysis of the correlation structure, i.e., the system of pairwise correlations. &#13;
As the correlation coefficients are calculated from a given data set, the analysis usually does not allow to forecast the future correlated behaviour of the system. However, in many examples of complex systems, the dynamic correlation structure shows certain patterns that form and cluster and dissipate again over time. If there are thus certain consistent patterns in the analyzed correlation structure to be found, the joint behaviour of the system may be forecasted, at least for short time periods. &#13;
We present such an approach to forecast correlation matrices by means of a financial time series example. By analyzing the eigenmodes of the correlation matrices for oscillation patterns the main market dynamics are identified. Then, the principal eigenmode oscillations are forecasted by multivariate autoregressive and mean-reversion models allowing to infer the future correlation structure for certain time periods. The inferred correlation matrices are further regularized and compared to benchmark models.  &#13;
The proposed method can be of use in any field with the need of analyzing empirical correlation structures, e.g. in climate research.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-09T14:34:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-09T14:34:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-06-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.ini.uzh.ch/~lorimert/NDES2017/assets/NDES2017_programme_booklet.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7780</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>NDES 2017, 25th Nonlinear Dynamics of Electronic Systems Conference, Zernez, 5-7 June 2017</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22929</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-08-02T14:33:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Pflegekind und endlich 18?! Wie erleben Pflegekinder ihre Volljährigkeit und welche Bedeutung hat diese für sie?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Werner, Karin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Pflegekind</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Care Leaver</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Jugendalter</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kinder- und Jugendhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.7: Jugendhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-07-30T13:47:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-07-30T13:47:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-05-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22929</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22929</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22929</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Online-Seminar für Pflegeeltern und Fachkräfte der Pflegekinderhilfe, PFAD Deutschland, 28. Mai 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/374</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:43:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_51</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Spielfähigkeit von Kindern mit ADHS und deren Spielkameraden : wie beeinflussen sich Kinder mit ADHS und ihre normal entwickelten Spielkameraden gegenseitig in ihrer Spielfähigkeit? Nadine Keller, Lindenweg 32, 6033 Buchrain, S08276651 Stephanie Zillig</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Keller, Nadine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zillig, Stephanie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.8515: Ergotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:04:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:04:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-374</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-374</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/374</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/374</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/374</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20759</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-10-30T04:01:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_53</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Essstörungen in der Schwangerschaft - ein Risiko? : inwiefern beeinflussen maternale Essstörungen (Anorexia nervosa und Bulimia nervosa) in der Schwangerschaft den Schwangerschaftsverlauf, die Geburt und das fetale Outcome?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tarjan, Jessica</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Russo, Norina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Eating disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pregnancy outcome</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Obstetric outcome</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fetal outcome</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Midwifery</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616.8: Neurologie und Krankheiten des Nervensystems</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Hintergrund: Von Anorexia nervosa und Bulimia nervosa betroffene Frauen weisen eine gestörte Wahrnehmung des eigenen Körperbildes auf (ICD 10, 1992). Die regelmässige und ausgewogene Nahrungsaufnahme der Mutter ist für die physiologische Gewichtszunahme und Entwicklung des Kindes jedoch dringend notwendig.&#13;
&#13;
Ziel: Ziel dieser Arbeit ist es, Hebammen für mögliche Auswirkungen bezüglich Schwangerschaftsverlauf, Geburt und fetalem Outcome von mütterlichen Essstörungen in der Schwangerschaft zu sensibilisieren.&#13;
&#13;
Methode: Dieses Ziel wird mittels eines Literaturreviews bearbeitet. Die verwendete Literatur setzt sich aus Fachdatenbankrecherchen sowie Fachbüchern zusammen. Die systematische Würdigung wird mit Hilfe der Vorlage von Law &amp; Letts (1998) kritisch beurteilt und ergänzend mit Fachliteratur diskutiert.&#13;
&#13;
Ergebnisse: Die verwendeten Studien erzielten keine einheitlichen Ergebnisse. Tendenziell lässt sich aber sagen, dass eine deutliche Korrelation zwischen maternalen Essstörungen in der Schwangerschaft und negativen Outcomes in Bezug auf die Schwangerschaft, Geburt sowie das kindliche Outcome bestehen.&#13;
&#13;
Schlussfolgerung: In dieser Arbeit konnte durch diverse Studien belegt werden, dass Essstörungen in der Schwangerschaft eine deutliche Relation zu negativen geburtshilflichen Outcomes haben. Es ist daher unerlässlich, dass eine Hebamme, welche eine betroffene Frau betreut, sich in das Thema Essstörungen vertieft.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-10-29T15:09:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-10-29T15:09:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-20759</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-20759</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20759</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20759</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20759</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>122 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16525</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T14:06:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Why do we feel responsible? : developing a model of stakeholder responsibility perceptions</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Voegtlin, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Butz, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>CSR</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Managerial perception</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Stakeholder salience</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The article forwards a concept of managers’ stakeholder responsibility perceptions. It develops a theoretical framework that specifies antecedents and outcomes related to the degree of responsibility people working in organizations perceive toward specific stakeholders. More specifically, it argues that the degree of stakeholder responsibility is dependent on managers’ perception about their task-related obligations, their relational obligations and their social-welfare obligations. These in turn, are driven by individuals’ value orientation and societal expectations about the job responsibilities of managers. Finally, the perceived degree of responsibility has implications for managers’ integrative stakeholder behavior and has consequences for their well-being. The article discusses moderating influences between responsibility perceptions and the behavioral and psychological consequences. It thereby advances theory on stakeholder salience and prioritization by positioning stakeholder responsibility perception a concept that allows for both/and rather than either/or solutions to stakeholder engagement.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-04-05T13:57:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-05T13:57:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5465/ambpp.2016.15875abstract</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.5465/ambpp.2016.15875abstract</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16525</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16525</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16525</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0065-0668</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2151-6561</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Academy of Management Conference, Anaheim CA, USA, August 2017</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Academy of Management Proceedings</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Academy of Management</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9881</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T09:27:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Policy integration : mapping the different concepts</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tosun, Jale</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lang, Achim</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Boundary-spanning policy regime</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Comprehensive planning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Holistic government and governance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Joined-up government</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Policy coherence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Policy integration and mainstreaming</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Whole of government</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>320: Politik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>A growing number of studies have examined the collaboration of actors from two or more policy domains in order to integrate aims and concerns derived from one policy domain into another. In our literature review, we refer to this empirical phenomenon as ‘policy integration’, exemplified by the Health in All Policies approach. Despite the wealth of literature on the subject, the scientific community only has access to a portion of the insights that have come out of this field of research, due primarily to the fact that policy integration is discussed using a variety of different terms, which tend to be specific to the policy domain under investigation. To facilitate a more inclusive scientific debate on policy integration, we provide a comprehensive overview of the different terminologies associated with policy integration and analyse the recurring themes in the respective literature strands. What is the motivation for policy-makers to promote policy integration? What is the design of the instruments used for policy integration? How does policy integration affect the policy-making process? And how well does policy integration perform? These are the four questions guiding our study.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-29T09:44:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-29T09:44:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1080/01442872.2017.1339239</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1080/01442872.2017.1339239</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9881</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9881</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9881</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0144-2872</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1470-1006</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Policy Studies</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Routledge</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3016</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-26T07:16:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Antifreeze Beschichtungen für Rotorblätter</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Siegmann, Konstantin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hirayama, Martina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>660: Technische Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Günstige Winde an vereisungsgefährdeten Standorten führen dort zu immer mehr Windenergieanlagen. Eisabweisende Beschichtungen sollen dabei helfen, die Rotorblattvereisung zu reduzieren. Spezielle Eiweisse von arktischen Fischen öffnen den Weg für neuartige Beschichtungen.&#13;
	 </dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-23T15:37:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-23T15:37:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3016</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3016</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3016</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1660-9778</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Erneuerbare Energien</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schweizerische Vereinigung für Sonnenenergie</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8031</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T10:33:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Durch die Erfahrung der Betroffenen die Wirksamkeit der Mobilitätsfördernden Pflegeintervention besser verstehen : eine phänomenologische Studie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Suter-Riederer, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Imhof, Lorenz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-07-13T07:13:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-13T07:13:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8031</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8031</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8031</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Pflegekongress, Wien, Österreich, 24.-25. November 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13425</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-13T12:22:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>A three-layer severity index for power system voltage stability assessment using time-series from dynamic simulations</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Vanfretti, Luigi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Segundo Sevilla, Felix Rafael</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Voltage stability</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Single voltage source model</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Time-domain simulations</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>This paper presents a three-layer voltage stability index computed using time-series obtained from dynamic simulations. The proposed index provides the distance with respect to voltage and power limits. Voltage, active and reactive power signals, which are determined using time series from dynamic simulations, are used to compute the index. The methodology assumes that no other information about the system (model) is available. A set of 3 different simulations at different loading levels and a given contingency are required to calculate the index. In the first layer, a two-element vector indicates if a power or a voltage limit was violated. In the second layer, a vector is used to specify which power and voltage loading level was violated and finally, in the third layer a matrix is used to retrieve precise information about which power and voltage limit has been violated in pre- or post-contingency. The index can analyze simultaneously different buses. The proposed index is illustrated using synthetic data and then tested using timedomain simulations on the KTH-Nordic32 system.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-30T13:24:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-30T13:24:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1109/ISGTEurope.2014.7028788</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1109/ISGTEurope.2014.7028788</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13425</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13425</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13425</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-4799-7720-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>IEEE PES Innovative Smart Grid Technologies, Europe</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>IEEE PES Innovative Smart Grid Technologies, Istanbul, Turkey, 12-15 October 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>IEEE</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4928</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-12-15T13:36:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Computerlinguistik und Sprachtechnologie : eine Einführung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carstensen, Kai-Uwe</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ebert, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Endriss, Cornelia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jekat, Susanne Johanna</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Klabunde, Ralf</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Langer, Hagen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Computerlinguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>410.285: Computerlinguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-09T13:59:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-09T13:59:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2001</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4928</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4928</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4928</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3-8274-1027-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Spektrum Lehrbuch</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>581 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Spektrum Akademischer Verlag</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19542</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-25T10:37:13Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Language and human factors : growing digital together</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kavanagh, Morgan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Delorme Benites, Alice</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ehrensberger-Dow, Maureen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Massey, Gary</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schaub-Torsello, Romina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Agency</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Human factor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Intervention</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>378: Hochschulbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.0071: Sprachdidaktik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>While increasing digitization is attractive in many domains, it is also a source of concern and scepticism in others. In education, especially in the areas of language learning and teaching, the introduction of digital tools can unnecessarily widen the gap between students and teachers if not done properly. Learners might value the accessibility and flexibility of new online language courses and resources even as they regret the reduced or lack of personal contact with native speakers. Educators might be wary of the promises of yet another new form of digital technology, having too often abandoned previous tools they had rushed to adopt and implement without enough preparation. Others might be too timid to engage in a paradigm shift from which they feel excluded. The mosaic of attitudes and opinions that contributes to these two extremes of learner- and teacher-centeredness deserves greater consideration, in particular the personal, cognitive and emotional factors that come into play when digitizing language teaching practices. More concretely, we are interested in exploring how to best empower educators to adopt digital practice as an integral part of their professional and teaching identity. The action research project we will report on, co-funded by swissuniversities and the ZHAW, focuses on the ergonomics of socio-technical systems and reflective practice. The objective of the project is to provide tertiary-level language and translation teachers with a space for exchange and learning, guided by more advanced peers in a situation created to promote collective learning. These learning exchange spaces build on the concept of proximal zones of development as described by Vygotsky - in other words, allowing teachers to move between what they already know and what they can accomplish with the help of colleagues with more digital experience. By moving away from the traditional model of ad hoc training in educational tools, where teachers are directly confronted  with what they cannot (yet) do, this action research project aims to radically change teachers' attitudes in the face of digital innovation and empower them to assume agency and appropriate new tools for their own purposes. Over the course of the two-year project, the effect of collaborative interventions are being monitored with techniques familiar from translation and writing process research (e.g. screen recordings, eye tracking, cued commentaries, and semi-structured interviews). We will report on the preliminary results from the first set of interventions and explain how such findings can be applied to other disciplines and professions to better understand the essentially human dimension of the digital transition.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-02-25T10:37:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-02-25T10:37:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-02-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19542</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19542</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19542</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Applied linguistics in the digital age : conference of the Swiss association for applied linguistics, Neuchâtel, 12-14 February 2020</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2989</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-10-25T12:37:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Investigating demands on language professionals : methodological challenges in exploring translation competence</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Massey, Gary</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ehrensberger-Dow, Maureen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Übersetzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Translationsprozessforschung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Berufspraxis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kompetenz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die professionellen Anforderungen an Sprachexperten sind in den letzten Jahren stark gestiegen und umfassen heute nicht mehr nur das Übersetzen im traditionellen Sinne sondern unter anderem auch die Revision von eigenen Übersetzungen und Texten, von fremden Übersetzungen sowie von Texten nicht-muttersprachlicher Autoren. Am Arbeitsplatz zeigt sich dieser Wandel in der Entwicklung neuer Software-Applikationen und neuer Geschäftsprozesse in vielen Übersetzungsdienstleistungsbetrieben. Im Bereich der Forschung wurde bisher allerdings nur wenig unternommen, um herauszufinden, welche Anforderungen diese Übersetzungs- und Schreibprozesse an die kognitiven Ressourcen stellen. Viele Übersetzer sind unter Umständen nicht bereit für den Wandel am Arbeitsplatz und empfinden eventuell eine gewisse berufliche Orientierungslosigkeit. Unser empirischer Ansatz zur Erforschung translatorischer Kompetenz befasst sich mit den methodologischen Herausforderungen von Forschung am Arbeitsplatz und trägt zu einem besseren Verständnis der professionellen Anforderungen an Sprachexperten bei.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-23T14:22:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-23T14:22:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://m4.ti.ch/fileadmin/DECS/DCSU/AC/OLSI/documenti/lm.pdf#page=133</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2989</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1023-2044</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Bulletin suisse de linguistique appliquée</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Vereinigung für Angewandte Linguistik in der Schweiz</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8447</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-20T06:25:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Abgrenzung überwinden : Change Management: neues Denken in Veränderungsprozessen - das heisst Perspektivenwechsel auf individueller sowie kollektiver Ebene</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Chlopczik, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Coaching</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Organisationsentwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Change Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Theorie U</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-07-24T14:51:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-24T14:51:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-01-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8447</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8447</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8447</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1422-8971</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Handelszeitung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Ringier Axel Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2909</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:00:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Essen für die Zukunft : Anforderungen an die Verpflegungskonzepte von Morgen</dc:title>
          <dc:title>Veranstaltung Care Gastronomie «Wohn- und Pflegemodelle, Ernährungsverhalten und Verpflegungskonzepte der Zukunft»</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brombach, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>613.2: Diätetik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618.97: Geriatrie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Jeder Mensch wird in eine bestimmte historische Zeit hineingeboren und erlernt bestimmte Voraussetzungen und Lebensmittel als „normal“ zu empfinden, die jedoch von zuvor Geborenen als Neuheit erlebt werden. Jede Generation hat also ganz spezifische, sozial-kulturell geprägte Bedingungen, die den Umgang, die Auswahl, Kenntnisse an Lebensmittel prägen und damit Anforderungen und Erwartungen an Verpflegungssysteme beeinflussen. Was Menschen im jungen und mittleren Erwachsenenalter gegessen haben, welche Präferenzen sie haben, wird auch im höheren Lebensalter für sie wichtig bleiben. Wenn wir also Verpflegungskonzepte „von Morgen“ betrachten, ist es hilfreich zu verstehen, welche gegenwärtigen Prägungen in jeder Generation vorliegen und wie diese in ein jeweiliges zukünftiges Verpflegungskonzept integriert werden können. In diesem Vortrag werden zwei explorative Studien vorgestellt, die jeweils in einem drei-Generationen Design durchgeführt wurden. Dabei sollen folgende Fragen beantwortet werden: 
- Welche Veränderungen lassen sich in Bezug auf Essverhalten, Mahlzeitenmuster, Bedeutungen und Umgang mit Esstraditionen in einer Drei-Generationenperspektive beobachten?
- Was können wir aus Ernährungsbiografischen Studien für Verpflegungskonzepte ableiten?
- Gibt es Muster oder Strukturen von Mahlzeiten, die über die Generationen hinweg tradiert oder verändert werden, die dann in den Verpflegungskonzepten berücksichtigt werden müssen?
- Wie kann die Flexibilität, die wir heute im Bereich der Verpflegung schätzen, umgesetzt werden?
- Gibt es „personalisierte“ Verpflegungskonzepte und wie könnten diese aussehen? 

Als Hintergrund der Ausführungen dient ein Zeithorizont von 1900 bis zur Gegenwart. Damit reihen sich die Gedankengänge ein in Überlegungen, wie sie Haupt und Torp anstellen, wenn sie von einem „langen 20. Jahrhundert“ sprechen, wenn sie den Entwicklungsprozess der Lebensmittelproduktion und -verarbeitung umreissen. In diesem langen 20. Jahrhundert werden die heutigen Rahmenbedingungen angelegt, in dessen Kontext sich auch die Verpflegungskonzepte von Morgen auszurichten haben.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-21T13:12:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-21T13:12:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2909</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2909</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2909</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Careum Weiterbildungstagung, Aarau, 1. Februar und 29. März 2017</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2471</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T12:15:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>UF001 LokDepot, Basel : the first commercial rooftop aquaponic farm in Switzerland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Graber, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Durno, Mark</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gaus, Roman</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mathis, Alex</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Junge, Ranka</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Aquaponics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Building integrated agriculture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>630: Landwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Introduction: Aquaponics is an innovative and sustainable food production system integrating aquaculture with hydroponic vegetal crops. This emerging technology has the potential to play a key role in provision of food while tackling global challenges such as water scarcity, food safety, food security, urbanization, and reductions in energy use and food miles. While it is a widely discussed technology today (about 1.3m hits on Google in May 2014), only very few research papers were published describing efficiency and performance of real systems. Results: In 2012, the Swiss company UrbanFarmers, a spin-off of the Zurich University of Applied Sciences (ZHAW) built a 260 m2 greenhouse farm on an industrial rooftop in Basel (UF 2014). Together with the research team at ZHAW, the aquaponic farm layout was planned, installed, operated and monitored. In its first year of operations, 700 kg Tilapia and 3’500 kg of different vegetables were produced and sold to restaurants, and to Migros, Switzerland’s largest retailer. This pilot farm achieved three major goals: to showcase the proof of technology for aquaponic rooftop farms, to demonstrate proof of market acceptance by Swiss consumers for this new way of farming food, and to deliver key performance figures that allow planning and scale-up for future commercially interesting farm units. Conclusion: Further innovations are required that simplify operations and enable cost-effective aquaponic farming, while making the products safe for human consumption: new planting techniques, new varieties of produce, biological pest control, irrigation techniques, and integration with existing building infrastructures.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-01T08:12:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-01T08:12:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2471</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2471</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2471</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>2014 International Conference on Vertical Farming and Urban Agriculture VFUA 2014, Nottingham, UK, 9-10 September 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19099</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:30:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Choosing cybersecurity insurance in a new risk environment</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dufresne, Alexandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>332.38: Versicherungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The recent passage of the GDPR and the CCPA complicates the data privacy liability landscape – and the task of buying the right cyber insurance. In a recent webinar, Jones Day attorneys Jennifer Everett and Richard DeNatale, along with Aarti Soni, cyber coverage leader for the insurance brokerage firm Marsh, and Fred Karlinsky, a shareholder at Greenberg Traurig, explained what corporate counsel should look for in insurance coverage in this regulatory environment and offered concrete advice about specific language and provisions in insurance plans.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-01-16T12:36:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-01-16T12:36:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-11-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19099</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19099</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19099</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Cybersecurity Law Report</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Mergermarket Limited</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19478</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T15:35:47Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Conference talk on investigating tar formation at low pressures in wood gasification systems, applying a novel thermo-chemical simulation model</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Boiger, Gernot Kurt</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Buff, Vincent</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zubiaga, Asier</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Caels, Pedro</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Wood gas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Simulation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Thermodynamics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Tar</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>540: Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Introduction and Short Description:&#13;
The method of gasifying wood via pyrolysis, gas purification, feeding a gas motor and producing electricity via a generator, has been applied for decades. Even-though wood gasification remains a promising technology regarding de-centralized sustainable energy supply, its main limitations, namely the issues of unsteady operation, excessive tar-formation and consequential high maintenance requirements, have never been fully overcome. In order to tackle these deficiencies and to increase the understanding of thermo-chemical wood-gas phase reaction dynamics, a numerical model has been created. After validating the simulator against comparable software, it has been applied to predict and thus understand tar-formation phenomena within a small experimental co-current gasification system. A particular focus within this work is laid on the investigation and minimization of tar-formation phenomena within low-pressure zones (e.g. downstream of valves) at temperatures T≤500K. Model-based analysis has led to a range of recommended process modifications to reduce the occurrence of tars.&#13;
 &#13;
Methodology, Results and Discussion:&#13;
The novel thermo-chemical wood-gas model is inspired by a unifying perspective on physical phenomena, based on Gibbs fundamental equation. The tool considers coal C(s), water H2O(v), methane CH4, carbon-dioxide CO2, carbon-monoxide CO, hydrogen H2 and tar represented by naphthalene C10H8 as interacting chemical species i. Within the applied simulation concept, any chemical reaction k such as, but not exclusively the hetero-/homogeneous Boudouard-,  Methanation- or Water-Gas-Shift reaction is driven by non-zero molar Gibbs free energies of reaction ΔGR,k.&#13;
&#13;
The solver has been validated by comparison to a well-known approach based on minimizing global Gibbs free energy within a LaGrange function. Graphs compare respective results of calculated wood-gas equilibria compositions over a process-relevant temperature range, and clearly shows 1:1 correspondences between the solvers.&#13;
&#13;
Applying the solver and accounting for decreasing temperature and pressure along the wood-gas flow path, shifts in species concentrations can be qualitatively predicted. On this basis the following measures can be recommended to minimize tar occurrence in low-pressure zones: i) Decrease gas residence time and ii) increase temperatures. iii) Increase hydrogen to carbon ratio RH/C as well as iv) oxygen to carbon ratio RO/C in the wood gas, either by v) removing coal from the reaction zone or by adding either vi) water or vii) process air. Graphs show the comparison of three simulation runs where wood-gas with varying RH/C ratios is exposed to temperature and pressure drop. According to this prediction the amount of naphthalene decreases strongly at increasing RH/C.&#13;
&#13;
Conclusion and Outlook:&#13;
The full paper will contain more detailed insights into the physical and methodical principles behind the dynamic wood-gasification solver and will provide more detailed insights into predicted gas compositions as well as investigations leading to the “recommendations for minimizing tar formation under low-pressure conditions” formulated in 2.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-02-17T15:35:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-02-17T15:35:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-11-18</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19478</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19478</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19478</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-9503671-1-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the ICPS19 : 5th international conference on polygeneration strategies</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>ICPS19 - 5th International Conference on Polygeneration Strategies, Vienna, 18-20 November 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4501</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-16T17:09:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Large-scale data-driven financial risk assessment</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Breymann, Wolfgang</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bundi, Nils</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Heitz, Jonas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Micheler, Johannes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stockinger, Kurt</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Stress test</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Big data</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Simulation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Financial risk</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332: Finanzwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The state of data in finance makes near real-time and consistent assessment of financial risks almost impossible today. The aggregate measures produced by traditional methods are rigid, infrequent, and not available when needed. In this chapter, we make the point that this situation can be remedied by introducing a suitable standard for data and algorithms at the deep technological level combined with the use of Big Data technologies. Specifically, we present the ACTUS approach to standardizing the modeling of financial contracts in view of financial analysis, which provides a methodological concept together with a data standard and computational algorithms. We present a proof of concept of ACTUS-based financial analysis with real data provided by the European Central Bank. Our experimental results with respect to computational performance of this approach in an Apache Spark based Big Data environment show close to linear scalability. The chapter closes with implications for data science.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-03-29T08:39:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-29T08:39:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-07-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-11821-1_21</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-030-11821-1_21</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4501</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4501</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4501</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-030-11820-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-030-11821-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Applied data science : lessons learned for the data-driven business</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6135</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-19T14:49:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Heilpädagogik als angewandte Entwicklungspsychologie?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Steinebach, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Heilpädagogik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Entwicklungspsychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>155: Differentielle Psychologie und Entwicklungspsychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>371: Schulen und schulische Tätigkeiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-28T12:26:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-28T12:26:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6135</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6135</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6135</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-8253-8297-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Gesichter der Heilpädagogik : Freiburger Perspektiven</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Edition S</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Universitätsverlag Winter</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken completeListSize="24863" cursor="195">oai_dc////19600</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
