<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="static/style.xsl"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-06-08T16:54:16Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" resumptionToken="oai_dc////4700">https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/oai/request/</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10949</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T12:55:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Pflegekinder im Übergang in die Volljährigkeit : Leitfaden - ein Arbeitsinstrument für Fachpersonen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Werner, Karin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Leitfaden</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pflegekinder</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Care Leaver</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Leaving Care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>306.8: Familiensoziologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.7: Jugendhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-09-21T11:46:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-21T11:46:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4812</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4812</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10949</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10949</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10949</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1421-2862</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Netz</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>PACH, Pflege- und Adoptivkinder Schweiz</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23012</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-08-26T10:41:14Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The effect of age on the pressure pain threshold of asymptomatic ankles and knees in young individuals with haemophilia</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Etzweiler, Denise</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Albisetti, Manuela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meichtry, André</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Huber, Erika</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Haemophilia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Young</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616: Innere Medizin und Krankheiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Introduction: Despite adequate medical treatment, many young adults with haemophilia develop joint alterations—especially in ankles and knees. Undetected over years, subtle structural changes cause subclinical symptoms, before problems become obvious. To objectify these silent pressure pains, the pressure pain threshold (PPT) can be measured by algometry.&#13;
&#13;
Aim: The aim was to investigate and compare the effect of age on PPTs in asymptomatic ankles and knees between boys and young adults with haemophilia and age-matched controls, in order to gain better knowledge about the alteration of the periarticular structures with increasing age.&#13;
&#13;
Material and methods: Nineteen persons with haemophilia (PwH; severe or moderate; 8–30 years) and 19 age-matched controls with ‘healthy’ ankles and knees were recruited. Asymptomatic joints with a Haemophilia Joint Health Score = 0 were included. The PPT was measured on four periarticular points per joint, and the data were analysed with a linear mixed model.&#13;
&#13;
Results: The PPT of the control group increased with age, whereas the PPT of the PwH decreased. The difference in age effect per year in kPa between PwH and controls was as follows: β [95%-CI]: −15.41 [−31.63; 0.79]. Although the result was not statistically significant (p = .08), a clear tendency was shown.&#13;
&#13;
Conclusion: The results suggest that subclinical alterations in the periarticular structures of these joints may evolve unnoticed over time. However, further research is warranted to determine whether this observed trend is confirmed in a larger sample and at what age the PPT begins to decrease in PwH compared to controls.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-08-26T10:41:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-08-26T10:41:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1111/hae.14344</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1111/hae.14344</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23012</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23012</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23012</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1351-8216</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1365-2516</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Haemophilia</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Wiley</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2708</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T10:12:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Constraints on creativity: the case of CAT tools</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ehrensberger-Dow, Maureen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Massey, Gary</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Translation-process</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Cognitive-ergonomics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>ErgoTrans presentation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Language-technology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>410.285: Computerlinguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The increasing use of language technology tools, such as translation memory, termbanks, and online dictionaries, has prompted an interest in their impact on cognitive processes, creativity, and the quality of translation products. Originally designed to improve consistency and increase speed, tools also facilitate searches for information and the recycling of previously-translated passages. Ideally, CAT tools relieve translators of the tedium involved with text production and help produce creative, appropriate solutions by freeing up cognitive capacity to deal with challenging translation problems (cf. O’Brien 2012). Recent research, however, indicates that CAT tools are not being used to their full potential or are even unnecessarily constraining the users they should have been designed for (Ehrensberger-Dow &amp; Massey 2014a, b). Drawing on a large corpus of translation processes collected from professionals and students, we discuss the nature of translation in terms of cognitive, physical, and organizational ergonomics. The cognitive demands of comprehending complex content in one language, while producing and revising output in another, add a new dimension to the usual considerations of computer usability. In fact, the productivity pressures imposed on many professionals might be forcing them to adjust to their tools rather than adapting those tools to their own needs. On the basis of our findings, we argue that professional translators need to take increased ownership of language technology tools, and play a more prominent role in contributing to needs assessment, product development, application testing, training, and the integration of language technologies into organizational processes.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-08T14:27:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-08T14:27:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014-10-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2708</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2708</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2708</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Translata II: «Translation Studies &amp; Translation Practice», Innsbruck, Austria, 30 October - 1 November 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17221</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-05T11:55:51Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Normalität und Identität bei (ehemaligen) Pflegekindern</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Reimer, Daniela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>155: Differentielle Psychologie und Entwicklungspsychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Eine Studie zur Entwicklung von Kindern, die in der besonderen Lebenssituation als "Pflegekind" gelebt haben. Diese Studie basiert unter anderen auch auf Interviews mit ehemaligen Pflegekindern. &#13;
In welcher Form ist es ihnen gelungen, ihre Identität zu finden und eine Normalität in der Gesellschaft leben zu können?</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-06-05T11:55:51Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-06-05T11:55:51Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-05-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.moses-online.de/fachartikel-normalitaet-identitaet-ehemaligen-pflegekindern-daniela-reimer</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17221</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2511-9524</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Moses Online</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>AktivVerbund</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8841</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-08T06:36:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Das in der eigenen Immobilie gebundene Kapital nutzen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hohgardt, Holger</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Grimm, Selina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cong, Tra Mi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Wohneigentum</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wohnen im Alter</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Immobilie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Real Estate</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vorsorge</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pensionierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vorsorgelücke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Rente</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333: Bodenwirtschaft und Ressourcen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-08-02T14:47:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-02T14:47:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3928</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3928</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8841</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8841</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8841</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Der Schweizerische Hauseigentümer</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>HEV Schweiz</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22349</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-04-30T03:00:56Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1315</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1354</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Einfluss einer nächtlichen Beladungssperre des Heizpufferspeichers auf die Effizienz von verschiedenen Heizsystemen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Funk, Sebastian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>333.79: Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>620: Ingenieurwesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Mit der Energiestrategie 2050 der Schweiz wird unter anderem der Ausbau von erneuerbaren Energien forciert. Dies soll im Sektor Haushalt zu grossen Teilen durch Heizsysteme gelingen, die ihre Energie aus erneuerbaren Quellen beziehen. Vor diesem Hintergrund lässt sich beobachten, dass die Absatzzahlen von Heizsystemen mit Wärmepumpen steigen.&#13;
Mit dieser Arbeit wurde das Ziel verfolgt, durch die Einführung einer nächtlichen Beladungssperre des Heizpufferspeichers eine einfach umsetzbare Regelstrategie zu untersuchen, mit welcher die Effizienz bei eben diesen Heizsystemen mit Wärmepumpen gesteigert werden soll. Durch die Einführung der Beladungssperre wird beabsichtigt, ein Teil der Last der Wärmepumpen in den Tag zu verschieben. Dadurch soll erreicht werden, dass die Wärmepumpen vermehrt dann betrieben werden, wenn die Wärmequellen eine durchschnittlich höhere Temperatur aufweisen. &#13;
Hierfür wurden Heizsysteme betrachtet mit Luft/Wasser-Wärmepumpe, Luft/Wasser-Wärmepumpe und solarthermischer Heizungsunterstützung sowie einem System mit Sole/Wasser- Wärmepumpe, welches einen von PVT-Modulen gespeisten Kaltspeicher als alleinige Wärmequelle nutzt. In der ersten von zwei Simulationsreihen wurde die Beladungssperre des Heizpufferspeichers bei den Heizsystemen für ein neugebautes Einfamilienhaus implementiert und optimiert. Anschliessend wurden in einer zweiten Simulationsreihe die Heizsysteme mit Beladungssperre für die Anwendungen saniertes Einfamilienhaus, neugebautes Mehrfamilienhaus und saniertes Mehrfamilienhaus getestet. &#13;
Durch die gezielte Lastverschiebung gelang es, die Wärmepumpen nachweislich bei einer höheren durchschnittlichen Quelltemperatur zu betreiben. Ein fail-safe-mechanismus verhinderte dabei das ungewollte Absinken der Gebäudetemperatur. Bei einem fixen Endzeitpunkt der Sperre um 09:00 Uhr morgens konnten die höchsten Effizienzsteigerungen beobachtet werden. Ein fester Startzeitpunkt konnte nicht ausgemacht werden, da je nach Anwendungsfall und Heizsystem eine unterschiedlich lange Beladungssperre zu den besten Ergebnissen führte. &#13;
Mit einer jährlichen Stromersparnis von über 7 % konnte bei allen drei Heizsystemen die höchste Effizienzsteigerung für die Anwendung saniertes Einfamilienhaus erreicht werden. Die jährliche Stromersparnis fiel hingegen bei den Neubau-Anwendungen mit rund 1.5 % bis 4.5 % niedriger aus. Es zeigte sich, dass der Effekt der Beladungssperre des Heizpufferspeichers bei einer Erhöhung der Heizungsvorlauftemperatur deutlicher ausfiel. Eine Kombination der Beladungssperre mit einer Nachtabsenkung oder einer Überhitzung des Heizpufferspeichers wiesen dagegen keine oder keine zusätzliche Effizienzsteigerung auf.&#13;
&#13;
With Switzerland's Energy Strategy 2050 and the associated aim of promoting the expansion of renewable energies, which in the household sector should be largely achieved by heating systems that obtain their energy from renewable sources, sales of heating systems with heat pumps are increasing. &#13;
The aim of this thesis was to investigate the possibility of increasing the efficiency of these heating systems with heat pumps by introducing a nocturnal load barrier on the heating buffer tank. The introduction of the load barrier is intended to shift part of electrical load of the heat pump into daytime. This is intended to ensure that the heat pumps are increasingly operated when the heat sources have a higher average temperature. &#13;
For this purpose, heating systems with an air/water heat pump, an air/water heat pump supported by solar thermal heating as well as a system with a brine/water heat pump, which uses a buffer tank loaded by PVT-modules as sole heat source, were considered. In the first of two simulations series, the load barrier of the heater buffer storage could be implemented and optimized in the heating system for a newly built single-family house. &#13;
Tested were subsequently, in a second series of simulations, heating systems with load barriers for the installation situations of refurbished single-family houses, newly built multi-family houses and refurbished multi-family houses. By shifting the electrical load, the heat pumps could be operated at a higher average source temperature. A fail-safe mechanism prevented the unwanted drop in building temperature. With a fixed end time of the lock at 09:00 o'clock, the highest increases in efficiency were observed. A fixed start time could not be determined because a load barrier of varying length, depending on the application and heating system, led to the best results. &#13;
With an annual power saving of more than 7 %, all three heating systems achieved the highest increase in efficiency for the application of a refurbished multi-family house. In contrast, the annual power savings for new-build applications were lower at around 1.5 % to 4.5 %. It was shown that the effect of the load barrier of the heating buffer storage tank was more pronounced when the heating flow temperature was increased. In contrast, a combination of the load barrier with a night setback or overheating of the heating buffer storage tank showed no or no additional increase in efficiency.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-04-29T08:30:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-04-29T08:30:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Master</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-22349</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-22349</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22349</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22349</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22349</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>100 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3147</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-24T12:43:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Phenol degradation in a three-phase biofilm fluidized sand bed reactor</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Etzensperger, M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Thoma, S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Petrozzi, Sergio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dunn, Irving J.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Dissolve oxygen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sole carbon source</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Biomass concentration</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Oxygen transfer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Aeration rate</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>572: Biochemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>«Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenzen.ch)»</dc:description>
          <dc:description>A previous three phase fluidized sand bed reactor design was improved by adding a draft tube to improve fluidization and submerged effluent tubes for sand separation. The changes had little influence on the oxygen transfer coefficients(KL a), but greatly reduced the aeration rate required for sand suspension. The resulting 12.5 dm3 reactor was operated with 1 h liquid residence time, 10.2dm3/min aeration rate, and 1.7-2.3 kg sand (0.25-0.35 mm diameter) for the degradation of phenol as sole carbon source. The KLa of 0.015 s−1 gave more than adequate oxygen transfer to support rates of 180g phenol/h · m3 and 216 g oxygen/h · m3. The biomass-sand ratios of 20-35 mg volatiles/g gave estimated biomass concentrations of 3-6 g volatiles/dm3. Offline kinetic measurements showed weak inhibition kinetics with constants ofKs=0.2 mg phenol/dm3, Ko2=0.5 mg oxygen/dm3 and KinI= 122.5 mg phenol/dm3. Very small biofilm diffusion effects were observed. Dynamic experiments demonstrated rapid response of dissolved oxygen to phenol changes below the inhibition level. Experimentally simulated continuous stagewise operation required three stages, each with 1 h residence time, for complete degradation of 300 mg phenol/dm3 · h.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T11:10:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T11:10:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1989</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1699</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00369397</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1699</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/BF00369397</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3147</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3147</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3147</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1615-7591</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1615-7605</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Bioprocess and Biosystems Engineering</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24881</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-04-29T03:04:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Dynamic analysis of cylindrical shells subject to multiple blasts using FSI</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mehreganian, Navid</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Boiger, Gernot Kurt</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moatamedi, Mojtaba</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fallah, Arash</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Multiphysics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Modeling</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Simulation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>FSI</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>CFD</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Finite element</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Finite volume</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Computational physics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>530: Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Localised pressure pulse loads can pose a significant threat to structural elements and critical equipment and may cause failure and damage in the target due to the concentrated energy delivered upon a localised area of the target. The impulse impinged upon the local area at the contact interface can exceed 80% of the total impulse that the charge can deliver upon the infinite target, leading to potential perforation of the structural element. When multiple charges are detonated, the advection of gaseous products depends, among other parameters such as fluid density, on the type of blast wave interference and superposition.&#13;
&#13;
This work examines the influence of multiple charge detonations blasted in the air on the external surface of cylindrical shells. Two types of detonations were considered, viz. simultaneous and sequential. In both cases the charges were positioned at 50mm and 75mm stand-off to the right and left of the shell. The Fluid-Structure Interaction (FSI) phenomenon was investigated in each scenario. The pressure registered with the gauge points of the rigid target was implemented in an uncoupled study on a flexible target which demonstrated different mode shapes occurring in the shell due to each blast scenario.&#13;
&#13;
A dimensionless impulse parameter was defined based on the Gaussian distribution function associated with the load shape, which renders the probability of the impulse as the total impulse that can potentially be imparted to the target.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-04-28T09:28:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-04-28T09:28:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21152/1750-9548.15.4.453</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-24881</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21152/1750-9548.15.4.453</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-24881</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24881</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24881</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24881</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1750-9548</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2048-3961</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>The International Journal of Multiphysics</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>International Society of Multiphysics</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19169</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-24T04:01:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Phylogenetic structure and formation mechanism of shrub communities in arid and semiarid areas of the Mongolian Plateau</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zheng, Ying</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dong, Lei</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Li, Zhiyong</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zhang, Jing Hui</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Li, Zijing</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Miao, Bailing</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jia, Chengzhen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Liang, Cunzhu</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wang, Lixin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Li, Frank Yonghong</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Cold limit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Desert shrub</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Paleoclimate</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Phylogenetic overdispersion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Species coexistence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>577: Ökologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>580: Pflanzen (Botanik)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The mechanisms of species coexistence within a community have always been the focus in ecological research. Community phylogenetic structure reflects the relationship of historical processes, regional environments, and interactions between species, and studying it is imperative to understand the formation and maintenance mechanisms of community composition and biodiversity. We studied the phylogenetic structure of the shrub communities in arid and semiarid areas of the Mongolian Plateau. First, the phylogenetic signals of four plant traits (height, canopy, leaf length, and leaf width) of shrubs and subshrubs were measured to determine the phylogenetic conservation of these traits. Then, the net relatedness index (NRI) of shrub communities was calculated to characterize their phylogenetic structure. Finally, the relationship between the NRI and current climate and paleoclimate (since the Last Glacial Maximum, LGM) factors was analyzed to understand the formation and maintenance mechanisms of these plant communities. We found that desert shrub communities showed a trend toward phylogenetic overdispersion; that is, limiting similarity was predominant in arid and semiarid areas of the Mongolian Plateau despite the phylogenetic structure and formation mechanisms differing across habitats. The typical desert and sandy shrub communities showed a significant phylogenetic overdispersion, while the steppified desert shrub communities showed a weak phylogenetic clustering. It was found that mean winter temperature (i.e., in the driest quarter) was the major factor limiting steppified desert shrub phylogeny distribution. Both cold and drought (despite having opposite consequences) differentiated the typical desert to steppified desert shrub communities. The increase in temperature since the LGM is conducive to the invasion of shrub plants into steppe grassland, and this process may be intensified by global warming.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-01-23T14:51:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-01-23T14:51:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.5787</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-19169</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1002/ece3.5787</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-19169</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19169</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19169</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19169</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2045-7758</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>31871647</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Ecology and Evolution</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Wiley</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12230</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:40:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>CO2-Senken und -Quellen in der Waldwirtschaft : Anrechnung im Rahmen des Kyoto-Protokolls</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fischlin, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Buchter, Bernhard</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Matile, Luzius</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hofer, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Taverna, Ruedi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>333.7: Landflächen, Naturerholungsgebiete</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-10-29T09:53:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-29T09:53:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.bafu.admin.ch/dam/bafu/de/dokumente/wald-holz/uw-umwelt-wissen/co2-senken_und_-quelleninderwaldwirtschaft.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12230</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Umwelt-Wissen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>45 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Bundesamt für Umwelt</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/25089</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-06-02T14:35:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Key Audit Matters : Entwicklungstendenzen in der Berichterstattung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Meyer, Beatrice</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zimmermann, Nicola</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>KAM</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Textanalyse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Revisionsbericht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>657: Rechnungswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Revisionsgesellschaften müssen seit fünf Jahren in Revisionsberichten, die sich auf Jahresabschlüsse von börsenkotierten Gesellschaften beziehen, Key Audit Matters (KAM) offenlegen. Die Frage stellt sich, ob innerhalb dieser Zeit Entwicklungstendenzen erkennbar sind. Der nachfolgende Beitrag widmet sich dieser Thematik.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-06-02T14:35:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-06-02T14:35:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/25089</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/25089</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/25089</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2297-5624</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Expert Focus</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>EXPERTsuisse</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14660</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-16T13:47:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>IT-Budgeting processes in Swiss banks and how they are influenced by rapidly changing regulatory requirements</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hitz, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Krey, Mike</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Albath, Marius</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wyss, Robin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Thoma, Per</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>IT-Budgeting</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Swiss bank</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332.1: Banken</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.1: Organisation und Finanzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The budgeting processes for IT projects in Swiss banks is a subject which has remained almost unexplored to date. For the purpose of this paper, a thorough literature review was conducted to gather information on different budgeting methods and identify the current challenges that banks are facing. To find out how the various budgeting processes of banks support their ability to react to fast-changing market conditions, how they differ from each other, and to identify the main problems of individual budgeting processes, interviews with five banks were conducted. While, on the whole, Swiss banks were found to be well-prepared for fast changes in the markets, a strong link to their IT project budget processes could not be confirmed. In addition, Swiss banks use traditional budgeting methods in combination with improved budgeting methods. A number of problem areas were identified for current budgeting processes; these include planning accuracy as well as implementation and business IT alignment.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-01-28T16:17:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-28T16:17:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3396</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5171/2018.785563</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3396</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.5171/2018.785563</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14660</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14660</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14660</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2165-9990</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of EU Research in Business</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Ibima Publishing</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8395</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-24T12:43:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Stability of person ability measures in people with acquired brain injury in the use of everyday technology : the test–retest reliability of the Management of Everyday Technology Assessment (META)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Malinowsky, Camilla</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kassberg, Ann-Charlotte</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Larsson-Lund, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kottorp, Anders Börje Mauritz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Brain injury</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Occupational therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Test–retest reliability</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Disability evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615.8515: Ergotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Aim: To evaluate the test-retest reliability of the Management of Everyday Technology Assessment (META) in a sample of people with acquired brain injury (ABI). 

Method: The META was administered twice within a two-week period to 25 people with ABI. A Rasch measurement model was used to convert the META ordinal raw scores into equal-interval linear measures of each participant’s ability to manage everyday technology (ET). Test-retest reliability of the stability of the person ability measures in the META was examined by a standardized difference Z-test and an intra-class correlations analysis (ICC 1). 

Results: The results showed that the paired person ability measures generated from the META were stable over the test–retest period for 22 of the 25 subjects. The ICC 1 correlation was 0.63, which indicates good overall reliability. 

Conclusion: The META demonstrated acceptable test-retest reliability in a sample of people with ABI. The results illustrate the importance of using sufficiently challenging ETs (relative to a person’s abilities) to generate stable META measurements over time.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-23T11:49:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-23T11:49:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.3109/17483107.2014.968812</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.3109/17483107.2014.968812</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8395</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8395</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/70343855.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8395</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1748-3107</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1748-3115</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>25270613</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Disability and Rehabilitation: Assistive Technology</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Taylor &amp; Francis</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5846</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-14T15:13:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1075</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1074</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1076</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Entwicklung von Simulationsmethoden für haustechnische Benutzungsgeräusche</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Walk, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Emrich, Frieder</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leuthardt, Fredi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Schallschutz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Benutzungsgeräusch</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bauakustik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>690: Hausbau und Bauhandwerk</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>720: Architektur</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Schweizer Norm SIA 181 "Schallschutz im Hochbau" legte bereits 1988 Grenzwerte für Benutzungsgeräusche von haustechnischen Anlagen fest. Da diese Geräusche ihrer Natur nach einer starken individuellen Streuung von Benutzer zu Benutzer bzw. von Messgruppe zu Messgruppe unterliegen, führten diese Grenzwerte zu einer beträchtlichen Planungsunsicherheit. Um hier Abhilfe zu schaffen, sollen in der überarbeiteten Fassung der Norm für die wichtigsten Benutzungsgeräusche Simulationsmethoden angegeben werden, die eine wesentlich bessere Reproduzierbarkeit von Messergebnissen gewährleisten.&#13;
Gegenstand dieser Untersuchung ist die Validierung unterschiedlicher Simulationsgeräte im Vergleich zu manuell ausgelösten Anregungen durch Messungen sowohl im Labor, als auch in realen Bausituationen in verschiedenen Landesteilen der Schweiz. Zum Einsatz kamen das Kleinhammerwerk nach Gösele, sowie verschiedene Schlaggeräte zur Erzeugung von Einzelimpulsen. Die Terzbandspektren und A-bewerteten Schallpegel der Originalgeräusche wurden mit denen der vorgeschlagenen Simulationsgeräte verglichen.&#13;
Die Resultate zeigen, dass mit einem optimierten Fallhammer ein den Originalgeräuschen gut entsprechender Spektrenverlauf erzielt werden kann, allerdings mit einem deutlich höheren Pegel, so dass neben der besseren Reproduzierbarkeit der Messungen auch die einfachere Durchführbarkeit gewährleistet ist. Zum Vergleich mit Anforderungswerten müssen daher noch Pegelkorrekturen berücksichtigt werden, deren Werte aus den Messresultaten bestimmt wurden. Dagegen produziert das Kleinhammerwerk nach Gösele deutlich weniger tieffrequente Geräuschanteile als die meisten Originalgeräusche und eignet sich damit nur für spezielle Benutzungsgeräuscharten als Simulationsgerät.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-05-15T16:27:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-15T16:27:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5846</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5846</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5846</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3-9808659-0-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Fortschritte der Akustik, DAGA 2003 : Plenarvorträge und Fachbeiträge der 29. Deutschen Jahrestagung für Akustik Aachen</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>29. Deutsche Jahrestagung für Akustik, Aachen, Deutschland, 18.-20. März, 2003</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Deutsche Gesellschaft für Akustik</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6642</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T12:31:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Schreiben und Öffentlichkeit</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Perrin, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-06T14:11:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-06T14:11:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008-10-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6642</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6642</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6642</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Schreiben in Beruf und Alltag, Wuppertal, Deutschland, Oktober 2008</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1040</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:30:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_24</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1094</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_33</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Auswahlkriterien für externe Asset Manager und Anlagegrundsätze : eine Untersuchung von 35 Schweizer Pensionskassen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Anhorn, Regina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moor, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Asset Manager</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Anlagegrundsätze</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pensionskassen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>360: Soziale Probleme und Sozialversicherungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Studie</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Das wirtschaftliche Umfeld mit geringem Wachstum, tiefen Zinsen und volatilen Finanzmärkten fordert die Schweizer Vorsorgeeinrichtungen. Hinzu kommen die demographische Entwicklung (höhere Lebenserwartung) sowie die von der Politik festgelegten Parameter wie BVG-Umwandlungssatz oder die Mindestverzinsung. Die Pensionskassen stossen bei der Finanzierung der Leistungen an ihre Grenzen.&#13;
Die Zinsen galten neben den Sparbeiträgen von Arbeitgebern und Arbeitnehmern in der beruflichen Vorsorge lange Zeit als „dritter Beitragszahler“. Diese Rolle ist mehr denn je in Frage gestellt. Im Herbst 2015 gab der Bundesrat bekannt, dass er den BVG-Mindestzinssatz für 2016 auf 1.25% senkt – auf das tiefste Zinsniveau seit Inkrafttreten des Gesetzes über die berufliche Vorsorge (1985).&#13;
Den steigenden Anforderungen an die Finanzierbarkeit der 2. Säule kann nicht nur mit Anpassungen auf der Anlageseite begegnet werden. Notwendig ist auch die Kürzung von Leistungen. Damit einher muss die Entpolitisierung der beruflichen Vorsorge gehen. Die Umverteilung hat zu grosse, nicht haltbare Dimensionen angenommen und die Generationensolidarität wird in der beruflichen Vorsorge zunehmend in Frage gestellt. &#13;
Die Vorsorgeeinrichtungen unterliegen wie andere Anleger den Verwerfungen an den Finanzmärkten. Mit einer weiteren Professionalisierung im Anlagebereich und einer aktiveren Wahrnehmung ihrer Rolle als bedeutende Investoren können jedoch Voraussetzungen geschaffen werden, um die Zukunft erfolgreich zu meistern.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2015-11-18T13:23:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-11-18T13:23:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1040</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1040</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1040</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1040</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1040</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6324</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T13:19:51Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Forschungsprojekt zur Optimierung von Erdwärmesonden</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hubbuch, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>620: Ingenieurwesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-31T14:03:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-31T14:03:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6324</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6324</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6324</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1662-5269</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1420-3219</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Gesundheits- und Umwelttechnik</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>SVG-Verlag</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5731</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T11:48:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Healthcare professionals as language mediators : incorporating translator education in language learning and teacher training</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ehrensberger-Dow, Maureen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Massey, Gary</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Language mediation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Language teaching</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Translator education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-02T12:41:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-02T12:41:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3624</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3624</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://www.ealthy.com/ealthy-magazine</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5731</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Ealthy Magazine</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>EALTHY</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12014</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:00:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Management of high-risk pregnancy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hauser, Regula</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Weiterbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>378: Hochschulbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Background: Expectant mothers who require extra-special care due to illness or a problem in their unborn child are part of your everyday job as a midwife. An increase in this type of care can been seen emerging from high incidences of multiple births, older first-time mothers and complex conditions. At the same time we are experiencing a national and international shortage of trained midwives, which leads to registered nurses in clinics increasingly taking care of these ill pregnant women and their unborn children despite a lack of specific training.

Aim: To achieve a high level of expertise in registered nurses and midwives who take care of women with high-risk pregnancies and their unborn children.

Methods: We have developed a continuing education programme for registered nurses and midwives in an inter-institutional cooperation between the Antenatal Ward at University Hospital Basel and the Institute of Midwifery at the Zurich University of Applied Sciences. 

Outcomes: Since 2013 the Institute of Midwifery has been offering a five-day training continuing education course with the following contents:
- physiology/pathology of pregnancy
- cardiotograms (CTG)
- multiple pregnancies
- diversity
- domestic violence

Conclusion: The continuing education programme is aimed at registered nurses and midwives who work in departments for prenatal care and wish to expand their knowledge.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-22T13:30:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-22T13:30:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-02-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12014</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12014</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12014</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Care 4 International Scientific Nursing and Midwifery Congress, Antwerp, Belgium, 8-10 February 2017</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13333</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-24T10:54:04Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Internationalisation of European higher education</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wittmann, Frank</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Hochschule</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Handbuch</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Internationalisierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>378: Hochschulbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-11-29T09:16:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-29T09:16:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13333</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13333</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13333</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-8183-0543-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Raabe</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15536</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T07:20:12Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Umgang mit Fehlern in der betrieblichen Ausbildung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Baumgartner, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Seifried, Jürgen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>331: Arbeitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-02-20T14:43:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-20T14:43:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15536</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15536</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15536</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Herbsttagung der Sektion Berufs- und Wirtschaftspädagogik (BWP), Konstanz, Deutschland, 27. September 2011</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4397</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-20T09:51:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Improving the forecast of freight transport demand using machine learning and time series analysis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bruckmann, Dirk</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jackson, Clare</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ott, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Weidmann, Ulrich</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>003: Systeme</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T14:15:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T14:15:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4397</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4397</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4397</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>14th Swiss Transport Research Conference, Ascona, 14-16 May 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18733</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-08-11T13:36:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Multi-task learning for multi-dimensional regression : application to luminescence sensing</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Michelucci, Umberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Venturini, Francesca</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Artificial intelligence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Machine learning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Oxygen sensor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Luminescence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>530: Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The classical approach to non-linear regression in physics is to take a mathematical model describing the functional dependence of the dependent variable from a set of independent variables, and then using non-linear fitting algorithms, extract the parameters used in the modeling. Particularly challenging are real systems, characterized by several additional influencing factors related to specific components, like electronics or optical parts. In such cases, to make the model reproduce the data, empirically determined terms are built in the models to compensate for the difficulty of modeling things that are, by construction, difficult to model. A new approach to solve this issue is to use neural networks, particularly feed-forward architectures with a sufficient number of hidden layers and an appropriate number of output neurons, each responsible for predicting the desired variables. Unfortunately, feed-forward neural networks (FFNNs) usually perform less efficiently when applied to multi-dimensional regression problems, that is when they are required to predict simultaneously multiple variables that depend from the input dataset in fundamentally different ways. To address this problem, we propose multi-task learning (MTL) architectures. These are characterized by multiple branches of task-specific layers, which have as input the output of a common set of layers. To demonstrate the power of this approach for multi-dimensional regression, the method is applied to luminescence sensing. Here, the MTL architecture allows predicting multiple parameters, the oxygen concentration and temperature, from a single set of measurements.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-11-20T09:38:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-11-20T09:38:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.3390/app9224748</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-18733</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.3390/app9224748</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-18733</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18733</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18733</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18733</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2076-3417</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Applied Sciences</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>MDPI</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11653</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T12:55:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Heimerziehung der Nachkriegszeit war düster</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Reimer, Daniela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Heimerziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>1968</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.7: Jugendhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenzen.ch)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Das Jahr 1968 stellt einen Meilenstein dar in der Entwicklung der Heimerziehung, weg von einer Strafanstalt hin zu einer modernen Fremdunterbringungsform. Dennoch gibt es noch viel Verbesserungsbedarf. Der Artikel schaut zurück und wagt einen Ausblick.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-11T12:28:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-11T12:28:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4021</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/s12054-018-0080-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4021</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/s12054-018-0080-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11653</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11653</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11653</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0931-279X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1863-8953</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Sozial Extra</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15957</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:00:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Path to innovation : linkages between academia and industry</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hefti, Jacques</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Commercialization of technology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Linkages between academia and industry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Building Bridges</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Innovation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Cooperation between academia and the private sector can take various forms, including conducting fundamental research that flows into the development of new products and processes of a commercial partner. It also implies knowledge transfer from the research institution to a company. In addition, closer cooperation with business helps universities to develop curricula that are relevant and meet the needs of students and society. Establishing international cooperation can contribute to building on already existing research. This contributes to provide graduates with the right skills and mind-sets for the global labour market.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-03-09T10:33:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-09T10:33:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15957</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15957</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15957</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Building Bridges: Sharing Best Practices on Commercialization of Technology, Warsaw, Poland, 9 June 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4800</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-01-29T07:27:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Unternehmenspolitik, Identität und Kommunikation : Modell - Prozesse - Fallbeispiele</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Niederhäuser, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rosenberger Staub, Nicole</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Reputationsmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kommunikationsmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Identitätsorientierte Kommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-04T14:21:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-04T14:21:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-8349-6397-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-8349-6397-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4800</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4800</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4800</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-8349-2201-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Gabler</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8693</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-28T08:03:13Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Overview of the taxation of non-resident athletes and entertainers in Switzerland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jau, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>343: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Sachen-, Finanz-, Steuer- und Wirtschaftsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-07-27T11:16:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-27T11:16:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8693</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8693</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8693</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1660-8399</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Causa Sport</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Dike</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11459</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T14:06:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The potential of gamification in changing consumer behaviour towards a more sustainable nutrition behaviour</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Berger, Verena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Miesler, Linda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hari, Jürg J.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Gamification</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Behavioral Change</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nutrition</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sustainable Consumption</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Purpose of the Paper: First, the paper discusses gamification and its impact on consumer behaviour in various areas and clarifies opportunities of the application of game elements in these areas. Second, the authors outline the potential of gamification to change consumer behaviour in the area of sustainable nutrition behaviour.

Design/Methodology/Approach: Various studies in the relevant research areas gamification, nutrition behaviour, consumer behaviour and behavioural change are reviewed to map gamification components to behavioural change constructs. Empirical studies are proposed providing a basis for the development of an effective programme for sustainable nutrition.

Findings: Gamification, based on social influence, promises to be an effective and practicable intervention approach to change behaviour and promote sustainable nutrition behaviour. Conclusions - Based on this review of relevant literature, parameters are identified for a proposed research project, which is still in its conceptual phase.

Practical Implications: Understanding the mechanisms behind gamification better can help to apply them more effectively to change consumer behaviour.

Originality: The paper provides a starting point for studying the potential of gamification in a systematic and interdisciplinary manner to find new ways to promote behaviours with positive impact on environment and society.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-04T14:21:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-04T14:21:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11459</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11459</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11459</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Academy of Marketing Conference 2014, Bournemouth, United Kingdom, 7-10 July 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15282</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T14:10:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1315</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1463</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Tourenvorschläge für Mountainbiker aus Bewegungsdaten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kessler, Sebastian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Bewegungsdaten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Map-Matching</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Personalisierter Tourenvorschlag</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mountainbike</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Segmentierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>910: Geografie und Reisen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Der Mountainbike-Sport erfreut sich steigender Beliebtheit und ist in Bergregionen längst ein wichtiger Wirtschaftsfaktor. Mountainbike-spezifische Zeitschriften, Internetseiten und Smartphone-Apps bieten unzählige Informationen über Mountainbike-Touren an. Obwohl sich bei Onlineplattformen Suchfilter einsetzen lassen, ist es oft schwierig und zeitaufwändig eine Mountainbike-Tour nach seinem eigenen Geschmack zu finden.&#13;
In den verschiedensten Bereichen nutzen Menschen GPS-Sensoren, um ihre Bewegungsdaten mittels GPS aufzuzeichnen. Aus den aufgezeichneten raumzeitlichen Daten können mittels moderner Methoden der Bewegungsanalyse nützliche Informationen gewonnen werden. Im Fall des Mountainbikings können relevante Toureninformationen aus den GPS-Daten abgeleitet und daraus ein personalisiertes Tourenprofil erstellt werden. Dieses kann wiederum verwendet werden, um personalisierte Tourenvorschläge zu unterbreiten.&#13;
In dieser Arbeit wurde ein Algorithmus entwickelt, welcher aus GPS-Tracks relevante Tourenparameter ableitet und daraus personalisierte Tourenprofile erstellt. Mittels Tourenprofil kann schliesslich aus einer beliebigen Auswahl an Mountainbike-Touren ein personalisierter Tourenvorschlag unterbreitet werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>In the last decade mountain biking has become a very popular sport. For mountain regions it has turned into an important economic factor. Targeted mountain biking magazines, websites and smartphone apps provide a wide range of information about mountain bike trails and tours. Although there is the possibility to apply search filters, it remains difficult to find a mountain bike tour according to one’s own preferences.&#13;
People use GPS-devices in many different areas to trace their movements while jogging or cycling. This spatio-temporal data can be processed by modern methods of movement analysis. Through the movement analysis, mountain biking specific information can be gained and used to draw up a mountain biker’s specific tour profile. A personalised mountain bike tour profile can then be used to develop personalised tour recommendations.&#13;
For this thesis a special algorithm was developed which uses GPS tracks to deduce tour parameters, draw up personalised mountain bike tour profiles and make individual tour recommendations.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-13T13:32:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-13T13:32:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2347</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2347</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15282</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15282</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15282</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>53 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6689</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-20T09:51:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Producing complex networks using coupled oscillatory circuits with evolutionary connections</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Uwate, Yoko</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ott, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nishio, Yoshifumi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Complex network</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-08T12:29:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-08T12:29:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1109/ISCAS.2018.8351665</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1109/ISCAS.2018.8351665</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6689</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6689</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6689</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-5386-4881-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-5386-4882-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2379-447X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>IEEE International Symposium on Circuits and Systems (ISCAS)</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>EEE International Symposium on Circuits and Systems (ISCAS), Florenz, Italy, 27-30 May 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>IEEE</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2130</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T10:32:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Personalized Nutrition : Nutri-Epigenetik und Ernährungsverhalten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brombach, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>613.2: Diätetik</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-01-18T11:16:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-18T11:16:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2130</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2130</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2130</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Lebensmittel 4.0 : Wohin führt die vierte industrielle Revolution und was bedeutet sie für die Entwicklung unserer Tisch- und Esskultur?, Wädenswil, 19. November 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12697</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-27T13:35:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ein deutscher und europäischer Blick auf Unternehmensübernahmen in der Schweiz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nobel, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Drenckhan, Helke</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>349: Rechtsvergleichung und ausländisches Recht</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-11-09T10:02:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-09T10:02:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0342-6971</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Wertpapier-Mitteilungen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Herausgebergemeinschaft Wertpapier-Mitteilungen Keppler Lehmann</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3066</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-25T08:03:45Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Das Vorurteil «a fool with a tool is still a fool» gilt nicht mehr!</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Liebhart, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Transhuman</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Autopilot</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Moderne Systeme räumen damit auf. Dank IT-Innovationen werden Menschen vielleicht nicht unbedingt immer klüger, aber doch weniger unvernünftig. Ein erfreulicher Fortschritt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T09:41:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T09:41:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4147</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4147</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3066</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3066</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3066</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-2397</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Netzwoche</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Netzmedien</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9726</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-26T09:57:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Das Ehrenamt - wenn's gut läuft, ein Gewinn für alle</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fringer, André</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Betreuung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Versorgung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Demenzkrank</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Freiwillig</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616.8: Neurologie und Krankheiten des Nervensystems</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Versorgung demenzkranker Menschen wird zukünftig ohne ehrenamtliche Betreuung kaum noch auskommen. Gerade hier jedoch ist das freiwillige Engagement besonders schwierig. An der Universität Witten/Herdecke wurden daher zehn Experten um ihre Meinung zu diesem Thema befragt. André Fringer, wissenschaftlicher Mitarbeiter der Universität, stellt das Ergebnis vor. Das A und O ist eine gute Anleitung der Ehrenamtlichen, lautet die wichtigste Botschaft.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-27T09:03:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-27T09:03:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9726</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9726</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9726</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1863-5172</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1863-5806</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Pflegen: Demenz</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Friedrich</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15087</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-14T13:37:56Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Forschungs-PR : eine Analyse von Strukturen, Ressourcen, Deutungsmustern und Normen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Giovanelli, Iris</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>659: Werbung und Öffentlichkeitsarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Vortrag</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Im Rahmen des Doktorandenkolloquiums der Universitäten Bern und Fribourg wurde die Dissertation erstmals einem kommunikationswissenschaftlichen Fachpublikum präsentiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-06T11:03:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-06T11:03:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15087</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15087</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15087</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Doktorandenkolloquium der Universitäten Bern und Fribourg, 2006</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11164</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-08T07:39:51Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Invalidenrentenanspruch bei depressiven Erkrankungen : eine kritische Auseinandersetzung mit der Rechtsprechung des Bundesgerichts</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Slavik, Eva</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>344: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Arbeits-, Sozial-, Bildungs- und Kulturrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Seit einiger Zeit urteilt das Bundesgericht regelmässig, dass therapierbare, leicht bis mittelschwer ausgeprägte Depressionen nie invalidisierend seien und verneint den Rentenanspruch von versicherten Personen mit diesen Diagnosen. Depressive Erkrankungen und daraus folgende Erwerbsausfälle sind sehr häufig. Diese Rechtsprechung hat daher eine erhebliche sozialpolitische Tragweite und weckt zahlreiche medizinische und rechtliche Bedenken. Sie wird mit dem Beitrag deshalb kritisch hinterfragt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-27T13:22:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-27T13:22:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-09-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11164</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11164</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://jusletter.weblaw.ch/juslissues/2017/904/zum-invalidenrentena_2823ec73e6.html</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11164</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-7410</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Jusletter</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Weblaw</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21082</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-12-18T09:31:56Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The influence of age on neurorehabilitation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wirz, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rutz-La Pitz, Louise</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Neurorehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Age</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616.8: Neurologie und Krankheiten des Nervensystems</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-12-18T09:31:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-12-18T09:31:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1093/med/9780198824954.003.0006</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1093/med/9780198824954.003.0006</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21082</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21082</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21082</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:9780198824954</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:9780191863790</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Oxford Textbook of Neurorehabilitation (2 edn)</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Oxford textbooks in clinical neurology</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Oxford University Press</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15358</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T10:12:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Commentary on Jauhar and Hayes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hengartner, Michael Pascal</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>000: Allgemeines und Wissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-02-14T10:46:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-14T10:46:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.addbeh.2019.02.007</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.addbeh.2019.02.007</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15358</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15358</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15358</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0306-4603</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1873-6327</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Addictive Behaviors</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18128</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T14:36:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Bewertung häuslicher Krisen : Sicht der Pflegenden</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stängle, Sabrina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fringer, André</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-09-05T14:36:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-09-05T14:36:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1024/85856-000</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1024/85856-000</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18128</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18128</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18128</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-456-85856-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Das Buchser Pflegeinventar für häusliche Krisensituationen (BLiCK) : Analysen, Werkzeuge und Empfehlungen zur Krisenintervention</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Hogrefe</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13289</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T13:39:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The variability of Sun-like stars : reproducing observed photometric trends</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Shapiro, A. I.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Solanki, S. K.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Krivova, N. A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schmutz, W. K.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ball, W. T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Knaack, Reto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rozanov, E. V.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Unruh, Y. C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Astro-ph.SR</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sun: activity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Stars: activity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Stars: solar-type</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Stars: variables: general</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Solar-terrestrial relations</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sun: atmosphere</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>500: Naturwissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Context: The Sun and stars with low magnetic activity levels become photometrically brighter when their activity increases. Magnetically more active stars display the opposite behavior and become fainter when their activity increases.&#13;
&#13;
Aims: We reproduce the observed photometric trends in stellar variations with a model thattreats stars as hypothetical suns with coverage by magnetic features different from that of the Sun.&#13;
&#13;
Methods: The model attributes the variability of stellar spectra to the imbalance between the contributions from different components of the solar atmosphere, such as dark starspots and bright faculae. A stellar spectrum is calculated from spectra of the individual components by weighting them with corresponding disk-area coverages. The latter are obtained by extrapolating the solar dependences of spot and facular disk-area coverages on chromospheric activity to stars with different levels of mean chromospheric activity.&#13;
&#13;
Results: We find that the contribution by starspots to the variability increases faster with chromospheric activity than the facular contribution. This causes the transition from faculae-dominated variability and direct activity-brightness correlation to spot-dominated variability and inverse activity-brightness correlation with increasing chromospheric activity level. We show that the regime of the variability also depends on the angle between the stellar rotation axis and the line-of-sight and on the latitudinal distribution of active regions on the stellar surface. Our model can be used as a tool for extrapolating the observed photometric variability of the Sun to Sun-like stars at different activity levels, which makes a direct comparison between solar and stellar irradiance data possible.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-27T17:28:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-27T17:28:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014-06-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201323086</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1051/0004-6361/201323086</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13289</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13289</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13289</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0004-6361</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1432-0746</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>EDP Sciences</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3051</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-25T07:09:56Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Survival guide für CIOs</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Liebhart, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ITSM</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>BPM</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>BIA</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>CIO</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Krise ist vorbei, doch noch immer kämpfen CIOs um höhere IT-Budgets, um endlich Unerledigtes realisieren zu können. Diese Strategien bringen Sie auf den richtigen Weg.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T09:22:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T09:22:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011-03-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4137</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4137</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3051</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3051</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3051</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1420-5009</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Computerworld</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>IDG Communications</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7647</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T12:31:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Gekaufte Wissenschaft : Wissenschaftsjournalismus im Kreuzfeuer «Wissen in der Pendlerzeitung 20 Minuten»</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wyss, Vinzenz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Koch, Carmen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wissenschaftskommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>20Minuten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>070: Nachrichtenmedien, Journalismus und Verlagswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-07-06T09:52:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-06T09:52:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7647</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7647</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7647</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>ScienceComm'13, La Chaux-de-Fonds, 26.-27. September 2013</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/564</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:43:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_52</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Können persistierende Schulterschmerzen (VAS 8-10) bei spastischer Hemiplegie nach Schlaganfall in der Rehabilitationsphase durch Einsatz von Botulinum Toxin (BOTOX) reduziert werden? : Welche physiotherapeutischen Vor- und Nachtei-le ergeben sich daraus?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Widmer, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:06:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:06:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-564</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-564</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/564</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/564</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/564</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14458</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T13:25:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Neue Versorgungsmodelle und Advanced Nursing Practice : ein Lösungsansatz um den Herausforderungen im heutigen Gesundheits- und Pflegewesen zu begegnen?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schubert, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-01-16T15:22:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-16T15:22:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14458</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14458</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14458</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>9. DGP-Hochschultag: Weitere Schritte zur Akademisierung der Pflege, Bochum, Deutschland, 16. November 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Deutsche Gesellschaft für Pflegewissenschaft (DGP)</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10410</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-28T09:38:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Den Nachfolgeprozess erfolgreich gestalten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schiess, Désirée Stephanie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>KMU</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Unternehmensnachfolge</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nachfolgeprozess</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>ZBB</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.1: Organisation und Finanzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-09-12T06:40:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-12T06:40:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10410</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10410</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10410</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0473-2839</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Organisator</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Galledia</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8695</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-12T13:17:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Zustellung an Verfahrensbeteiligte im Ausland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Plüss, Kaspar</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>342: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Staats- und Verwaltungsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-07-27T11:19:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-27T11:19:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8695</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8695</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8695</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>St. Galler Tagung zur Verwaltungsrechtspflege, St.Gallen, 7. Juni 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7059</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T11:57:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Besiedlungsdynamik in Primärsukzessionsflächen : Wirbellosen-Fauna im Gletschervorfeld Morteratsch</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schlegel, Jürg</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>590: Tiere (Zoologie)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Gletschervorfelder sind eisfreie Flächen, die durch den Rückzug der Gletscher seit Mitte des 19. Jahrhunderts frei gegeben worden sind. Sie nehmen in der Schweiz bereits heute eine grössere Fläche ein als der ganze Kanton Obwalden. Erstaunlicherweise bestehen, im Gegensatz zur gut untersuchten Vegetation, bisher erst sehr vage Kenntnisse zur Fauna von Gletschervorfeldern und vielen anderen neu entstandenen Flächen. Das Forschungsprojekt «Klimawandel und Wirbellosenfauna», finanziert durch verschiedene private Stiftungen, soll hierzu etwas Licht ins Dunkel ringen. Am Morteratsch-Gletscher befindet sich eines der Untersuchungsgebiete.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-18T10:03:51Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-18T10:03:51Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3757</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3757</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7059</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7059</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7059</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Unr.intern</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14061</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T09:10:44Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Intercontinental collaboration of research and education : experiences of the research project “Group Training Outcomes Measurement Study”</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Roos, Kim Caroline</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Suter, Julia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gubler Thomann, Ursula</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barnes, Mary</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>DeLorenzo, Christopher</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schatzberg, Sharan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Groups</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Group therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Group leadership</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Assessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Teaching</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615.8515: Ergotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Introduction/Rationale: With globalisation, work with international partners is required in research and education to use resources effectively. New internet technologies allow collaboration over long distance. Nevertheless these opportunities have limitations. To what extend it is useful to encourage a long distance project? In an intercontinental project a Swiss and an American university worked together on a research in occupational therapy education.

Objectives: What are the experiences from researchers and students working on an intercontinental research project? 

Method: In the course of collaboration between the Tufts University Occupational Therapy Department Medford MA USA and the ZHAW in Zurich, a research team of both universities started gathering data from Swiss students for a validation research of the assessment the Functional Group Model (Schwartzberg and Barnes, 2014). Thirty-six Swiss students joined the project. Project participation required minimal in vivo knowledge. After finishing the project, students discussed their experiences in a focus group interview which was later analysed by content analysis to identify recurrent themes.

Results: The focus groups are currently under way.  Quantitative and qualitative data is now being collected via Qualtrics.

Conclusion: Working together between different countries over a long distance has been an interesting experience for all members. Necessary resources for a successful collaboration have been identified. Collaboration over long distance created new opportunity to gain and share knowledge, but has its limitation since always a physical, cultural and language barrier has to be overcome.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-12-20T09:33:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-20T09:33:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4945</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4945</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14061</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14061</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14061</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Connected in diversity : positioned for impact</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>33rd Council Meeting of the World Federation of Occupational Therapists, Cape Town, South Africa, 21-25 May 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22071</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-15T12:51:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Impact of shear stress on cell growth and microcarrier-cell-agglomerate formation in microcarrier-based cultivations of adipose tissue-derived stromal/stem cells</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jossen, Valentin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eibl-Schindler, Regine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kraume, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pörtner, Ralf</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eibl, Dieter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>610.28: Biomedizin, Biomedizinische Technik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>660: Technische Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Cell-based therapies have become increasingly important in the field of regenerative medicine, as global revenues of approximately 1 billion US$ indicate. A special focus in the clinical field is placed on human mesenchymal stem cells (hMSCs), especially on those isolated from the stromal vascular fraction of the adipose tissue. Due to their good clinical efficacy and tolerability, they can be used for allogeneic cell therapies (e.g. Crohn’s disease, graft versus host disease, acute myocardial infarct). However, the required number of therapeutically active human adipose tissue-derived stromal/stem cells (hASCs) for allogeneic applications is in the range of trillion cells per year. Thus, alternatives to the 2-dimensional planar cultivation systems, typically applied to propagate hASCs are urgently required. Different studies have recently demonstrated the applicability of stirred single-use bioreactors as a promising alternative to the planar cultivation systems. In these dynamically mixed culture systems, the required growth surface for the adherent growing cells is provided by microcarriers (MCs), which are suspended in the bioreactor. Although adherent mammalian cells are well investigated in combination with MCs for the production of vaccines, working with hASCs is more complex due to their higher shear sensitivity. This raises the question of how the induced fluid shear stress affects the cell expansion, the cell quality and the formation of MC-cell agglomerates during the cultivation in dynamic bioreactors. &#13;
For this purpose, MC-based cell expansions were performed in single-use spinner flasks at different impeller speeds below (25, 43 rpm) and above (90 and 120 rpm) the specific suspension criteria NS1u (49 rpm) and NS1 (63 rpm) for polystyrene-based MCs. Cell numbers, metabolites and the formation of MC-cell agglomerates were measured during the cell expansion process. Furthermore, the expression of standard surface markers (CD14, CD20, CD34, CD45, CD73, CD90, CD105) for hASCs were analysed after harvesting of the cells. Beside the biological investigations, Computational Fluid Dynamics simulations were performed in order to predict the velocity gradients and the hydrodynamic forces. The results indicated that too low (25 rpm) and too high impeller speeds (120 rpm) result in statistically significant lower cell densities (0.81 and 0.25 x 106 cells/mL) compared to those at the suspension criteria (1.25 and 1.11 x 106 cells/mL). These lower cell densities can be ascribed to mass transport limitations at low impeller speeds and to too high hydrodynamic strains at high impeller speeds. The effect of the shear stress on the MC-cell agglomerate formation at high impeller speeds was not significant, when compared the Sauter mean diameters to those resulting at the suspension criteria. In contrast, impeller speeds below the suspension criteria resulted in a strong MC-agglomerate formation, which may support mass transfer limitations.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-03-15T12:51:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-03-15T12:51:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22071</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22071</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22071</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>BioTech 2016, Wädenswil, Switzerland, 5-8 September 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16361</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-20T08:48:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Towards model based re-design of the copper electro-winning process</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brunner, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Boiger, Gernot Kurt</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Model based development</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Electro winning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Copper</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Simulation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>OpenFoam®</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fluiddynamics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>003: Systeme</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>660: Technische Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>High purity copper, suitable for electrical applications, can only be obtained by electrowinning. One aspect of this process is its self-induced natural convection through density variations of the electrolyte at both anode and cathode. The eventual goal is to highlight convective effects as main copper-transport mechanisms between the copper-winning electrodes. In order to do this, first the full dynamic complexity of the process needs to be understood. Thus an OpenFoam® based 3D model of the process has been created. This finite-volume multiphysics approach, solves the laminar momentum and copper-ion species conservation equations, as well as local copper-ion conversion kinetics. It uses a Boussinesq approximation to simulate the species-momentum coupling, namely natural draft forces induced by variations of the spatial copper concentration within the fluid. The model shows good agreement with benchmark-cases of real-life electrochemical cells, found in literature. Now the software can be applied to investigate how different forced convection conditions affect the speed of the entire copper-raffination process.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-03-28T11:47:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-28T11:47:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16361</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16361</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5c9f89c101232c1d41297d67/t/5d7942861dbee613b38a0b6f/1568227984715/MULTIPHYSICS+2016+-+Abstracts.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16361</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2409-1669</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2409-7527</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Multiphysics 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>International Conference of Multiphysics, Zurich, 8-9 December 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>The International Journal of Multiphysics</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>International Society of Multiphysics</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22314</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-04-22T08:57:51Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kommentar zu Art. 55 OR</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fischer, Willi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Iten, Marc'Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-04-22T08:57:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-04-22T08:57:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22314</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22314</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22314</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-03751-685-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Haftpflichtkommentar : Kommentar zu den schweizerischen Haftpflichtbestimmungen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Dike</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9631</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-04T12:56:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Arbeitgeberattraktivität im Drei-Ländervergleich : adaptive Conjoint-Analyse der Job-Präferenzen bei Fachkräften</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Scheidegger, Nicoline</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Conjoint-Analyse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Jobpräferenz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>DACH-Region</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Arbeitgeberattraktivität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>331: Arbeitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Im Rahmen eines überregionalen Forschungsprojektes werden Faktoren für die Arbeitgeberattraktivität herausgearbeitet. Mittels eines Methodenmixes aus qualitativer Vorstudie und adaptiver Conjoint-Analyse mit Fachkräften aus dem industriell-gewerblichen Sektor werden Bedingungen geklärt, unter denen Arbeitnehmende bereit sind, ein neues Jobangebot anzunehmen. Ein Ländervergleich (Deutschland, Schweiz und Österreich) zeigt dabei signifikante Unterschiede in der Bedeutung und Gewichtung der Kriterien. Generell werden betriebliche Merkmale des Arbeitsplatzes eher in die Präferenzurteile bei der Wahl einbezogen als Merkmale der Region. Aus den länderspezifischen Unterschieden lassen sich Hinweise für eine differenzierte und gezielte Ansprache der Zielgruppe in Stelleninseraten ableiten.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-24T13:19:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-24T13:19:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9631</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9631</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9631</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1615-7729</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Wirtschaftspsychologie</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Pabst Science Publishers</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18470</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-18T08:25:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kommentar zu Art. 57 ZGB SchlT</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kley, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Seferovic, Goran</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-10-18T08:25:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-10-18T08:25:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18470</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18470</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18470</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-280-07353-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>ZGB : Kommentar : Schweizerisches Zivilgesetzbuch</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Orell Füssli Kommentar</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Orell Füssli</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22427</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-05-05T13:02:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Mehr Inklusion durch intelligente Algorithmen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Frau, Daniela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rietmann, Konrad</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gerber, Marius</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>006: Spezielle Computerverfahren</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.3: Personalmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Künstliche Intelligenz (KI) soll Wahrnehmungsverzerrungen reduzieren und Inklusion sowie Diversität nicht nur im Recruiting, sondern auch in der Personalentwicklung fördern.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-05-05T13:02:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-05-05T13:02:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.hrtoday.ch/de/article/mehr-inklusion-durch-intelligente-algorithmen</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22427</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2235-8471</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>HR Today</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ALMA Medien</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24107</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-03T04:03:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1315</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1463</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Totholzkäferfauna in Dürrständern : wie beeinflusst sie die Weissrückenspechtpräsenz?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hasler, David</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Totholzkäfer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Präsenzflächen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Absenzflächen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Weissrückenspecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Buche</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Dürrständer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>590: Tiere (Zoologie)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erst seit wenigen Jahren werden in der Ostschweiz regelmässig einzelne Brutpaare des Weissrückenspechts (Dendrocopos leucotos) festgestellt. Wegen seiner hohen Lebensraumansprüche - naturnahe Wälder mit vielen absterbenden und toten Bäumen - ist sein Vorkommen auf entlegene und schwer zugängliche Wälder beschränkt. Das Untersuchungsgebiet befindet sich im Grenzgebiet Ostschweiz-Lichtenstein-Vorarlberg. Basierend auf gesicherten Nachweisen des Weissrückenspechts liess sich das Untersuchungsgebiets mosaikartig in Weissrückenspechtpräsenz- und absenzflächen unterteilen. Diese zwei Lebenraumklassen wurden nach der Zusammensetzung der Totholzkäferfauna untersucht und verglichen, zumal sich der Weissrückenspecht fast ausschliesslich von Totholkäferlarven ernährt. Diese Arbeit ging der Frage nach, ob die Habitatwahl innerhalb seines Verbreitungsgebiets durch das Nahrungsangebot abhängig ist.&#13;
Für diesen Zweck kam die “Dürrständer-Methode“ zum Einsatz. Insgesamt 86 Dürrständer der Baumart Rotbuche (Fagus sylvatica) sind im Frühjahr 2018 auf zwei Metern Länge eingepackt worden. So waren die entwickelnden Käferlarven gezwungen, durch die einzige Öffnung in einen mit Ethanollösung gefüllten Behälter zu fallen. Die Unterschiede waren beträchtlich: Sowohl Artenzahl und Individuenanzahl waren in Präsenzflächen deutlich grösser als in Absenzflächen. Die Käferanzahl nahm mit zunehmenden Brusthöhendurchmesser (BHD) in Präsenflächen zu, in den Absenzflächen war ein gegenteiliger Trend sichtbar. Die Exposition schien keinen Einfluss auf die Käferabundanz zu haben. Die Evenness war in Präsenzflächen deutlich höher als jene in Absenzflächen. Die Erkenntnisse sind mit Vorsicht zu geniessen, zumal eine Vielzahl an anderen nicht berücksichtigten Faktoren die Habitatwahl mitbestimmt haben könnten. Dass die Spechtpräsenz tatsächlich abhängig ist von der Nahrungszusammensetzung scheint wahrscheinlich, konnte aber nicht abschliessend verifiziert werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Only in recent years, individual breeding pairs of the White-backed Woodpecker (Dendrocopos leu-cotos) have been found regularly in Eastern Switzerland. Because of its high habitat requirements - near-natural forests with many dying and dead trees - its occurrence is limited to remote and hard to reach forests. The study area was located in the border area Eastern Switzerland-Lichtenstein-Vorarlberg. Based on verified evidence of the White-backed Woodpecker, the study area could be subdivided into mosaic-like White-backed Woodpecker-presence and White-backed Woodpecker-absence habitat areas. These two life classes were studied and compared according to the composition of the deadwood beetle fauna, especially since it feeds almost exclusively on deadwood beetle larvae &#13;
This work addresses the question of whether the habitat choice within its range is dependent on the food supply. &#13;
The ”snag-method” was used for this purpose. A total of 86 snags of the tree species European beech (Fagus sylvatica) were packed in the spring of 2018 over two meters in length. Thus, the developing beetle larvae were forced to fall through a single opening into a container filled with ethanol solution. The differences were considerable: Both the number of species and the number of in-dividuals were significantly larger in presence areas than in absence areas. The number of beetles increased with increasing breast height diameter (BHD) in present areas, in the absence areas however, a contrary trend was visible. Exposure did not appear to affect beetle abundance. Even-ness was significantly higher in presence areas than in absence areas. The findings are to be treated with caution, especially since a large number of other disregarded factors could have influenced the habitat choice. The fact that the presence of the White-backed Woodpecker actually de-pends on the food composition seems likely, but could not be conclusively verified.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-02-02T14:50:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-02-02T14:50:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-24107</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-24107</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24107</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24107</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24107</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>48 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10028</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-27T13:35:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Art. 2 Abs. 1bis KG : Gedanken zum neuen Unternehmensbegriff</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Krauskopf, Patrick</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Henckel, Sophie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>FIHR</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kartellrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>343: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Sachen-, Finanz-, Steuer- und Wirtschaftsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Mit Art. 2 Abs. 1bis KG hat der Gesetzgeber marktaktive Verwaltungseinheiten dem persönlichen Geltungsbereich des schweizerischen Kartellgesetzes unterstellt. Damit einher geht eine weite und offen formulierte Unternehmensdefinition. Insbesondere spielen die konkrete Rechts- und Organisationsform des Unternehmens keine Rolle mehr. Vor diesem Hintergrund untersucht der vorliegende Beitrag, welche Auswirkungen die gesetzliche Neuerung für die Beurteilung von Privatunternehmen, namentlich bei konzerninternen Sachverhalten und dem Phänomen der Vertikalintegration, zeitigen könnte.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-30T10:27:58Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-30T10:27:58Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10028</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10028</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10028</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1422-2019</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Sic! Zeitschrift für Immaterialgüter-, Informations- und Wettbewerbsrecht</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schulthess</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3486</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-02T07:57:42Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Schreibabys : zur Behandlung von Regulationsstörungen im Säuglingsalter</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>von Wyl, Agnes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bindernagel, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mögel, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zollinger, Ruedi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>618.92: Pädiatrie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-07T14:16:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-07T14:16:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3486</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3486</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3486</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-03754-071-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Bereit zum Dialog? : Beiträge zur Psychiatrie und Psychotherapie für Kinder und Jugendliche</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>EMH Schweizerischer Ärzteverlag</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15400</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-07T14:03:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Rationally "irrational" : theory and empirical evidence</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Fundamental Uncertainty</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Macro Finance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Rational Expectation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>330: Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>This paper presents a model for asset markets with a subjectively rational solution for the price of the traded assets. Consequently, traders cannot act objectively rational and an increase in the numbers of traders does not enlarge the information set necessary for determining the "true" price. An empirical test is suggested. It demonstrates the relevance of the argument.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-16T09:36:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-16T09:36:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15400</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15400</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15400</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>30 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Centre for Economic Policy Research</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2641</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T09:11:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Das Essverhalten von Frauen über 65 Jahren - Entwicklung und Einflussfaktoren im Laufe des Lebens bei Frauen der Geburtenjahrgänge 1927-1947: eine qualitative Studie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Glei, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brombach, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martins, Isabell</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>300: Sozialwissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>613.2: Diätetik</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-02-06T15:01:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-06T15:01:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2641</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2641</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2641</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-88749-248-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the German Nutrition Society : Abstractband zum 51. Wissenschaftlichen Kongress</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>51. Wissenschaftlicher Kongress der Deutschen Gesellschaft für Ernährung, Paderborn, Deutschland, 12.-14. März 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the German Nutrition Society</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Deutsche Gesellschaft für Ernährung</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14371</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T09:27:51Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The influence of personality on violent victimization : a study on police officers</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ellrich, Karoline</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Baier, Dirk</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>155: Differentielle Psychologie und Entwicklungspsychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>364: Kriminologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The current study aims to examine the influence of police officer characteristics, civilian characteristics, and possible interactions between both on violent victimization of police officers. Based on literature distinguishing between ‘provocative’ and ‘submissive’ victims, focus is given on effects of police officers’ personality in terms of the five-factor model plus risk-taking. Patrol police officers (n = 1813) from Lower Saxony, Germany, completed a paper-and-pencil survey including personality assessments as well as questions about their last three police encounters. Binary logistic multilevel regression analyses demonstrate that police officers with higher scores on neuroticism and openness to experience were more likely to be violently attacked. Furthermore, agreeableness reduced police officers’ risk of violent victimization, while risk-taking and neuroticism increased their risk when confronted with a violent civilian. The study indicates that personality and especially traits that are assumed to provoke potential perpetrators were linked with violent victimization. It further stresses the need to include perpetrator attributes in victim studies in order to identify relevant interaction effects between both parties.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-01-11T12:31:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-11T12:31:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1080/1068316X.2016.1168424</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1080/1068316X.2016.1168424</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14371</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14371</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14371</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1068-316X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1477-2744</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Psychology, Crime &amp; Law</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Routledge</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1781</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T12:31:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Aktuelle Befunde aus der JAMES-Studie mit einem Fokus auf Social Media</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Waller, Gregor</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2017-12-13T15:03:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-12-13T15:03:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013-11-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1781</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1781</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1781</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Praxisforum 2013 «Social Media und Soziale Arbeit», Olten, 6. November 2013</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22151</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-26T08:00:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Entwicklung in Richtung Enterprise Application Integration von nicht-medizinischer Software in Spitälern</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gerber, Nicole</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.11: Krankenhäuser und verwandte Einrichtungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-03-26T08:00:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-03-26T08:00:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22151</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22151</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22151</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>IFM-Symposium 2017, Zürich (Schweiz), 6. Oktober 2017</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15304</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-22T12:56:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wissenschaft und Praxis vernetzen : wissenschaftliches Arbeiten in den Gesundheitsberufen handlungs- und kompetenzorientiert unterrichten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Huber, Marion</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dönnges, Godela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Wissenschaftliches Arbeiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kompetenzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>000: Allgemeines und Wissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-02-13T14:40:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-13T14:40:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.3205/13gma184</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.3205/13gma184</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15304</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15304</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15304</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>GMA 2013 - "Tradition: Hemmschuh oder Chance" : Abstractband</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Jahrestagung der Gesellschaft für Medizinische Ausbildung (GMA), Graz, Österreich, 26.-28. September 2013</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Gesellschaft für Medizinische Ausbildung (GMA)</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10287</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-25T16:53:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Anreize verstärken : Leistungsauftrag Eingliederung : Anmerkung zur nächsten IV-Revision</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mosimann, Hans-Jakob</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Invalidenversicherung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Verwaltungsreform</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Eingliederung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>360: Soziale Probleme und Sozialversicherungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-09-06T08:59:51Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-06T08:59:51Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10287</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10287</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10287</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0255-9072</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Schweizerische Zeitschrift für Sozialversicherung und berufliche Vorsorge</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Stämpfli</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9920</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T09:26:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Labor supply and growth effects of environmental policy under technological risk</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Clemens, Christiane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pittel, Karen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>330: Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenzen.ch)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>This paper analyzes the effects of technological risk on long-run growth when labor supply is elastic and production gives rise to a pollution externality. We show that the randomness of production, as well as the endogeneity of labor supply, affects the equilibrium solutions for the social planner and for the market economy. We analyze the effects of environmental policy, discuss conditions for an optimal policy, and find that the response of labor supply to changes in the model parameters and to variations in the policy instruments crucially depends on the volatility of output.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-29T13:45:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-29T13:45:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3958</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100509990988</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3958</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1017/S1365100509990988</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9920</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9920</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9920</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1469-8056</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1365-1005</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Macroeconomic Dynamics</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Cambridge University Press</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8365</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-07T15:31:13Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Mitarbeiterinnen und Mitarbeiter stärken</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Eberhardt, Daniela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Klink, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.3: Personalmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-07-20T07:56:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-20T07:56:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8365</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8365</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8365</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-621-27962-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-621-27935-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Positive Psychologie in der Praxis : Anwendung in Psychotherapie, Beratung und Coaching</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Beltz Juventa</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19612</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T10:55:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Bereit für anspruchsvolle Gespräche? : ein Kommunikationstraining</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Oberndörfer, Katrin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hippold, Ilona</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Kommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Kurzbeschreibung Workshop „Kommunikationstraining“&#13;
Die Teilnehmenden haben die Möglichkeit mit professionellen Schauspielern im spielerischen, experimentellen Übungsfeld sich Situationen zu stellen, die für sie in der Praxis anspruchsvoll und/oder belastend sind. So können herausfordernde Gespräche mit Hilfe von Improvisationsübungen nach dem Motto „Probieren geht über Studieren“ trainiert werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-03-05T10:55:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-03-05T10:55:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19612</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19612</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19612</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>1. Schweizer Perinatalkongress, Baden, 17. Mai 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20028</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-05-20T06:53:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Art. 43 VwVG</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gächter, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Egli, Philipp</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>342: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Staats- und Verwaltungsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Der Kommentar zum Bundesgesetz über das Verwaltungsverfahren (VwVG) erscheint 10 Jahre nach der Erstauflage in stark überarbeiteter und erweiterter Form. Die in der Zwischenzeit ergangenen Entscheidungen und die neuere Literatur sind eingearbeitet (Stand Mai 2018).&#13;
&#13;
Seit 50 Jahren ist das VwVG die Grundlage für das Verfahren vor den Bundesbehörden und vor dem Bundesverwaltungsgericht. Gleichzeitig finden sich in zahlreichen Gesetzen des Bundes abweichende Verfahrensvorschriften, welche in der Praxis zu prozessualen Stolpersteinen werden können. Die Neuauflage weist auf diese abweichenden Normen hin, einerseits in den einzelnen Kommentierungen und anderseits mit dem Anhang, der einen raschen Überblick über alle spezialgesetzlichen Verfahrensnormen bietet.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-05-14T13:58:38Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-05-14T13:58:38Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20028</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20028</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20028</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-03891-008-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>VwVG : Kommentar zum Bundesgesetz über das Verwaltungsverfahren</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Dike</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7441</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-02T07:58:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Foto-Interessen-Test F-I-T Serie 2012</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stoll, François</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jungo, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Toggweiler, Stephan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Testmaterial</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Berufsinteressentest</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Berufswahl</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Berufsberatung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>158: Angewandte Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-28T10:16:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-28T10:16:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7441</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7441</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7441</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schweizerisches Dienstleistungszentrum Berufsbildung</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22811</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-17T03:01:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>2000-Watt-Gesellschaft leben : Reduktion des End-Energieverbrauchs durch Verhaltensänderungen : Nutzerinterventionen im Hüttengraben-Areal</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sandmeier, Ernst</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lobsiger-Kägi, Evelyn</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marek, Reto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tomic, Uros</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kälin, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>2000 Watt Gesellschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Verhaltensinterventionen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Verhaltensänderung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Suffizienz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Monitoring</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333.79: Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Im vorliegenden Projekt wurden technische Lösungen mit Verhaltens-Interventionen verknüpft, um nachhaltig den Energieverbrauch in Gebäuden und Haushalten zu senken. Gemeinsam mit der Baugenossenschaft Zurlinden (BGZ) wurden passende, sozial akzeptierte und potentiell hoch wirksame Interventionen entwickelt und in einer Neubausiedlung systematisch getestet. Durch ein Monitoring des Energieverbrauchs wurde die Wirksamkeit der Interventionen quantifiziert. Zusätzlich wurde deren Akzeptanz mittels Fragebogen analysiert.&#13;
Am meisten Endenergie konnte durch eine energetische Betriebsoptimierung der Raumheizung eingespart werden, jedoch stiess die dadurch bewirkte Reduktion der Raumtemperaturen anfänglich auf wenig Akzeptanz. Ein Jahr später stieg die Akzeptanz wieder annähernd auf das gleiche Niveau wie vor der Reduktion.&#13;
Eine weitere Intervention zielte auf den Verbrauch von Warmwasser. Durch, Feedback, Information und sozialen Vergleichen mit den Nachbarn konnte 15 % Warmwasser eingespart werden. Der Effekt reduzierte sich 3 Monate nach den Massnahmen auf 7 %.&#13;
Durch die letzte, den Haushaltsstrom betreffende Intervention konnte mittels einer Wettbewerbssituation und dem Verbrauchs-Feedback etwas Endenergie eingespart werden, jedoch konnten nur wenig aussagekräftige Resultate erzeugt werden, da die Intervention mit dem pandemiebedingten Lockdown in der Schweiz zusammenfiel.&#13;
Basierend auf dem gesamten Forschungsprojekt zwischen 2017 und 2020 können folgende Schlussfolgerungen gezogen werden:&#13;
- Die energetische Betriebsoptimierung der Heizung lohnt sich. Diese muss aber mit Kommunikationsmassnahmen begleitet werden, damit sie von den Nutzer*innen akzeptiert wird.&#13;
- Die Verbrauchsfeedbacks wurden von Haushalten als interessant eingestuft und können eine Reduktion im End-Energieverbrauch bewirken.&#13;
- Eine offene Kommunikation mit der Mieterschaft, in welcher die Ziele und die eingesetzten Technologien einer Massnahme sorgfältig erklärt werden, wird die Akzeptanz erhöhen.&#13;
- Die Messinfrastruktur soll von Anfang an bedürfnisgerecht geplant und die Übermittlungswege müssen definiert und getestet werden.&#13;
Die BGZ wird diese Erkenntnisse in die Planung weiterer Immobilien aufnehmen und die Kommunikation mit ihren bestehenden Mieter*innen dahingehend weiterentwickeln.&#13;
Aus diesen Ergebnissen wurde eine Umsetzungshilfe mit empfohlenen Interventionen abgeleitet. Das Ziel der Umsetzungshilfe (Faktenblatt) ist es, anderen Genossenschaften und Immobilienverwaltungen Hinweise zu geben, wie sie durch Interventionen den Energieverbrauch in ihren Siedlungen reduzieren können.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-07-16T07:17:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-07-16T07:17:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-12-23</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-22811</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-22811</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22811</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22811</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22811</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>43 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Bundesamt für Energie</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15825</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-25T07:45:44Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Decision making in asset management : optimal allocation of resources for maximizing value realization</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Heitz, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Goren, Lilach</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sigrist, Jörg</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.1: Organisation und Finanzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Asset Management is about realizing value from physical assets, but formal methods how to do this are still missing. In this paper, we present a formal model for decision making in asset management, based on the general concepts of ISO 55000, in particular the notion of value realization. With this framework, we can first define what optimal decisions are, and second show how to solve these problems in the context of Asset Management. The model describes both the cost and the value contributions of assets in an asset portfolio. The basic policy decision problem is decomposed into a budget setting step, and an allocation problem, where the latter can be solved with standard optimization algorithms. We apply the model to the case of an electrical supply network and find that the supply quality (value) can be increased by about 20% without spending more money, or the costs can be decreased by 16% without sacrificing quality, by optimized asset policy decisions with our model.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-03-06T15:07:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-06T15:07:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-27064-7_25</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-319-27064-7_25</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15825</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15825</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15825</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-319-27062-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-319-27064-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2195-4356</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2195-4364</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the 10th World Congress on Engineering Asset Management (WCEAM 2015)</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>WCEAM 2015, Tampere, Finland, 28-30 September 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Lecture Notes in Mechanical Engineering</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24805</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-04-21T06:48:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Biodiverse Speichertürme als wertvolle Ökosysteme in der Stadtentwicklung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Trachsel Geissmann, Evelyn</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Fassadenbegrünung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pflanzenverwendung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Biodiversität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kletterpflanzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>307: Gemeinschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2022-04-21T06:48:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-04-21T06:48:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Master</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24805</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24805</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24805</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Hochschule Wismar, University of Applied Sciences Technology, Business and Design</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9140</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-01T03:00:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The distance between forests and crops affects the abundance of Drosophila suzukii during fruit ripening, but not during harvest</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cahenzli, Fabian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bühlmann, Irene</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Daniel, Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fahrentrapp, Johannes</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Liquid bait</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pest monitoring</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Soft fruit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Spotted wing drosophila</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Trap color</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Phytomedicine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>590: Tiere (Zoologie)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenzen.ch)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Drosophila suzukii (Matsumura; Diptera: Drosophilidae) is an invasive pest with the ability to reproduce not only in various soft fruit crops, but also in numerous wild hosts. Forests and forest edges harbor many wild hosts, provide suitable microclimatic conditions and are therefore thought to enhance the abundance of D. suzukii. Although the comprehension of pest activity based on specific landscape elements is important to implement efficient management strategies, knowledge of how forests affect the abundance of D. suzukii in nearby crops is very limited. We conducted a monitoring study with liquid baited traps across different crops at different distance from the forests. During fruit ripening, more flies were captured in crops closer to forests (22.21 % decrease per 500 m distance), whereas there was no significant relationship during harvest. Since color can affect the efficiency of D. suzukii traps, we have used traps either with a red or black lid. Acquired data suggest that traps with black lids capture significantly more flies than traps with red lids. We provide a quantitative estimation of how and when distance from adjacent forests affects the abundance of D. suzukii in crop fields. Our results can help consultants and farmers to estimate the pest pressure of D. suzukii in crop fields near forested, noncrop areas and to implement appropriate control strategies when D. suzukii populations increase and fruit becomes susceptible to infestation.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-17T09:32:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-17T09:32:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1093/ee/nvy116</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-9140</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1093/ee/nvy116</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-9140</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9140</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9140</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9140</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0046-225X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1938-2936</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Environmental Entomology</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Oxford University Press</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/451</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:43:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_52</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Welchen Effekt hat ein Koordinationstraining in Bezug auf die Sturzprophylaxe bei geriatrischen Patienten ab 60 Jahren, gemessen an der Berg Balance Scale und/ oder der Anzahl an Stürzen?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Manser, Melanie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Nadia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:05:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:05:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-451</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-451</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/451</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/451</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/451</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24070</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-02T13:35:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Prävention ist die beste Medizin : wie gute Betreuung Heimeintritte verhindern kann</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Filippo, Martina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>344: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Arbeits-, Sozial-, Bildungs- und Kulturrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2022-02-02T13:35:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-02-02T13:35:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24070</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24070</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24070</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2235-2953</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2235-6851</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Pflegerecht</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Stämpfli</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19511</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-20T14:05:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Schweizer Restschuldbefreiung? : Deutsches Vorbild?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Busch, Dörte</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Theus Simoni, Fabiana</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Deutschland kennt seit 1999 ein Restschuldbefreiungsverfahren. Damit können redliche, aber zahlungsunfähige natürliche Personen (Konsumenten und Unternehmerinnen) von ihren Schulden befreit werden, die nach Durchführung eines Insolvenzverfahrens sowie einer Treuhandphase mit Erwerbspflicht des Schuldners noch unbezahlt sind; die Zustimmung der Gläubiger ist dafür nicht nötig. In der Schweiz hat das Parlament den Bundesrat beauftragt, eine Vorlage zur Sanierung von Privatpersonen auszuarbeiten. Vorliegend wird aufgezeigt, wie die Sanierung von Privatpersonen im SchKG verbessert werden und eine Restschuldbefreiung aussehen könnte. Dabei sollen die deutschen Erfahrungen berücksichtigt werden. Nach dem vorliegenden Vorschlag würden die Gläubiger neu ab Konkurseröffnung und während des Restschuldbefreiungsverfahrens während insgesamt drei Jahren vom pfändbaren Schuldnereinkommen profitieren, dies als «Preis» für die Restschuldbefreiung des redlichen Schuldners.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-02-20T14:05:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-02-20T14:05:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1660-3362</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Aktuelle juristische Praxis</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Dike</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4052</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T09:11:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Elterliche und haushälterische Risikofaktoren für einen ungünstigen Lebensmittelverzehr bei Säuglingen während des Übergangs zur Familienkost</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Marx, Kerstin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dawczynski, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lorkowski, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brombach, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>613.2: Diätetik</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-19T13:14:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-19T13:14:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4052</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4052</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4052</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>55. Wissenschaftlicher Kongress der Deutschen Gesellschaft für Ernährung, Stuttgart, Deutschland, 7.-9. März 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/267</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:42:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_51</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die ergotherapeutische Sichtweise der Betätigungsorientierung in der Handrehabilitation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gerber, Julia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.8515: Ergotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:02:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:02:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-267</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-267</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/267</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/267</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/267</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1135</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-19T10:17:44Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>An online NP-HPLC-DPPH method for the determination of the antioxidant activity of condensed polyphenols in cocoa</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pedan, Vasilisa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fischer, Norbert</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rohn, Sascha</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Condensed cocoa polyphenols</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Degree of polymerisation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Online NP-HPLC-DPPH</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Antioxidant capacity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>664: Lebensmitteltechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In Press</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Unroasted cocoa beans are rich in monomeric flavanols and particularly epicatechin-based proanthocyanidin oligomers, with the latter making up to 60% of the total polyphenol content. Although the antioxidant activity of cocoa polyphenols is well known, it is still a challenging analytical field, especially, when it comes to the determination of condensed polyphenols and the evaluation of their single contribution to the overall activity. Therefore, an online NP-HPLC-DPPH assay was developed to separate the homologous series of condensed polyphenols for assessing their antioxidant capacity in relation to their degree of polymerization (DP), simultaneously. In this context, normal-phase chromatography allows separation of polyphenols based on their degree of polymerization. This study showed that an unroasted cocoa extract contains condensed polyphenols with a DP of up to 10 monomer units. By means of the online post-column derivatisation with 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH), the antioxidant capacity of the separated condensed polyphenols was assessed. It could be shown that, with the exception of the dimers, the contribution to the total antioxidant activity decreased from monomers to decamers. However, from the single proanthocyanidins identified, nonameric and decameric proanthocyanidins were found to have the highest values for the antioxidant capacity. The degree of polymerization associated with each molecular weight fraction was further confirmed using electrospray ionization mass spectrometry coupled with reverse-phase liquid chromatography. The online NP-HPLC-DPPH method can be used as qualitative and quantitative analysis of condensed proanthocyanidins and the simultaneous elucidation of the biological activity of proanthocyanidins in complex mixtures.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2016-08-17T12:05:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-08-17T12:05:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-11-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1135</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2015.10.030</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1135</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.foodres.2015.10.030</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1135</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1135</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1135</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0963-9969</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1873-7145</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Food Research International</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7120</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-12T13:17:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Protecting PROFINET cyclic real-time traffic : a performance evaluation and verification platform</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Doran, Hans</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Network security</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Automation system</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Industrial ethernet</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Real-time ethernet</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>620: Ingenieurwesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>PROFINET is a widely adopted, real-time capable Industrial Ethernet standard, that as other automation system technologies, is subject to an increasing level of vertical integration into company’s existing IT infrastructure. This integration exposes automation systems to well-known cyber attacks, which leads to a growing need for suitable security solutions. The challenge in protecting PROFINET automation systems is ensuring the suitability of solutions for use with minimal PROFINET cycle times of 250 μs needed to fulfill high-speed motion control market expectations. We develop a prototype of a transparent security switch, designed to apply protection mechanisms on-the-fly. We use this platform to test an initial implementation of a protection system, present preliminary results and further work.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-20T14:22:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-20T14:22:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3896</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1109/WFCS.2018.8402379</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3896</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1109/WFCS.2018.8402379</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7120</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7120</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7120</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-5386-1066-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-5386-1067-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the 14th IEEE International Workshop on Factory Communication Systems</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>14th IEEE International Workshop on Factory Communication Systems, Imperia, Italy, 13-15 June 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>IEEE</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6269</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:01:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The politics of discourse : how to design applied discourse research</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stücheli-Herlach, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Discourse analysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Organisationskommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Diskursanalyse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Public Storytelling</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>401.4: Lexikologie und Terminologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-30T12:11:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-30T12:11:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6269</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6269</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6269</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>11th International Congress of Qualitative Inquiry, Illinois, USA, 20-23 May 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17233</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:39:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Whitepaper Mexico Cleantech</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Qvist-Sorensen, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Siev, Ronny Ilan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>333.79: Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Environmental protection is a new and increasingly  important concept in Mexican policy making. In addition, the country needs to improve its insufficient and ageing infrastructure. New policies, laws and regulations support a new mindset to tackle these important issues. With economic growth the need for energy is increasing. The Mexican energy reform, which is currently being implemented, will end the state monopoly and liberalize the market. Diversification of energy sources, growth of renewable energy and reduction of carbon dioxide and greenhouse gases are among the government’s long-term goals for the coming 20 years. Auctions for contracts in wind, solar and geothermal energy started in March 2016, initializing the wholesale market and attracting large international energy companies into Mexico. In line with the Mexican government’s initiatives, the three leaders of the NAFTA countries presented in June 2016 the North American Climate, Clean Energy and Environment Partnership Action Plan, to align their policies regarding clean energy, energy efficiency and emission goals. The three NAFTA countries joined the Paris Agreement on climate change, a reduction of emissions and promotion of a clean economy. Mexico ratified the agreement in September 20161. In March 2016 the countries of the Pacific Alliance (Mexico, Colombia, Peru and Chile) signed a green economy declaration, commit-ting to a green development plan and discussing a possible carbon emissions market. The Low Carbon Business Action (LCBA) supports the government’s future goals for Mexico. The LCBA aims to reduce CO² emissions in Mexico by mapping the needs and fitting these with the best solutions of European companies in the areas of energy efficiency (buildings and industry), waste and waste water management. Access for the Mexican population to clean drinking water is another leading policy objective. Mexico’s water services are not fulfilling the requirements, which could be expected from an OECD country. Even in the capital, less than half of the population has access to a constant stream of drinking water, leading to tensions within the society. This Whitepaper is the result of a thorough analysis of 11 different Cleantech sectors in Mexico, includ-ing current policy changes. The Whitepaper evaluates national and international incentive programs of these sectors and con-cludes that six sectors in Mexico should be of special interest for Swiss internationally oriented Clean-tech companies, namely: drinking water, waste water treatment, solar energy, energy efficiency, sustainable buildings and pollution control.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-06-05T12:37:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-06-05T12:37:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Weiteres (textuelles Material)</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.zhaw.ch/storage/sml/institute-zentren/imi/center-international-industrial-solutions/pdf/Whitepaper_Cleantech_Mexico_-_Final_2017.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17233</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>69 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/218</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T13:56:44Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_51</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Betätigung und Partizipation ermöglichen mittels Alltagstechnologie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bossart, Angela Katharina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Burgunder, Patricia Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Occupational therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Everyday technology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Acquired brain injury</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Cognitive impairment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Occupation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Participation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615.8515: Ergotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Darstellung des Themas: Menschen mit einer erworbenen Hirnverletzung leiden häufig an kognitiven Einschränkungen. Dies kann die Betätigungen und die Partizipation erschweren oder verunmöglichen. Eine Möglichkeit diese Einschränkungen zu kompensieren ist der Einsatz von Alltagstechnologien. 
Ziel: Anhand einer Literaturrecherche wird dargestellt, wie die Ergotherapie Menschen mit einer erworbener Hirnverletzung mit Hilfe von Alltagstechnologien als Kompensation bei der Durchführung von Betätigungen unterstützen kann, damit die Partizipation ermöglicht werden kann. Daraus werden schliesslich Empfehlungen für die ergotherapeutische Praxis abgeleitet. 
Methode: In elektronischen Datenbanken wurde recherchiert und Interviews mit Fachpersonen wurden durchgeführt. Die Hauptstudien, welche sich mit Personen mit einer erworbenen Hirnverletzung und Alltagstechnologien als Kompensation kognitiver Einschränkungen befassen, wurden kritisch beurteilt. Die Ergebnisse wurden den Enablement Skills des CMCE zugeordnet. Schlussfolgerungen für die ergotherapeutische Praxis werden aufgezeigt.
Ergebnisse: Die Hauptstudien untersuchen verschiedene Alltagstechnologien auf deren Potenzial zur Kompensation kognitiver Einschränkungen in Hinblick auf Betätigungs- und/ oder Partizipationsziele der Menschen mit erworbener Hirnverletzung. Zudem werden mögliche Instruktionsmethoden aufgezeigt. 
Schlussfolgerung: Die Interventionen aus den Ergebnissen lassen sich in die ergotherapeutische Praxis integrieren. Sie stellen somit eine weitere Interventionsmöglichkeit für Menschen mit erworbener Hirnverletzung dar. Die Betätigung kann ermöglicht und die Partizipation begünstigt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2015-07-24T09:13:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-07-24T09:13:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-218</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-218</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/218</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/218</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/218</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12947</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T10:12:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Mechanism-based design of a ROMP catalyst for sequence-selective copolymerization</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bornand, Marc</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chen, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>540: Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Back and forth like a metronome is how the carbene moiety swings in a dual‐site catalyst which produces a predominantly alternating copolymer of norbornene and cyclooctene from a one‐pot reaction of appropriate mixtures of the two monomers (see scheme). The alternating sequence of the polymer was confirmed by NMR spectroscopy and gel‐permeation gravimetric analysis.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-16T14:53:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-16T14:53:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1002/anie.200502606</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1002/anie.200502606</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12947</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12947</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12947</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1433-7851</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0570-0833</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>16342133</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Angewandte Chemie: International Edition</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Wiley</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13614</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-25T07:10:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Standbein der Qualitätssicherung in der ausserklinischen Geburtshilfe : die geburtshilfliche Statistik</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schmid, Monika</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-12-06T13:04:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-06T13:04:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13614</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13614</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13614</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1422-4526</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1662-5862</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Hebamme.ch</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schweizerischer Hebammenverband</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1885</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T11:44:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Blogs – a democratic tool? : a global megaphone for civil protest?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Genner, Sarah</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2017-12-19T14:32:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-12-19T14:32:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://sarah.genner.cc/uploads/5/1/4/1/51412037/blogs_prag.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1885</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Conference of the Marie Curie Research Network «European Protest Movements Since 1945»: Confronting Cold War Conformity: Peace and Protest Cultures in Europe, 1945-1989, Prague, 18-25 September 2008</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11010</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T14:09:42Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_236</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_8947</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Tränen in der Beratung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lerch, Tabea</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>331: Arbeitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die vorliegende Arbeit beschäftigt sich mit dem Phänomen des Weinens. Wir Menschen weinen vom Augenblick der Geburt an bis zum Ende des Lebens. Der wissenschaftliche Forschungsstand über das Weinen steckt noch in den Kinderschuhen. Das Verhalten selber und die auslösenden Gründe sind vielfältig. Dennoch wird versucht, einen Zusammenhang zur Berufs-, Studien- und Laufbahnberatung herzustellen, denn auch in diesen Beratungssitzungen wird geweint. Anhand von vier Interviews mit erfahrenen Berufs-, Studien- und LaufbahnberaterInnen werden Einstellungen und Verhaltensweisen aus der Praxis explorativ erkundet und mit den theoretischen Modellen in Verbindung gebracht. Die wissenschaftlichen Theorien scheinen (noch) sehr uneinheitlich zu sein, die Aussagen aus den Interviews bestätigen jedoch Praxisberichte, die vor bald vierzig Jahren gemacht worden waren.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-26T08:12:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-26T08:12:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Master</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2207</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2207</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>87 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16486</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-04-04T13:19:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Internetgebrauch und interaktive (Online-) Spiele : Schlussbericht zur Erfüllung der Postulate Forster-Vannini (09.3521) vom 09.06.2009 und Schmid-Federer (09.3579) vom 10.06.2009 : Gefährdungspotenzial von Internet und Online-Games</dc:title>
          <dc:title>Dangers potentiels d’Internet et des jeux en ligne</dc:title>
          <dc:title>Pericolosità di Internet e die giochi in rete</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Annaheim, Beatrice</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mueller, Max</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Inglin, Sophie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wicki, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Windlin, Béat</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gmel, Gerhard</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bundesamt für Gesundheit</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Kohortenstudie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Längsschnittstudie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Online Spiel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Videospiel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Weitere Informationen zum Projekt unter: https://www.aramis.admin.ch/Texte/?ProjectID=27133</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Das Schweizerische Cannabismonitoring (cmo) beinhaltet eine längsschnittlich angelegte und gleichzeitig repräsentative Befragung von in der Schweiz wohnhaften Jugendlichen und jungen Erwachsenen im Alter von 13 bis 29 Jahren. Diese Untersuchung wurde nach 2004 und 2007, im Jahr 2010 – mit 5032 Befragten – zum dritten Mal durchgeführt. In der letzten Erhebung (2010) wurde dem Fragebogen zusätzlich ein Modul zum Thema Internetgebrauch und interaktiven (Online-) Spielen (sog. Games) angefügt. Damit konnten für die Schweiz zum ersten Mal repräsentative Zahlen zum Gameverhalten bei Jugendlichen und jungen Erwachsenen erhoben werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-04-04T13:19:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-04T13:19:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.aramis.admin.ch/Dokument.aspx?DocumentID=35340</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16486</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>47 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Bundesamt für Gesundheit</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15734</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-28T09:39:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Neue Runde im Steuerstreit zwischen der Schweiz und der EU</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hanebrink, Jens</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Schweiz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>EU</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Steuerstreit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>343: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Sachen-, Finanz-, Steuer- und Wirtschaftsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>349: Rechtsvergleichung und ausländisches Recht</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-03-01T13:34:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-01T13:34:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15734</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15734</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15734</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0005-9935</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Der Betrieb</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Handelsblatt Fachmedien</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5020</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T12:55:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wohnlichkeit im Aussenraum</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hagen Hodgson, Petra</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Stadtentwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Alter</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Grünräume</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Garten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>307: Gemeinschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>635: Gartenpflanzen (Gartenbau)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Ein Forschungsprojekt untersucht, wie älter werdende Menschen gemeinsam gärtnern, damit sie gesund bleiben, Lebensfreude und sinnlichen Genuss haben.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-10T14:47:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-10T14:47:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1942</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1942</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5020</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5020</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5020</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Hochparterre</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Hochparterre</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12762</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-24T12:43:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Homogeneous model complexes for supported rhenia metathesis catalysts</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lai, Yu-Ying</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bornand, Marc</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chen, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>540: Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>A series of rhenium trioxo complexes (L-ReO3) was synthesized, characterized, and demonstrated to be active in olefin metathesis. The relationship between perrhenate (ReO4-), perrhenyl (ReO3+), and metathesis-active rhenium complexes (L-ReO3) was elucidated. Their chemical behavior can be tuned through the Lewis acid–base interaction. DFT calculations were performed for the metathesis reaction of L-ReO3 with norbornene, which demonstrates that electron-withdrawing substituents or ligands are beneficial for olefin metathesis activity. Moreover, a rhenium-alkylidene complex was synthesized, which can be activated by B(C6F5)3 to afford an active metathesis catalyst. This system can be regarded as a homogeneous model of the hypothetical species present in the heterogeneous catalytic systems. The findings from the present study are consistent with our previous gas-phase studies and constitute the elucidation of the working principles for the metathesis-active rhenium species on the surface.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-13T15:44:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-13T15:44:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1021/om300852s</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1021/om300852s</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12762</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12762</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12762</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0276-7333</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1520-6041</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Organometallics</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>American Chemical Society</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7346</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-18T07:15:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Produktpiraterie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Münch, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brun, Simon</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Produktpiraterie, ein ebenso aktuelles wie facettenreiches Phänomen. Der vorliegende Band analysiert die vielschichtige Thematik aus juristischer, wirtschaftlicher, historischer, geografischer und kriminologischer Perspektive und zeigt Lösungsansätze und Instrumente zur Piraterie-Bekämpfung auf. Eigene Kapitel untersuchen die Piraterie in der Pharmabranche, das Geschäft mit gefälschten Uhren, die Piraterie in der Bekleidungsindustrie, die Softwarepiraterie, die Musik und Filmpiraterie sowie die Problematik der nachgeahmten Autoersatzteile. Das Buch, das aus einer interdisziplinären Lehrveranstaltung an der ZHAW School of Management and Law hervorgegangen ist, bietet eine Gesamtschau, welche die Produktpiraterie in ihren verschiedenen Aspekten und in ihren konkreten Auswirkungen in unterschiedlichen Branchen fassbar werden lässt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-26T14:17:38Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-26T14:17:38Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7346</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7346</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7346</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7255-5771-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>202 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Schulthess</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1656</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-04T08:26:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Intelligente und smarte Verpackungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Yildirim, Selçuk</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Röcker, Bettina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>664: Lebensmitteltechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Sichere und qualitativ hochwertige Lebensmittel werden vom Konsumenten vorausgesetzt. Dabei spielt die Verpackung eine grosse Rolle. Innovative Technologien wie intelligente und smarte  Verpackungen ermöglichen eine Überwachung des aktuellen Qualitätszustands eines Lebensmittels und können diesen nach aussen kommunizieren.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2017-12-04T13:35:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-12-04T13:35:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://www.lebensmittelindustrie.com/archiv-redaktion/2016/ausgabe-12/intelligente-und-smarte-verpackungen/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1656</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Lebensmittel-Industrie: Fachmagazin für das Management der Nahrungsmittel- und Getränkeindustrie</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>B2B Swiss Medien</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15397</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-26T09:57:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Linear enzyme cascade for the production of (–)-iso-isopulegol</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Peters, Christin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Buller, Rebecca</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>(–)-iso-isopulegol</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Biocatalysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ene reductases</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Enzyme cascade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Squalene hopene cyclases</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>660.6: Biotechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Biocatalysis has developed enormously in the last decade and now offers solutions for the sustainable production of chiral and highly functionalised asset molecules. Products generated by enzymatic transformations are already being used in the food, feed, chemical, pharmaceutical and cosmetic industry, and the accessible compound panoply is expected to expand even further. In particular, the combination of stereo-selective enzymes in linear cascade reactions is an elegant strategy toward enantiomeric pure compounds, as it reduces the number of isolation and purification steps and avoids accumulation of potentially unstable intermediates. Here, we present the set-up of an enzyme cascade to selectively convert citral to (-)-iso-isopulegol by combining an ene reductase and a squalene hopene cyclase. In the initial reaction step, the ene reductase YqjM from Bacillus subtilis selectively transforms citral to (S)-citronellal, which is subsequently cyclised exclusively to (-)-iso-isopulegol by a mutant of the squalene hopene cyclase from Alicyclobacillus acidocaldarius (AacSHC). With this approach, we can convert citral to an enantiopure precursor for isomenthol derivatives.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-16T09:31:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-16T09:31:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1515/znc-2018-0146</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1515/znc-2018-0146</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15397</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15397</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15397</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1865-7125</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0939-5075</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>30645192</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Zeitschrift für Naturforschung C</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>De Gruyter</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9003</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T12:31:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>How writing shapes the writer : understanding developmental changes in student writers</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kruse, Otto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Schreibentwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schreibpädagogik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wissenschaftliches Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>378: Hochschulbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The teaching and tutoring of writing is meant to instruct students on how to write better texts. This goal, however, is not the only and probably not the most important one as many interventions in writing pedagogy try to change the writer instead of the text. But how, when and why do writers change? To understand the impact of pedagogical interventions on the writer one should look at the role writing itself plays in development. I will argue that writing changes the writer in a slow, smooth and gradual way that may be called “shaping”. This is a self-induced and self-managed process and writing pedagogy has to understand its nature in order to help students navigate their intellectual development successfully. Three interrelated areas where shaping may take place will be focused on: Shaping the mind, shaping knowledge and shaping the identity of the writer. I will discuss how these fields are affected by writing and how writing pedagogy can address them differentially in order to build up academic literacy.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-15T09:16:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-15T09:16:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9003</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9003</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9003</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:0-9648067-5-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Tutoring and Teaching Academic Writing : Procedures of the Second Conference of the European Association for the Teaching of Academic Writing</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Second Conference of the European Association for the Teaching of Academic Writing, Budapest, Hungary, 23-25 June 2003</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2969</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-27T07:17:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Investigating information literacy : a growing priority in translation studies</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Massey, Gary</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ehrensberger-Dow, Maureen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Training</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Resource</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Translation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Competence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>020: Bibliotheks- und Informationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Although not always labelled as such, information literacy has been implicitly recognized as a key aspect of translation competence by practitioners, teachers, and scholars. Yet, researchers have only recently begun to systematically examine information behavior in the translation processes of students and professionals to determine how translation-centered information literacy develops. The questions of how and whether translators use the tools and resources at their disposal and how students, novices, and professionals differ in this regard remain to be investigated in detail. The multi-method approach we use to analyze translation competence and information behavior combines data from ethnographic observation of the translation situation, surveys, semi-structured interviews, keystroke logging, computer screenshot recordings, concurrent and cue-based retrospective verbalizations of recorded translation processes, and eye-tracking. We report on the initial phases and results of a study on translators' information behavior to indicate how this type of research can contribute to understanding the development of translation competence and to improving information literacy teaching.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-23T07:35:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-23T07:35:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1556/Acr.12.2011.2.4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1556/Acr.12.2011.2.4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2969</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2969</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2969</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1588-2519</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Across Languages and Cultures</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Akademiai Kiado</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23413</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-08T15:27:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ergänzungsleistungen für Familien : Erfahrungen aus dem Kanton Solothurn</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Baumgartner, Edgar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gautschi, Joel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ehrler, Franziska</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Ergänzungsleistungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Familienarmut</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sozialhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>361: Sozialarbeit und Sozialhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Nach zehnjähriger Diskussion hat der Bund 2011 das Thema Ergänzungsleistungen für Familien bis auf Weiteres den Kantonen überlassen. In Anbetracht der Blockade auf Bundesebene hat der Kanton Solothurn bereits vorgängig eine kantonale Lösung gesucht und 2010 Ergänzungsleistungen für Familien eingeführt. Evaluationsergebnisse zeigen, dass die neue Leistung im Kanton Solothurn ein wirksames Instrument zur Bekämpfung von Familienarmut darstellt und die Sozialhilfe entlastet.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-11-08T15:27:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-08T15:27:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.bsv.admin.ch/dam/bsv/de/dokumente/themenuebergreifend/publikationen/CHSS/chss-06-2014.pdf.download.pdf/de-06-2014.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23413</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1420-2670</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Soziale Sicherheit: CHSS</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Bundesamt für Sozialversicherungen</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22382</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-04-29T10:30:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Building a new high-density air temperature measurement network in two Swiss cities</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Anet, Julien G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schlögl, Sebastian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Spirig, Curdin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Frey, Martin P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Renold, Manuel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gutbrod, Karl G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>551: Geologie und Hydrologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>With progressive climate change, weather extremes are very likely to become more frequent. While rural regions may suffer from more intense and longer drought periods, urban spaces are going to be particularly affected by severe heat waves. This urban temperature anomaly, also known as “urban heat island” (UHI), can be traced back to different factors, the most prominent being soil sealing, lower albedo and lack of effective ventilation.&#13;
&#13;
City planners have started developing mitigation strategies to reduce future forecasted heat stress in urban regions. While some heat reduction strategies are currently intensely scrutinized and applied within pilot projects, the efficiency of latter mitigation actions can be overseen due to the low density of reference in situ air temperature measurements in urban environments. The same problem applies when trying to benchmark modeling studies of UHI as the amount of benchmarking data may be insufficient.&#13;
&#13;
To overcome this lack of data, over the last two years, a dense air temperature measurement network has been installed in the Swiss cities of Basel and Zurich, counting more than 450 sensors. The low-cost air temperature sensors are installed on street lamps and traffic signs in different local climate zones of the city with an emphasis on street canyons, where air temperatures are expected to be the largest and most of the city’s population lives and works. These low-cost sensors add valuable meteorological information in cities and complement the WMO reference stations.&#13;
&#13;
Air temperature measurements from the low-cost sensor network were controlled for accuracy, reliability and robustness and homogenized in order to minimize radiation errors, although 40% of the stations were equipped with self-built radiation shields, allowing an efficient passive ventilation of the installed sensors.&#13;
&#13;
We demonstrate the strength of our network by presenting first results of two exemplary heat waves that occurred in July 2019 and August 2020 and show that a) the radiation-error corrected datasets correlate well with different high-quality reference WMO stations, and b) the existence of urban heat islands in Zurich and Basel can be well confirmed, showing significant air temperature differences of several degrees between rural and urban areas.&#13;
&#13;
The results demonstrate the advantages of a high-density low-cost air temperature network as a benchmark for future urban heat islands modelling studies.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-04-29T10:30:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-04-29T10:30:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-egu21-9102</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.5194/egusphere-egu21-9102</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22382</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22382</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22382</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>EGU General Assembly 2021, Online, 19-30 April 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>European Geosciences Union</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22618</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-23T12:18:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>An underestimated photoactive area in organic solar cells based on a ZnO interlayer</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Chen, Zhi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wang, Jie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jin, Hui</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Yang, Jianming</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bao, Qinye</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ma, Zaifei</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tress, Wolfgang</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tang, Zheng</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektro-, Kommunikations-, Steuerungs- und Regelungstechnik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Solution-processed ZnO is commonly used as a charge-selective interlayer between an absorber and electrode in organic solar cells. In this work, the impact of the resistance of the sol–gel grown ZnO interlayer on solar cell performance is investigated. We find that the UV-induced doping effect leads to a significantly reduced ZnO resistance, which gives rise to an underestimated photoactive area and thus overestimated short-circuit current density (Jsc) for the solar cell measured without an aperture. Moreover, we show that this so far mostly overlooked issue can be unintentionally triggered during common fabrication and characterization processes, because the UV photons flux from a solar simulator, or from a light source for encapsulating the solar cell, are already sufficient in leading to the too much increased lateral conductivity of the ZnO. Finally, we demonstrate that interlayers with rather high sheet resistance can lead to an overestimation of Jsc (e.g. by 10% for a 10 MΩ per square interlayer in a 2 mm2 device). Therefore, the validity of the argument that high-resistance interlayers do not lead to overestimated Jsc should always be carefully evaluated.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-06-10T14:36:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-06-10T14:36:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1039/D1TC00745A</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1039/D1TC00745A</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22618</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22618</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22618</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2050-7526</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2050-7534</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of Materials Chemistry C</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Royal Society of Chemistry</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5848</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T11:47:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1075</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1074</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1076</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Planerische Strategien helfen Naturgefahrenrisiken dauerhaft zu minimieren</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jenni, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jud, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Domschky, Anke</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Naturgefahr</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Siedlungsplanung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Raumplanung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>711: Raumplanung (Städtebau)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-15T16:29:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-15T16:29:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5848</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5848</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5848</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-1692</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Die Schweizerische Kommunal-Revue</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Trend-Verlags-AG</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken completeListSize="24863" cursor="47">oai_dc////4800</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
