<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="static/style.xsl"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-06-08T16:55:16Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" resumptionToken="oai_dc////12300">https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/oai/request/</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7388</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-02T07:59:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Marketing : Konzepte - Instrumente - Aufgaben</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lucco, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rüeger, Brian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ergenzinger, Rudolf</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Thommen, Jean-Paul</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erfolgreiches Marketing zeichnet sich durch konsequente Kundenorientierung aus. Erreicht wird dies, indem Marketingstrategien sowie klassische und digitale Marketinginstrumente kreativ kombiniert und wirkungsvoll umgesetzt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-26T15:05:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-26T15:05:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7388</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7388</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7388</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-03909-146-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>207 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Versus</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5785</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T10:32:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Typology of the media use of young people in Switzerland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Süss, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Mediennutzung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Medienpsychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mediensozialisation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Jugendforschung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-08T12:59:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-08T12:59:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013-06-26</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5785</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5785</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5785</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Kongress der International Association of Media and Communication Research IAMCR, Dublin, Ireland, 26. Juni 2013</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17307</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-11T07:31:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Creative cultural production and ethnocultural revitalization among minority groups in Russia</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Suleymanova, Dilyara</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>306: Kultur</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In this article, I discuss how globally circulated forms of creative cultural production and digital technologies are appropriated by minority ethnocultural activists in Russia, and how these processes result in new forms of expression of ethnic culture and reinterpretation of minority cultural heritage. I focus on creative cultural and digital initiatives that have emerged within the last 5-7 years in an autonomous region of the Russian Federation: the Republic of Tatarstan. These initiatives were launched by young grassroots activists and entrepreneurs who are Tatars – an ethnic group that predominantly resides in the Republic of Tatarstan. As a republic with a certain degree of autonomy under the Russian federal legislation, Tatarstan has been the centre of the Tatar classic cultural production (theatre, music, arts, and literature), as well as of the Tatar language education. Under the policies of centralization and cultural unification Russia has pursued under the presidency of Vladimir Putin (2000 onwards), most of the political autonomy arrangements that Tatarstan achieved in the 1990s have been dismantled. The new restrictive ideological climate in Russia has repercussions for activism around ethnocultural questions, such as preservation of minority language and identity. At the same time, dissemination of transnational forms of cultural production and the advancement of digital technologies in Russia contribute to innovative cultural developments in the regions. Adapting these global formats and genres to the local cultural activities, the young members of the Tatar community develop new forms of ethnocultural activism. They produce alternative ways of representing and articulating ethnic identity, which depart sharply from the Soviet-born templates of representing ethnic culture. The urban activities these groups pursue allow for the depoliticization of ethnocultural activism in the conditions of an increasingly restrictive ideological and political climate in which minority activism is often equated with separatism.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-06-19T12:11:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-06-19T12:11:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1080/09502386.2018.1429004</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1080/09502386.2018.1429004</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17307</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17307</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17307</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0950-2386</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1466-4348</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Cultural Studies</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Taylor &amp; Francis</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2920</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T12:15:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Responsible journalism, media ethics and journalistic practise : media justifications and a systematic quest for answers for the publication or non-publication of Charlie-Hebdo-cartoons</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Keel, Guido</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>IAM</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Research</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>070: Nachrichtenmedien, Journalismus und Verlagswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In the aftermath of the attack on the French satirical magazine Charlie Hebdo, there was a remarkable debate in the media and on social media on the limits of satire, as well as the responsibility of the media and of journalists. Media houses published lengthy explanations on why they had decided to publish or not to publish the cartoons and/or the first Charlie Hebdo cover after the attack. In countless variations, two irreconcilable positions were held against each other: Printing cartoons offending Islam is protected by the freedom of expression, versus printing cartoons offending Islam is violating the dignity of Muslims.&#13;
This contribution first looks at the arguments and justifications of media around the world. Based on a content analysis, it describes and structures the basic lines of argument representing different views on how the concept of responsible, ethical journalism is understood and interpreted, from media around the world.&#13;
In a second step, this presentation will try to bring the different lines of seemingly irreconcilable positions together in a framework of media ethics. While the discipline of media ethics and journalism studies cannot provide us with the answer whether the cartoons should be published or not, they can at least provide us with a model which allows us to systematically look at the various arguments brought about by media houses and journalists, and integrate them into a more comprehensive analysis.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-21T16:09:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-21T16:09:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2920</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2920</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2920</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>2015 International Communication Association Nordic Regional Conference, Copenhagen, Denmark, 11-13 October 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5120</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:01:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Teaching instrumental competence in an e-learning environment : a Swiss perspective</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Massey, Gary</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riediger, Hellmut</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lenz, Simon</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Recherchieren</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Translation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Instrumentalkompetenz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>E-learning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Cognitive models used to identify and evaluate translation competence generally postulate a cluster of interacting, continuously evolving sub-competencies. Such models represent the acquisition and application of translation competence as a dynamic, open-ended process, suggesting that translator training should stress the development of procedural knowledge and skills. Initial research by PACTE (2005) indicates that the acquisition of the instrumental sub-competence, identified as "knowledge related to the use of documentation sources and information technologies applied to translation" (PACTE 2005), is a major feature distinguishing the problem-solving decisions taken by professional translators from those of novices. Trainers and practitioners have long recognised the need to integrate training in instrumental competence into translation curricula. Efficient and effective solutions are offered by the deployment of blended e-learning scenarios, with students receiving authentically situated instruction in an online environment and direct exposure to some or all of the tools and procedures of professional translation practice. This paper will describe e-learning offerings in instrumental competence developed since 2002 for the Degree Programme in Translation and the Bachelor's Programme in Language and Communication at the Zurich University of Applied Sciences, Winterthur. It will consider the process of designing, organising and integrating multilingual entry-level blended-learning courses on research methodology and information management for target groups of up to 200 students, presenting the problems, solutions, results and experiences involved, and focusing on the particular challenges posed by interactivity, collaboration and motivation.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T13:58:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T13:58:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5120</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5120</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5120</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>eCoLoTrain Workshop, Lubljana, Slovenia, 31 August - 1 September 2007</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10498</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-20T09:51:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Investigating the consequences of interference between multiple CD8+ T cell escape mutations in early HIV infection</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Garcia, Victor</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Feldman, Marcus W.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Regoes, Roland R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>CD8+ T-Lymphocytes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Computational biology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Epitopes, T-Lymphocyte</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Molecular evolution</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>HIV infections</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>HIV-1</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Humans</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Immune evasion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>571: Physiologie und verwandte Themen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>During early human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection multiple CD8+ T cell responses are elicited almost simultaneously. These responses exert strong selective pressures on different parts of HIV's genome, and select for mutations that escape recognition and are thus beneficial to the virus. Some studies reveal that the later these escape mutations emerge, the more slowly they go to fixation. This pattern of escape rate decrease(ERD) can arise by distinct mechanisms. In particular, in large populations with high beneficial mutation rates interference among different escape strains – an effect that can emerge in evolution with asexual reproduction and results in delayed fixation times of beneficial mutations compared to sexual reproduction – could significantly impact the escape rates of mutations. In this paper, we investigated how interference between these concurrent escape mutations affects their escape rates in systems with multiple epitopes, and whether it could be a source of the ERD pattern. To address these issues, we developed a multilocus Wright-Fisher model of HIV dynamics with selection, mutation and recombination, serving as a null-model for interference. We also derived an interference-free null model assuming initial neutral evolution before immune response elicitation. We found that interference between several equally selectively advantageous mutations can generate the observed ERD pattern. We also found that the number of loci, as well as recombination rates substantially affect ERD. These effects can be explained by the underexponential decline of escape rates over time. Lastly, we found that the observed ERD pattern in HIV infected individuals is consistent with both independent, interference-free mutations as well as interference effects. Our results confirm that interference effects should be considered when analyzing HIV escape mutations. The challenge in estimating escape rates and mutation-associated selective coefficients posed by interference effects cannot simply be overcome by improved sampling frequencies or sizes. This problem is a consequence of the fundamental shortcomings of current estimation techniques under interference regimes. Hence, accounting for the stochastic nature of competition between mutations demands novel estimation methodologies based on the analysis of HIV strains, rather than mutation frequencies.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-13T06:18:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-13T06:18:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4703</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004721</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4703</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004721</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10498</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10498</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10498</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1553-7358</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1553-7358</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>26829720</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>PLOS Computational Biology</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Public Library of Science</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23484</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-12T04:03:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_50</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Hokuspokus oder evidenzbasierte Therapie? : die Anwendung der Hypnose als pflegerische Intervention gegen akute Schmerzen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Crameri, Simona</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lucchini, Jano</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Acute pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pain management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Analgesia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hypnoanalgesia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hypnosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hypnotic suggestion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615: Pharmakologie und Therapeutik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616: Innere Medizin und Krankheiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Einleitung:&#13;
In der Schweiz, sowie weltweit, stellen akute Schmerzen ein zunehmendes relevantes Thema dar. Dies führt zu einem Anstieg des Schmerzmittelverbrauch, sowie den damit verbundenen Nebenwirkungen und hohen Kosten. Aus diesem Grund werden in diesem Kontext nicht-pharmakologische Interventionen vermehrt eingesetzt. Eine davon ist Hypnose, welche durch Suggestionen eine positive Veränderung der Schmerzwahrnehmung erzeugt. &#13;
&#13;
Ziel:&#13;
Diese Arbeit untersucht die Wirkung und Sinnhaftigkeit der Hypnose als pflegerische Intervention gegen akute Schmerzen. &#13;
&#13;
Methode:&#13;
Vom 17.08.2020 bis 09.02.2021 wurde in PubMed, CINAHL Complete und PsychInfo eine systematisierte Recherche durchgeführt. Um die Fragestellung zu beantworten wurden acht Studien ausgewählt, zusammengefasst und kritisch beurteilt. Zusätzlich wurde durch einen Fragebogen die Expertise von Fachpersonen erfasst. &#13;
&#13;
Relevante Ergebnisse:&#13;
Alle verwendeten Studien beschreiben eine signifikante analgetische Wirkung der Hypnose. Diese ist von Pflegefachpersonen anwendbar und erzeugt dazu eine Kostenreduktion sowie weitere Vorteile. Die Güte der Literatur wird durchschnittlich als mittelmässig beurteilt. &#13;
&#13;
Schlussfolgerung: &#13;
Hypnose hat sich als eine wirksame pflegerische Intervention gegen akute Schmerzen erwiesen. Aufgrund der Wirkung sowie der zahlreichen positiven Effekten dieses Verfahrens soll die Anwendung von Hypnose gefördert werden</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-11-11T15:10:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-11T15:10:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23484</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23484</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23484</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23484</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23484</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>139 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14987</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-02T07:58:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Entwicklungsoptionen für den Zukunftsraum Aarau : Bericht im Auftrag der 11 Gemeinden Aarau, Biberstein, Buchs (AG), Densbüren, Erlinsbach (AG), Küttigen, Muhen, Oberentfelden, Schönenwerd (SO), Suhr und Unterentfelden</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Steiner, Reto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kaiser, Claire</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Reichmuth, Lukas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Entwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fusion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gemeinde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Zukunft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Interkantonale Zusammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>350: Öffentliche Verwaltung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Mit dem Projekt „Zukunftsraum Aarau“ beabsichtigen die 11 Gemeinden Aarau, Biberstein, Buchs, Densbüren, Erlinsbach, Küttigen, Muhen, Oberentfelden, Schönenwerd (SO), Suhr und Unterentfelden den funktionalen Raum Aarau langfristig zu stärken. Zu diesem Zweck untersuchte das Kompetenzzentrum für Public Management der Universität Bern von Juni 2014 bis Juli 2015 vertieft, wie die Zusammenarbeit in der Region verbessert werden kann. Geprüft wurden die beiden Optionen „Verstärkte interkommunale Zusammenarbeit“ und „Fusion“ sowie deren mögliche Auswirkungen auf die Organisation, die Finanzen, die Demokratie und Identifikation der Bevölkerung sowie die Regionalentwicklung (Raum-, Siedlungs-, Infrastruktur- und Landschaftsentwicklung). Eine kantonsübergreifende Fusion wurde gemäss Auftrag ausgeschlossen, weshalb Schönenwerd nur für die Variante der verstärkten IKZ berücksichtigt wurde.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-05T15:41:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-05T15:41:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14987</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14987</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14987</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>KPM-Schriftenreihe</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>214 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>KPM</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18726</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-12T10:29:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Interpreting, translation and English as a lingua franca (ELF)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Albl-Mikasa, Michaela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>420: Englisch</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-11-14T15:36:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-11-14T15:36:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18726</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18726</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18726</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Invited lecture held at Waseda University, Tokyo, Japan on 12 June 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11593</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-13T08:58:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Exportpotenzialmonitor für die Nahrungsmittelindustrie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Flückiger, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>338: Produktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Tagungsreferat</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-10T11:46:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-10T11:46:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11593</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11593</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11593</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Tag der Schweizer Nahrungsmittel-Industrie, Bern, 31. August 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23745</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-12-11T13:34:44Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Combining ICF and Clinical Reasoning in a single case documentation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Luomajoki, Hannu</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Akhbari Ziegler, Schirin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Huber, Omega</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-12-11T13:34:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-12-11T13:34:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23745</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23745</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23745</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Wien European Physiotherapy Teachers Association, 2012</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14724</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T11:32:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>"Öffentliche Beziehungen" als organisationale Öffentlichkeit : funktionale Rahmenbedingungen von Öffentlichkeitsarbeit</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Szyszka, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>659: Werbung und Öffentlichkeitsarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-01-29T14:16:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-29T14:16:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1999</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-663-10931-0_9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-663-10931-0_9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14724</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14724</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14724</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-531-13399-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-663-10931-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Öffentlichkeit : Diskurs zu einem Schlüsselbegriff der Organisationskommunikation</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Westdeutscher Verlag</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22039</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-16T04:01:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Using smartphone accelerometer data to obtain scientific mechanical-biological descriptors of resistance exercise training</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Viecelli, Claudio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Graf, David</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Aguayo, David</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hafen, Ernst</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Füchslin, Rudolf M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Accelerometry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Adult</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Female</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Healthy volunteer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Human</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Male</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Middle aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Muscle contraction</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Muscle, skeletal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Reproducibility of results</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Weight lifting</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Young adult</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Resistance training</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Smartphone</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>613: Persönliche Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Background&#13;
Single repetition, contraction-phase specific and total time-under-tension (TUT) are crucial mechano-biological descriptors associated with distinct morphological, molecular and metabolic muscular adaptations in response to exercise, rehabilitation and/or fighting sarcopenia. However, to date, no simple, reliable and valid method has been developed to measure these descriptors.&#13;
&#13;
Objective&#13;
In this study we aimed to test whether accelerometer data obtained from a standard smartphone placed on the weight stack can be used to extract single repetition, contraction-phase specific and total TUT.&#13;
&#13;
Methods&#13;
Twenty-two participants performed two sets of ten repetitions of their 60% one repetition maximum with a self-paced velocity on nine commonly used resistance exercise machines. Two identical smartphones were attached on the resistance exercise weight stacks and recorded all user-exerted accelerations. An algorithm extracted the number of repetitions, single repetition, contraction-phase specific and total TUT. All exercises were video-recorded. The TUT determined from the algorithmically-derived mechano-biological descriptors was compared with the video recordings that served as the gold standard. The agreement between the methods was examined using Limits of Agreement (LoA). The association was calculated using the Pearson correlation coefficients and interrater reliability was determined using the intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC 2.1).&#13;
&#13;
Results&#13;
The error rate of the algorithmic detection of single repetitions derived from two smartphones accelerometers was 0.16%. Comparing algorithmically-derived, contraction-phase specific TUT against video, showed a high degree of correlation (r&gt;0.93) for all exercise machines. Agreement between the two methods was high on all exercise machines as follows: LoA ranged from -0.3 to 0.3 seconds for single repetition TUT (0.1% of mean TUT), from -0.6 to 0.3 seconds for concentric contraction TUT (7.1% of mean TUT), from -0.3 to 0.5 seconds for eccentric contraction TUT (4.1% of mean TUT) and from -1.9 to 1.1 seconds for total TUT (0.5% of mean TUT). Interrater reliability for single repetition, contraction-phase specific TUT was high (ICC &gt; 0.99).&#13;
&#13;
Conclusion&#13;
Data from smartphone accelerometer derived resistance exercise can be used to validly and reliably extract crucial mechano-biological descriptors. Moreover, the presented multi-analytical algorithmic approach enables researchers and clinicians to reliably and validly report missing mechano-biological descriptors.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-03-15T09:49:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-03-15T09:49:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0235156</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-22039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0235156</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-22039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1932-6203</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>32667945</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>PLOS ONE</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Public Library of Science </dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1471</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-04T14:45:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Tripartite species interaction : eukarotic hosts suffer more from phage susceptible than from phage resistant bacteria</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wendling, Carolin Charlotte</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Piecyk, Agnes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Refardt, Dominik</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chibani, Cynthia Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hertel, Robert</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Liesegang, Heiko</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bunk, Boyke</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Overmann, Jörg</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Roth, Olivia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Bacteriophages</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vibrio</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pipefish</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lysogeny</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>570: Biologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Background: Evolutionary shifts in bacterial virulence are often associated with a third biological player, for instance temperate phages, that can act as hyperparasites. By integrating as prophages into the bacterial genome they can contribute accessory genes, which can enhance the fitness of their prokaryotic carrier (lysogenic conversion). Hyperparasitic influence in tripartite biotic interactions has so far been largely neglected in empirical host-parasite studies due to their inherent complexity. Here we experimentally address whether bacterial resistance to phages and bacterial harm to eukaryotic hosts is linked using a natural tri-partite system with bacteria of the genus Vibrio, temperate vibriophages and the pipefish Syngnathus typhle. We induced prophages from all bacterial isolates and constructed a three-fold replicated, fully reciprocal 75 × 75 phage-bacteria infection matrix.&#13;
&#13;
Results: According to their resistance to phages, bacteria could be grouped into three distinct categories: highly susceptible (HS-bacteria), intermediate susceptible (IS-bacteria), and resistant (R-bacteria). We experimentally challenged pipefish with three selected bacterial isolates from each of the three categories and determined the amount of viable Vibrio counts from infected pipefish and the expression of pipefish immune genes. While the amount of viable Vibrio counts did not differ between bacterial groups, we observed a significant difference in relative gene expression between pipefish infected with phage susceptible and phage resistant bacteria.&#13;
&#13;
Conclusion: These findings suggest that bacteria with a phage-susceptible phenotype are more harmful against a eukaryotic host, and support the importance of hyperparasitism and the need for an integrative view across more than two levels when studying host-parasite evolution.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2017-11-13T15:33:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-11-13T15:33:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3456</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12862-017-0930-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3456</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1186/s12862-017-0930-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1471</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1471</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1471</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1471-2148</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>BMC Evolutionary Biology</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>BioMed Central</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18337</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T13:56:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_51</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ergotherapie für Erwachsene mit Sehbehinderung : die Kompetenzen und Aufgaben der Ergotherapie in der interprofessionellen Rehabilitation von Erwachsenen mit Sehbehinderung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hofer, Lena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schnüriger, Sandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Occupational therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Competence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Interprofessional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Low Vision Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610: Medizin und Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615.8515: Ergotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Altersbedingte Sehbehinderungen kommen durch die zunehmende Lebenserwartung in der Schweiz immer häufiger vor. Diese haben einen grossen Einfluss auf die Selbstständigkeit im Alltag. In der Schweiz existieren bereits Angebote für Menschen mit Sehbehinderung, in welchen vorwiegend «Rehabilitationsfachkräfte» arbeiten. Die Ergotherapie ist im Vergleich zu anderen Ländern in diesem Gebiet noch wenig vertreten.
Das Ziel unserer Arbeit ist, Kompetenzen und Aufgaben der Ergotherapie in der interprofessionellen Sehbehindertenrehabilitation für Erwachsene in der Schweiz zu definieren.
Es wurde eine strukturierte Literaturrecherche auf diversen Gesundheitsdatenbanken durchgeführt. In der anschliessenden Selektion wurden Quellen ausgewählt, in denen die Ergotherapie in einem interprofessionellen Behandlungsteam untersucht wurde. Die Artikel wurden in das ICF-Modell eingeordnet.
Wichtige Kompetenzen und Aufgaben haben Ergotherapeutinnen und Ergotherapeuten in den Domänen Aktivitäten und Partizipation, beispielsweise bei der Unterstützung der Hilfsmittelanwendung in Alltagsaktivitäten. Weiter können sie in der Domäne Umweltfaktoren beispielsweise Abklärungen und Anpassungen im häuslichen Umfeld vornehmen.
Die betätigungsfokussierte und ganzheitliche Herangehensweise der Ergotherapie widerspiegelt sich in den Resultaten. Da sich die verwendeten Begriffe wenig von den Kompetenzen der Rehabilitationsfachkräfte unterscheiden, sind für eine gute interprofessionelle Zusammenarbeit gemeinsame Absprachen im Team notwendig.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-10-04T13:15:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-10-04T13:15:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-18337</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-18337</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18337</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18337</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18337</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>117 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19729</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-12T14:13:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die OTIPM Implementierung in der Neurologie am Inselspital : von akut bis ambulant</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Senn, Daniela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eichenberger, Magdalena</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.8515: Ergotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616.8: Neurologie und Krankheiten des Nervensystems</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-03-12T14:13:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-03-12T14:13:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19729</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19729</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19729</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Ergotherapie-Kongress «ergo5.0 - Stars of Daily Living», Locarno, 6.-7. September 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17219</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:30:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_24</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1094</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_33</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Individualisierte Versicherungslösungen in einer digitalen Welt : eine Studie des Zentrums für Risk &amp; Insurance</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Arisov, Elisabeth</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Becker, Johannes Gerd</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Erny, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zeier Röschmann, Angela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Digitalisierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Versicherungen in der Schweiz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Motorfahrzeugversicherung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Krankenzusatzversicherung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gebäude- und Hausratsversicherung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Quantifizierung von Risiko</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332.38: Versicherungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-06-05T11:51:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-06-05T11:51:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3237</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3237</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17219</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17219</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17219</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>42 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10645</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:39:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>What drives SME to energy efficient behavior? : results of a Swiss survey</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hackenfort, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rohrer, Jürg</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Verhalten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Behavior</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Energy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Climate</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333.79: Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Though energy efficient behavior plays a key role in Swiss policy decisions, only few SME participate in energy efficiency programs (EEP). In order to better understand the underlying decision making process of executives, we developed a questionnaire referring to different psychological theories. 
3 groups of executives in SME could be separated: a non-, planned- and realized-participation group. Differences occurred, for example, with regard to the awareness of the own energy consumption, the estimation of how much the SME could take advantage of a participation in EEP and their self estimated knowledge of efficiency measures in general.
Therefore, it seems to be crucial to consider the results of the study when executives in SME should be addressed to take part in energy efficiency measures.  </dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-17T12:32:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-17T12:32:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10645</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10645</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10645</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>BECCC Behavior - Energy &amp; Climate Change Conference, Sacramento CA, USA, 18-21 October 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17510</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-16T13:49:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Zusammen in die Zukunft : fit für Data Science</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Heitz, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Heinatz Bürki, Gundula</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meierhofer, Jürg</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Data Science</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Smart Services</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>KMU</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658: Allgemeines Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Daten sind das Gold des 21. Jahrhunderts - dessen sind sich auch die KMU in der Schweiz bewusst. Doch begrenzte Ressourcen und Fokus auf das operative Geschäft hemmen den Einsatz von datengetriebener Innovation. Hier setzt das Projekt Data4KMU des IBH-Labs KMUdigital an und will auch KMU den Anschluss an Data Science ermöglichen. Die Erfolgsgeschichte ist eines der Innovationsprojekte, welches von Mitgliedern der Swiss Alliance for Data-Intensive Services geleitet wird, dem Schweizer Technologie-Netzwerk, das Unternehmen bei der Entwicklung neuer datenbasierten Produkte und Dienstleistungen unterstützt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-07-17T09:17:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-07-17T09:17:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://issuu.com/prestigemedia/docs/kmurundschau_2019_02</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17510</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2296-7575</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>KMU Rundschau</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Prestige Media</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13860</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T09:27:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Percolation concepts in solid state ionics</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dieterich, Wolfgang</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dürr, Oliver</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pendzig, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bunde, Armin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nitzan, Abraham</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>530: Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Structural disorder is an inherent property of solid materials, which can support a macroscopic ionic current. Many transport phenomena in these solid ionic conductors appear to be related to concepts from percolation theory. We demonstrate this for three classes of materials, namely (i) dispersed ionic conductors, which show conductance properties that can be related to random electrical networks, (ii) ion-doped network glasses, whose concentration-dependent diffusion properties are accessible by critical path analysis, and (iii) polymer ionic conductors. For the latter we discuss Monte Carlo simulations which indicate the applicability of dynamic bond percolation theory.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-12-14T15:09:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-14T15:09:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1999</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/S0378-4371(98)00597-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/S0378-4371(98)00597-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13860</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13860</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13860</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0378-4371</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1873-2119</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13556</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-16T07:28:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>"Kann ich mir das überhaupt zumuten?" : wie Menschen mit zerebralem Insult und Multipler Sklerose die mobilitätsfördernde Pflegeintervention auf dem Boden erleben</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Suter-Riederer, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mahrer Imhof, Romy</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schnepp, W.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Imhof, Lorenz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Erleben</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pflegeintervention</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bewegungsförderung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Alltag</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Phänomenologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616.8: Neurologie und Krankheiten des Nervensystems</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-12-05T13:42:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-05T13:42:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13556</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13556</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13556</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2414-6889</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2409-448X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal für Qualitative Forschung in Pflege- und Gesundheitswissenschaft</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>pflegenetz</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13671</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T09:25:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Unterrichts-Leitlinien für einen problem- und handlungsorientierten Unterricht in gymnasialen Lehr-/Lernumgebungen : theoretische Festlegung, Umsetzung und Wirkung in der Schulpraxis - eine Pilot-Studie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Eberle, Franz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Müller Werder, Claude</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pflüger, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Otazo, Priscilla</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>371: Schulen und schulische Tätigkeiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-12-07T13:39:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-07T13:39:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13671</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13671</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13671</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3-905905-00-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Beiträge zur Handlungsorientierung</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Berichte aus Praxis und Forschung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>hep-Verlag</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1811</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T10:17:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>European academy of nursing science and the Swedish Society of Nursing summer conference 2017 : the future direction of European nursing and nursing research</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Polit, Denise F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sidani, Souraya</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Richards, David A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Willman, Ania</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kitson, Alison</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Huijben-Schoenmakers, Marleen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rademaker, Arno</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Scherder, Erik</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bjuresäter, Kaisa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Larsson, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bergsten, Ulrika</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Smith, Margaret Coulter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pearson, Claire</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tropea, Savina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>O’May, Fiona</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Irvine, Lindesay</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rush, Robert</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wilson, Rowena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rahn, Anne C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Behncke, Anja</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Buhl, Anke</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Köpke, Sascha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, Maria Goreti Da Rocha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Shaha, Maya</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hjelm, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bohman, Doris M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Willman, Ania</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kristensson, Jimmie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Holst, Göran</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Øverlie, Anne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Machiels, Mariska</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zwakhalen, Sandra M. G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Metzelthin, Silke F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hamers, Jan P. H.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Darcy, Laura</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Karlsson, Katarina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Galvin, Kathleen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Van Hecke, Ann</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Malfait, Simon</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eeckloo, Kristof</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Råberus, Anna</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Holmström, Inger K.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sundler, Annelie J.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dijkstra, Ate</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gesar, Berit</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bååth, Carina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hedin, Hanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hommel, Ami</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Helou, Nancy</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Shaha, Maya</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zanchi, Anne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Varsi, Cecilie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Børøsund, Elin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mirkovic, Jelena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marcheschi, Elizabeth</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Von Koch, Lena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pessah-Rasmussen, Hélène</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Elf, Marie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Audulv, Åsa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kneck, Åsa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Koppitz, Andrea Luise</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>de Wolf-Linder, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Blanc, Geneviève</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bosshard, Georg</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Volken, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2017-12-13T15:30:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-12-13T15:30:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12912-017-0218-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1186/s12912-017-0218-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1811</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1811</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1811</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>European Academy of Nursing Science and the Swedish Society of Nursing Summer Conference, Malmö, Sweden, 4-5 July 2017</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23567</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-29T09:18:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Asset oder Risiko : eine Bestandsaufnahme zu Goodwill und Goodwill-Impairment der SMI- und DAX-Unternehmen (Teil 2)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Acker, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gut, Madeleine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Streiff, Gheorghita</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Begründung impairment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>DAX</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Goodwill</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Goodwill-Bestand</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.1: Organisation und Finanzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Frage, ob Goodwill ein Asset oder Risiko darstellt, ist in Krisenzeiten dringlich. Es ist zu klären, inwieweit die über Jahre angewachsenen Goodwill-Beträge in den Konzernbilanzen der SMI- und DAX-Unternehmen (siehe hierzu Teil 1 des Beitrags, IRZ 2021, IRZ Jahr 2021 Seite 233 ff., Heft 5) im Corona-Jahr 2020 weiterhin bestehen. Im Fokus des aktuellen Beitrags steht eine Bestandsaufnahme des Goodwills und der Goodwill-Impairments im SMI und DAX im Jahr 2020 der Covid-19-Pandemie. Die ergänzende qualitative Analyse der Anhangberichterstattung liefert aufschlussreiche Erkenntnisse zur Begründung von Impairments aufgrund von Covid-19. Das Ergebnis der Untersuchung verdeutlicht, dass die einschneidenden Auswirkungen der Pandemie die Werthaltigkeit des im Zeitverlauf angehäuften Goodwill-Volumens weniger als erwartet beeinflussten und sich die vermutete Goodwill-Blase auch in der Krise resilient zeigt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-11-29T09:18:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-29T09:18:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23567</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23567</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23567</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1862-5533</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Zeitschrift für internationale Rechnungslegung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Beck</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15207</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-02-07T16:40:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Vorbemerkungen zu den §§ 36-50 KV</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wiederkehr, René</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>342: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Staats- und Verwaltungsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-02-07T16:40:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-07T16:40:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15207</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15207</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15207</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7272-8725-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Kommentar der Kantonsverfassung Luzern</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Stämpfli</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14292</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-12T13:18:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kurzpräsentation des Projekts Konzept und Umsetzung eines Schweizer Zentrums für Barrierefreie Kommunikation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jekat, Susanne Johanna</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Barrierefreie Kommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schweizer Zentrum für barrierefreie Kommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.0087: Barrierefreie Kommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-01-10T13:46:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-10T13:46:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14292</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14292</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14292</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Departementsversammlung Angewandte Linguistik ZHAW, Winterthur, 14. März 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13639</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-12-16T12:31:45Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Map-generation algorithm using low-frequency vehicle position data</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Steiner, Albert</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leonhardt, Axel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>TRB</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Map generation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Traffic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Floating car data</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Providing accurate map data is essential for a variety of applications in traffic engineering, e.g. navigation systems. To overcome costs and effort associated with classical map generation methods (e.g. surveying or specialized vehicles) a method for automatic map generation based on position data stemming from vehicle fleets that are already equipped with GPS and participate in day-to-day traffic is presented. The method is designed in particular for urban road networks, where building work is carried out frequently.&#13;
In this paper we make use of taxi fleet data for map generation. The data used were recorded at relatively low frequencies (15 to 90 seconds), such that a trivial connection of subsequent positions is not possible. The problem is solved by processing the data through a series of algorithmic steps. After data cleaning and transforming raw data by a Transverse Mercator projection to a plane, density regions based on geographic position and estimated headings are calculated. The density images are filtered by a Gaussian kernel and a watershed transform is applied. From the resulting image a skeleton is derived and intersections are detected by dedicated rules.&#13;
The resulting directed graph is compared with aerial images from Google Earth and an existing OpenStreetMap digital road network.&#13;
Using data from vehicles participating in day-to-day traffic allows not only to derive static network information (nodes / links), but - depending on the vehicle fleet used - to annotate the resulting graph with attributes directly deduced from data, like typical link speed distributions or turning fractions at intersections.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-12-07T08:13:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-07T08:13:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13639</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13639</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13639</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>TRB 90th Annual Meeting Compendium of Papers</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>90th Annual Meeting of the Transportation Research Board, Washington, USA, 23-27 January 2011</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Transportation Research Board</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6505</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-14T13:36:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wirtschaftskrise : Politisierung der Unternehmenskommunikation?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stücheli-Herlach, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Public Affairs</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Organisationskommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wirtschaftskommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>330: Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>401.4: Lexikologie und Terminologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Wirtschaftskrise in den Industrieländern hat nicht nur kurzfristig zu einer Politisierung der Unternehmenskommunikation geführt. Das Phänomen dürfte länger andauern und an Intensität gewinnen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-04T13:17:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-04T13:17:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6505</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6505</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6505</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>IAM live, Kundenveranstaltung, Winterthur, 5. Mai 2009</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5055</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-04-10T15:51:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Kunst des In-die-Geschichten-Erzählens</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Perrin, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-10T15:51:21Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-10T15:51:21Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5055</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5055</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5055</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-906272-30-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Die Kunst der Story : Journalismus-Atelier</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Werd Weber</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3263</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-18T07:15:39Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Practical instrumental analysis : methods, quality assurance and laboratory management</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Petrozzi, Sergio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Laboratory class</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Instrumental analytics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>540: Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-02-27T15:06:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-27T15:06:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1002/9783527665891</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1002/9783527665891</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3263</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3263</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3263</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-527-32951-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>467 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Wiley</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/588</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:42:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_52</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Eine Analyse der konservativen und nichtmedikamentösen Behandlung von kindlicher Adipositas zur Prävention von Folgekrankheiten : welche Rolle spielt dabei die Physiotherapie?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Christen, Salome</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:06:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:06:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-588</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-588</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/588</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/588</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/588</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23923</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-14T13:34:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Froid de confort – aujourd’hui : solutions intelligentes pour un climat intérieur agréable</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brunner, Arnold</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kriegers, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Prochaska, Vladimir</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tillenkamp, Frank</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Réfrigération</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Froid de confort</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>620: Ingenieurwesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Les bonnes solutions de techniques du bâtiment sont mises en réseau et prennent toujours en compte l’en- semble du système, qu’il s’agisse de bâtiments, de complexes de bâtiments ou de zones entières. Nous considé- rons donc le froid de confort d’au- jourd’hui comme une machine frigori- fique-thermique exploitant judicieuse- ment la précieuse chaleur produite lors du refroidissement. Toutefois, ces so- lutions ne fonctionnent que si elles sont robustes et peuvent être utilisées facilement et correctement dans la vie quotidienne.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-01-14T13:34:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-01-14T13:34:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://pubdb.bfe.admin.ch/fr/publication/download/9742</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23923</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>211 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Die Planer - SWKI</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24197</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-09T13:30:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Environmental adjustment needs of children with special educational needs in Austrian mainstream schools : the child and teacher perspective</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Morgenthaler, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kramer-Roy, Debbie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schulze, Christina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Participation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Special educational need</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Child perspective</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Inclusion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Accommodation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Barrier</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>371: Schulen und schulische Tätigkeiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Children with special educational needs included in Austrian main stream schools are provided with special educational support, which aim to create learning environments, that meet the children’s needs on an individual level. Little is known about what adjustments children with special educational needs in mainstream school classes require to promote participation in school occupations. This is the first study in Austria exploring the student-environment-fit from self-perceived chil dren’s perspective and comparing this to teachers’ perspective by using the School Setting Interview. In this cross-sectional matched  pairs study twenty-five children (mean age 12.5 ± 1.4) with special educational needs and twenty-one teachers from six Austrian second ary schools were interviewed. Participants’ ratings were analyzed descriptively and statistically with Wilcoxon-Sign Rank Test. Reported adjustments from the child and teacher perspectives were analyzed with qualitative content analysis and presented using the occupa tional, social and physical environmental dimensions from the Model of Human Occupation. Results indicate perceived student environment-fit differs between school activities as well as between children and teachers. Three out of 16 school activities showed a statistically significant difference between children and teacher matched-pair analysis. Children perceive more unmet needs then teachers. Most adjustments are reported in the social environment dimension and inform practitioners what adjustments are perceived to be useful for children with Special Educational Needs and their tea chers. Both children’s and teacher’s perspectives provide valuable information. Significantly, children in this study were able to identify required needs and describe adjustments. To increase participation in school occupations, children can and need to be actively included in the decision-making process.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-02-04T15:16:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-02-04T15:16:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1080/19411243.2022.2027838</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-24197</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1080/19411243.2022.2027838</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-24197</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24197</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24197</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24197</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1941-1243</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1941-1251</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of Occupational Therapy, Schools, &amp; Early Intervention</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Taylor &amp; Francis</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/784</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T10:44:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_236</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_237</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Lebenszufriedenheit und Diabetes Mellitus : erste Schritte zur deutschen Validierung des Diabetes Quality Of Life Measure DQOL</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nick, Eva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vasella, Noëmi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Diabetes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Diabetes mellitus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Zufriedenheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lebensqualität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fragebogen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Validierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:10:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:10:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-784</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-784</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/784</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/784</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/784</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>77 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1280</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T13:56:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_53</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kiwi-Vakuum versus Metallglocke - ein Vergleich : die Vor- und Nachteile der jeweiligen Methode in Bezug auf zwei maternale und neonatale Outcomes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gassler, Anja</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Häfliger, Michelle</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Vacuum assisted delivery</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kiwi OmniCup</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Metal cup</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Maternal and neonatal outcome</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Darstellung des Themas: Die Vakuumentbindungsrate in der Schweiz ist steigend. Da das Kiwi Vakuum das jüngste System auf dem Markt ist, lassen sich in den Fachbüchern noch kaum Vor- und/oder Nachteile dieses Extraktors im Vergleich zu älteren Extraktoren finden. Als problematisch beobachtet wird in der Praxis, dass das Kiwi OmniCup unter anderem durch seine Betitelung „Kiwi“ von den Paaren oft nicht als Vakuumextraktion wahrgenommen wird.
Ziel: Ziel dieses Literaturreviews ist es, das Kiwi Vakuum mit der Metallglocke zu vergleichen und mögliche Vor- und/oder Nachteile in Bezug auf das maternale Outcome (Dammintakt/-riss I bis IV°, Episiotomie) und das neonatale Outcome (Kephalhämatom, leichte Kopfverletzung wie Geburtsgeschwulst oder Hautschürfung) abzuleiten.
Methode: In medizinischen Datenbanken sowie Google Scholar wurde nach themenrelevanten Studien recherchiert. Vier Studien wurden unter Berücksichtigung definierter Ein- und Ausschlusskriterien selektiert und ausgewertet.
Relevante Ergebnisse: Der Vergleich der beiden Vakuumextraktoren dieser Studien lässt keine Vor- und/oder Nachteile bezüglich den festgelegten maternalen und neonatalen Outcomes ableiten.
Schlussfolgerung: Die Hebammenbetreuung von Frauen und ihren Neugeborenen während und nach einer Vakuumextraktion sollte nicht vom Vakuumextraktor bestimmt werden, da die Auswirkungen dieselben sind. Wichtig ist, dass die Frauen nach beiden Vakuumextraktoren ausführlich über deren mögliche Folgen aufgeklärt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2017-07-19T09:07:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-07-19T09:07:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1279</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1279</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1280</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1280</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1280</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>41 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9546</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-25T16:52:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Datenschutz im Sozialversicherungsrecht  : Weitergabe von Krankendaten an die Krankenassen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hedinger, Barbara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pärli, Kurt</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wantz, Nadine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Sozialversicherungsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pflegerecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Datenschutz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>344: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Arbeits-, Sozial-, Bildungs- und Kulturrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-08-24T08:11:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-24T08:11:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9546</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9546</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9546</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2235-2953</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2235-6851</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Pflegerecht</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Stämpfli</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18186</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-16T07:28:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Management research and religion : a citation analysis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Filser, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>200: Religion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658: Allgemeines Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Research on management with regard to religion became a growing field of interest in the last decades. Nevertheless, the impact of religion on actor’s economic behavior is also an old research topic, as the writings of Max Weber (The protestant ethic and the spirit of capitalism, Allen and Unwin, London, 1930) underline. The purpose of this contribution is to highlight the developments of this topic and to guide scholars to identify possible gaps. The structuring and investigation on this topic will help us to advance and better understand past research, while leading to some further reflections. We conduct a citation analysis of 215 articles and 7,968 cited references to examine the citation structure and make out the most-influential publications that have shaped research most so far. On the basis of the analysis it is to be assumed that three research streams affect progress: Best practices regarding performance issues, religion at work as well as religion, and personal ethics. Finally, the publications that each topic-clusters contains are reflected and discussed to achieve a structural overview of the state of the art of research.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-09-12T13:44:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-09-12T13:44:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012-02-18</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10551-012-1240-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/s10551-012-1240-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18186</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18186</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18186</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0167-4544</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1573-0697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of Business Ethics</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23455</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-29T13:37:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Automated assessment of writing and pragmatic competence : a critical review</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gautschi, Curtis</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Automated assessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pragmatics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Writing assessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>410.285: Computerlinguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The automated scoring of essays and other written texts (AES), by means of natural language processing tools, is playing an ever-increasing role in the evaluation of writing ability. While able to provide quick, cost-effective and consistent feedback to learners of foreign languages (Shermis &amp; Burstein, 2013), the use of computers to assess writing skills has been met with considerable scepticism (Condon, 2013). Of particular concern is the issue of construct relevance and representation in the automated assessment of writing (Weigle, 2013), which has relied heavily on a narrow range of linguistic features (e.g., McNamara, Crossley &amp; McCarthy, 2010), cohesion markers or complexity indices (e.g., Coh-index; see Allen, Jacovina, &amp; McNamara, 2016). Thus, while aspects of organizational competence (e.g., grammatical, lexical, syntax and text-level organization) are to some degree measurable, the valid measurement of pragmatic competence remains a challenge for AES (e.g., communicative facets including message conveyance, communicative intent, sensitivity to genre, and the socially constructed transfer of meaning - see, Allen et al., 2016; Bridgeman, Powers, Stone &amp; Mollaun, 2011; Deane, 2013). This has been acknowledged by leaders in the high-stakes AES industry in their efforts to improve the measurement of pragmatic aspects in the communicative paradigm for both automated assessment of writing and speaking (e.g., Chen et al., 2018; Evanini, Hauck &amp; Hakuta, 2017).&#13;
&#13;
This presentation seeks to problematize the issues raised above. First, an AES tool and CEFR-level prediction algorithm created and experimentally implemented at a major University of Applied Sciences in Switzerland as part of an online English placement test for first-year engineering students (Gautschi, 2020) is critically examined with respect to its design, results and coverage of pragmatic competence aspects. Second the AES tool is placed within the context of current AES research and approaches to modelling pragmatic competence, with a view to critically reviewing:&#13;
•	current scoring model approaches&#13;
•	claims of communicative and pragmatic competence assessment&#13;
•	advancements in scoring accuracy through deep learning / neural network techniques&#13;
•	the reliance on human-machine agreement for validation support.&#13;
&#13;
Finally, it is argued that the value of future AES in testing crucially requires the active involvement of linguists and applied linguists to safeguard construct coverage of pragmatic competence in high-stakes assessment of communicative language ability by means of automated writing assessment.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-11-11T11:42:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-11T11:42:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23455</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23455</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23455</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>17th International Pragmatics Conference : abstracts</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>17th International Pragmatics Conference (IPrA), Winterthur (online), 27 June - 2 July 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>International Pragmatics Association (IPrA)</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7524</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-26T06:25:47Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Tagungsbericht : Coaching meets Research ... Praxisfelder im Fokus 5./6. Juni 2012, Basel, Schweiz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Seiger, Christine Pascale</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Künzli, Hansjörg</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Coaching</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Tagung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Forschung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Praxisfelder</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wissenstransfer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>158: Angewandte Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenzen.ch)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Über 200 Teilnehmerinnen und Teilnehmer kamen zum 2. Internationalen Coaching-Forschungskongress im deutschsprachigen Raum, der auch in diesem Jahr wieder von der Hochschule für Soziale Arbeit der Fachhochschule Nordwestschweiz (FHNW) organisiert wurde, gemeinsam mit vielen Kongresspartnern. &#13;
Neben Coaches zog es Forschende, Verbandsvertreter, Personalfachleute und Ausbilder nach Basel. Im Zentrum standen Praxisfelder von Coaching. Wie schon vor zwei Jahren war es die Absicht der Organisatoren, so der Kongressleiter Robert Wegener, durch vielfältige Formate eine Plattform für verschiedene Akteure der internationalen Coaching-Community zu bieten und den Dialog zwischen Forschung und Praxis anzuregen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-29T10:42:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-29T10:42:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4326</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11613-012-0295-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4326</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/s11613-012-0295-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7524</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7524</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7524</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1618-808X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1862-2577</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Organisationsberatung, Supervision, Coaching</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23866</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-25T08:17:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Rolle eines Hebammennetzwerkes in der Frühen Förderung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Grylka, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zsindely, Piroska</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Iseli, Katharina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Weber-Käser, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Freipraktizierende Hebamme</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Frühe Förderung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Netzwerkarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wochenbett</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Fragestellung: Projekte der Frühen Förderung bezwecken, psychosozial benachteiligte Familien zu unterstützen, damit ihre Kinder sich gut entwickeln und sich ihre sozialen Chancen im späteren Leben erhöhen. Eine lückenlose Versorgung ab Geburt ist für den Erfolg solcher Projekte wichtig. Freipraktizierende Hebammen übernehmen in der Versorgungskette eine wichtige Rolle, da sie ein niederschwelliges Wochenbettbetreuungsangebot für die erste Zeit nach dem Klinikaufenthalt anbieten. Hebammennetzwerke unterstützen Familien, die sich nicht selbst eine Hebamme organisieren können und bieten eine Betreuungsgarantie. Ziel dieser Studie ist, die Rolle eines Hebammennetzwerkes in der Frühen Förderung zu evaluieren.&#13;
&#13;
Methode: Die Evaluationsstudie umfasste drei Teilstudien: 1) Während eines Jahres wurden soziodemographische und perinatale Daten sowie Betreuungsaspekte von 192 der 240 vermittelten Wöchnerinnen (80,0%) in einem Erhebungstool erfasst. Zudem wurde mit den im Netzwerk tätigen Hebammen eine Onlineumfrage durchführt (n=41 Teilnehmerinnen, Rücklaufquote 91,1%). Mit insgesamt 15 Stakeholder/-innen wurden Einzel- und Gruppeninterviews geführt. Quantitativen Daten wurden deskriptiv mit R 4.0.3 und Stata 15 analysiert. Interviews wurden transkribiert und inhaltsanalytisch ausgewertet.&#13;
&#13;
Ergebnisse: Ein Großteil der vermittelten Frauen war ausländischer Nationalität (81,8%) und 30,7% hatte keine abgeschlossene Ausbildung. Insgesamt 66,7% der Hebammen besuchten die über die Hotline vermittelten Frauen gleich häufig wie Frauen, die selber eine Hebamme organisiert hatten; 23,1% etwas oder deutlich weniger häufig und 10,3% etwas oder deutlich häufiger. Nur wenige Hebammen (10,3%) wendeten Assessmentinstrumente für die Kindeswohlgefährdung häufig oder systematisch an, obwohl fast alle (92,3%) diese kannten. Aspekte zur Wichtigkeit der Vermittlungshotline für die Frühe Förderung fanden sich in den Themen «Versorgung im Netzwerk», «Nutzen für die Stakeholder» und «Frau und Familie» der Interviews. Mehrere Stakeholder betonten die wichtige Rolle der Hebammen im regionalen Projekt der Frühen Förderung. Das Schnittstellenmanagement zur Klinik funktionierte einwandfrei, dasjenige zu den nachfolgenden Angeboten schien jedoch verbesserungswürdig.&#13;
&#13;
Schlussfolgerungen: Das Hebammennetzwerk ermöglichte sozial benachteiligten Familien eine Wochenbettbetreuung und damit den Verbleib in der Versorgungskette. In den meisten Fällen unterschied sich die Häufigkeit der Besuche bei den vermittelten Frauen nicht von anderen Frauen. Abweichungen waren jedoch nach oben und unten zu beobachten. Die geringe Anwendung der Assessmentinstrumente wies auf einen Weiterbildungsbedarf der im Netzwerk tätigen Hebammen hin. Obwohl Verbesserungsbedarf an der Schnittstelle für die Weiterbetreuung festgestellt wurde, anerkannten die Stakeholder die wichtige Rolle der Hebammen in der Frühen Förderung. Daraus lässt sich ein Vorbildcharakter des Netzwerkes für andere Regionen erkennen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-01-12T13:23:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-01-12T13:23:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-26</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1055/s-0041-1739900</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1055/s-0041-1739900</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23866</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23866</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23866</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0948-2393</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1439-1651</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>30. Kongress der Deutschen Gesellschaft für Perinatale Medizin, online, 24.-27.November 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Zeitschrift für Geburtshilfe und Neonatologie</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Thieme</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12362</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T10:36:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Coffee</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Yeretzian, Chahan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Coffee Aroma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sensory Experience of Coffee</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Aroma Analysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sensory Profile</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>663: Getränketechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Coffee is a relatively young beverage that has only been known about since the 17th century. Initially consumed by the aristocracy, coffee has developed since the early 20th century into one of the world’s most popular beverages and is now part of our daily routine and lifestyle. It also represents a major source of income for many coffee-producing countries and is a significant business sector in consumer countries. The triumph of this beverage may have been driven by various factors, but there is no doubt that its unique flavor is the prime reason for its amazing success. Here we will review current knowledge on the aroma of coffee from a chemical and analytical perspective and outline future trends. It is believed that most coffee aroma compounds have already been identified and quantified. Yet little is understood about how these aroma compounds are generated from green coffee precursors during roasting. A true definition of the aroma of freshly roasted and/or brewed coffee is very elusive and some aroma compounds start to degrade the moment they form. Furthermore, research on interindividual differences in the sensation and perception of coffee aromas is still in its infancy. After reviewing our current knowledge on coffee aroma compounds, we will outline recent developments in time-resolved analysis in three fields:&#13;
&#13;
1. Aroma formation during roasting&#13;
 &#13;
2. Aroma extraction during espresso preparation and&#13;
 &#13;
3. In-mouth release during consumption.&#13;
 &#13;
Finally, we will address predictive models for sensory profiles derived from instrumental measurements – possibly the holy grail of aroma sciences.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-30T15:32:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-30T15:32:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-26932-0_6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-319-26932-0_6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12362</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12362</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12362</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-319-26930-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-319-26932-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Springer handbook of odor</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Springer Handbooks</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13565</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-04T12:57:04Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ästhetik und unternehmerischer Erfolg</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schüz, Mathias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Erfolg</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ästhetik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Unternehmen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658: Allgemeines Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-12-05T14:46:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-05T14:46:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13565</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13565</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13565</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>WirtschaftsKurier</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Verband Österreichischer Wirtschaftsakademiker</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5320</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-12-15T13:36:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ausgewählte Aspekte der maschinellen Übersetzung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jekat, Susanne Johanna</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>CAT</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>MT</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Unifikationsbasierte Grammatiken</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>410.285: Computerlinguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Vorlesung gehalten im Rahmen der "WiSe 2004/05" an der Universität Zürich, Institut für Computerlinguistik.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-16T14:20:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-16T14:20:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Vorlesung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5320</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5320</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5320</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11056</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T12:55:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die ungeplante Austrittsgestaltung aus Pflegefamilien : eine konzeptionelle Lücke in der Pflegekinderhilfe der Schweiz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bombach, Clara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gabriel, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stohler, Renate</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Werner, Karin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Abbruch</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pflegeverhältnis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.7: Jugendhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-09-26T13:28:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-26T13:28:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11056</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11056</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11056</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0947-8957</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Forum Erziehungshilfen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Beltz Juventa</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18498</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T13:57:04Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_50</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Pflegerische Interventionen zur Reduktion von Präoperativer Angst</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Albiez, Benjamin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Laube, Salome</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Preoperative anxiety</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Preoperative fear</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nursing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nursing care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nursing intervention</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Anaesthesia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Operation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Surgery</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Preoperative period</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Hintergrund: Präoperative Angst (PA) manifestiert sich bei bis zu 80 % der Patienten/-innen. Sie kann schwerwiegende Folgen haben und sich ungünstig auf den Operations-, Narkose- und Genesungsverlauf auswirken.  

Ziel: Das Identifizieren von wirksamen, pflegerischen, nichtmedikamentösen Interventionen bei Erwachsenen zur Reduktion von PA und das Ableiten von Implikationen für die klinische Praxis.  
Methode: Im November 2018 wurde eine systematisierte Literaturrecherche in den Datenbanken PubMed®, CINAHL®, PsychINFO und Cochrane Library durchgeführt. Die betrachteten Studien wurden mit dem Critical Appraisal Skills Programme sowie den Quantitative Review Form Guidelines von Law u. a., (1998) gewürdigt.  

Ergebnisse: Es wurden 15 quantitative Studien eingeschlossen, welche alle eine angstreduzierende Wirkung aufzeigen. Drei Ansätze mit zehn Subansätzen wurden identifiziert. Ein Ansatz untersucht Entspannungsinterventionen, welche Musikintervention, multimodale Intervention, Massage, Fotovideodarstellung, Entspannungsübungen und Naturklänge beinhalten. Der zweite Ansatz stellt die Informationsvermittlung anhand einer Informationsbroschüre und eines Informationsvideo dar. Im dritten Ansatz, der psychosozialen Unterstützung, wird Bezug auf eine psychosoziale Kurzzeitintervention, ein patientenzentriertes Gespräch und die Pflegevisite genommen.
Schlussfolgerung: Die eingeschlossene Literatur zeigt drei angstreduzierende Ansätze auf. Alle Interventionen können in der klinischen Praxis zur Angstreduktion angewendet werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-10-23T08:05:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-10-23T08:05:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-18498</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-18498</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18498</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18498</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18498</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>199 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9686</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-27T13:28:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Bin ich ein guter Chef?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Streuli, Elisa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Dilemma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mitarbeiterführung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Führungskraft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vorgesetzte</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kompetenz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Grundwerte</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>158: Angewandte Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Frage, was ein guter Chef oder eine gute Chefin ist, füllt ganze Bücherregale. Je höher die Position und je komplexer die Situation ist, desto wichtiger wird es, mit widersprüchlichen Anforderungen und Erwartungen konstruktiv umzugehen. Doch auch auf Teamleitungsebene stellen sich Fragen, die jede Führungsperson für sich aufgrund ihrer Ziele, vor allem aber im Einklang mit ihren grundlegenden Werten beantworten muss.&#13;
&#13;
Führungssituationen sind typischerweise durch Dilemmata und Paradoxien charakterisiert sind. Oft ist es nicht ein je mehr (oder weniger), desto besser, sondern ein sowohl-als auch, aber im richtigen Mass. Was braucht es, damit die kurz- und langfristigen Ziele der Organisation erreicht und die Mitarbeitenden individuell und als Team optimal arbeiten können? &#13;
Dabei müssen Führungskräfte oft unter grossem Druck und in Unkenntnis der weiteren Entwicklung entscheiden. In diesen Fragen zwischen sowohl-als auch, weder-noch und entweder-oder hilft es, für sich eigene, nicht verhandelbare Grundwerte festzulegen und in diesem Rahmen angepasst auf die Situation zu reagieren. Das gelingt längst nicht immer: Nobody is perfect – denn reibungslos funktionieren können Maschinen und Computer wesentlich besser! </dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-27T08:08:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-27T08:08:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013-08-26</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4357</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4357</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://www.hrtoday.ch/de/article/bin-ich-ein-guter-chef</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9686</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2235-8471</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>HR Today</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Jobindex</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23796</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-25T09:29:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Differences in epaAC© in heart failure patients with or without readmission : a retrospective case-control study</dc:title>
          <dc:title>Unterschiede im epaAC© bei Patient_innen mit Herzinsuffizienz mit oder ohne Rehospitalisation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Höhn, Eva-Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hediger, Hannele</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hermann, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Petry, Heidi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schmid-Mohler, Gabriela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Aktivitäten des täglichen Lebens</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Herzinsuffizienz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Rehospitalisation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Risikofaktor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Activities of daily living</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Heart failure</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nursing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Patient readmission</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Risk factor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616: Innere Medizin und Krankheiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Background: Heart failure is one of the most frequent reasons for hospitalization in elderly people. In heart failure, approximately 22.8 % of hospitalised patients are rehospitalised within 30 days. The nursing assessment tool epaAC could provide information on risk factors for readmission. &#13;
&#13;
Aim: The aim of this study was to identify possible group differences in the items and scores of the epaAC discharge assessment with regard to the endpoint of unplanned readmissions within 30 days after discharge from index-hospitalisation. &#13;
&#13;
Methods: Using a retrospective case-control design, differences in the epaAC variables were investigated by descriptive and comparative statistics. Chi-square test, Wilcoxon test and t-test were performed with two-sided alpha level α &lt; 0.05. Alpha error accumulation was accounted for by Benjamini &amp; Hochberg correction. &#13;
&#13;
Results: No significant group differences were found in all items and scores of the discharge epaAC. There is only weak evidence that the presence of acute respiratory impairment at time of discharge is higher in the patient with rehospitalisation than in those without rehospitalisation. &#13;
&#13;
Conclusions: The items and scores of the nursing assessment instrument epaAC did not significantly differ between patients with or without 30-days readmission. Further exploration to assess the epaAC's potential to predict rehospitalisation in heart failure is needed.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-12-20T10:28:21Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-12-20T10:28:21Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-10-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1024/1012-5302/a000847</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1024/1012-5302/a000847</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23796</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23796</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23796</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1012-5302</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1664-283X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>34708668</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Pflege</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Hogrefe</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15743</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T14:05:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Performance measurement and evaluation in the arts management: a meta-synthesis : comparing and contrasting approaches across artistic disciplines, institutional settings and regions</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Labaronne, Leticia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Performance measurement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kulturevaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kulturmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>306: Kultur</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-03-01T13:50:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-01T13:50:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15743</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15743</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15743</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>5th Workshop on «Managing Cultural Organisations» EIASM, Bologna, Italy, 15 December 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19820</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-19T13:48:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Der Kenntnisstand zu Tierschutz und Welfare in der Speisefischproduktion</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tschudi, Fridolin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stamer, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Aquakultur</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Speisefischproduktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Rechtliche Rahmenbedingung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Tierschutz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fischwohl</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schweizer Forellenproduktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>343: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Sachen-, Finanz-, Steuer- und Wirtschaftsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>630: Landwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Bedeutung der Aquakultur nimmt in den letzten Jahren stetig zu. Mit einer durchschnittlichen, weltweiten Wachstumsrate von 6-8 % pro Jahr ist die Aquakultur der zur Zeit am schnellsten wachsende Sektor tierischer Nahrungsprodukte (CIWF 2009). Durch die massive Überfischung der Weltmeere und das dadurch sinkende Angebot an hochwertigem Wildfang (Worm et al. 2006) kann zudem mit einem weiteren Wachstum der Aquakultur gerechnet werden. &#13;
Aquakulturbetriebe erhalten somit einen immer wichtigeren wirtschaftlichen Stellenwert und gelangen stärker in den Fokus der Öffentlichkeit. Weltweit, speziell auch in der Schweiz, entstanden in den letzten Jahren neue Betriebe mit neuen Betriebsformen. Technisch anspruchsvolle Kreislaufanlagen unterscheiden sich dabei in ihrer Ausführung untereinander und gegenüber von konventionellen Fliesskanälen stark. Eine Anpassung der rechtlichen Rahmenbedingungen ist deshalb nötig. Dies setzt jedoch voraus, dass die aktuelle Gesetzeslage dem Stand der Forschung entspricht und einfache Tierschutz-Kontrollmechanismen bestehen, die von den Behörden bzw. dem Fischwirt angewandt werden können. &#13;
In den letzten Jahren hat sich aufgrund der wachsenden Aquakultur auch die Forschung in diesem Gebiet intensiviert. Dabei wurde ein starker Fokus auf Tierschutz und das Wohlbefinden von Fischen (Fischwohl) in Aquakulturbetrieben gesetzt. Das Ziel dieser Arbeit ist es, den aktuellen Stand dieser Forschung mit Fokus auf die Schweizer Forellenproduktion darzulegen und möglichen Forschungsbedarf aufzuzeigen. Dafür werden zuerst die gängige Praxis der Forellenmast und Forellenzucht und deren gesetzliche Rahmenbedingungen kurz umrissen. Es folgen die gängigen, unterschiedlichen Definitionen von Fischwohl und deren wissenschaftlichen Grundlagen. Anschliessend werden mögliche Parameter vorgestellt, welche einen negativen Effekt auf das Fischwohl haben können, und deren Abweichungen zum Schweizer Recht dargelegt. Da es zur Kontrolle unumgänglich ist, das Fischwohl einfach und schnell bewerten zu können, werden mögliche Indikatoren für Fischwohl diskutiert und deren Relevanz für die zukünftige Forschung erläutert. Inwieweit es gerechtfertigt ist, wirtschaftliche und ernährungstechnische Interessen mittels Gesetzen zum Tierschutz einzuschränken, ist nicht Teil dieser Studie und muss separat diskutiert werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-03-19T13:48:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-03-19T13:48:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012-11-27</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://orgprints.org/21717/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19820</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>66 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>FiBL Forschungsinstitut für biologischen Landbau</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4393</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-16T07:27:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Modal vector fitting : a tool for generating rational models of high accuracy with arbitrary terminal conditions</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gustavsen, Bjørn</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Heitz, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Signal processing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>338: Produktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>This paper introduces a new approach for rational macromodeling of multiport devices that ensures high accuracy with arbitrary terminal conditions. This is achieved by reformulating the vector fitting (VF) technique to focus on eigenpairs rather than matrix elements. By choosing the least squares (LS) weighting equal to the inverse of the eigenvalue magnitude, the modal components are fitted with a relative accuracy criterion. The resulting modal vector fitting (MVF) method is shown to give a major improvement in accuracy for cases with a high ratio between the largest and smallest eigenvalue, although it is computationally more costly than VF. It is also shown how to utilize the impedance characteristics of the adjacent network in the fitting process. The application of MVF is demonstrated for a two-conductor stripline, a coaxial cable, and a transformer measurement. We also show a simplified procedure which achieves similar results as MVF if the admittance matrix can be diagonalized by a constant transformation matrix. The extracted model is finally subjected to passivity enforcement by the modal perturbation method, which makes use of a similar LS formulation as MVF for the constrained optimization problem.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T09:56:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T09:56:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1897</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1109/TADVP.2008.927810</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1897</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1109/TADVP.2008.927810</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4393</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4393</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4393</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2156-3950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>IEEE Transactions on Components, Packaging and Manufacturing Technology</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>IEEE</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19936</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T11:00:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Robotic Process Automation : das nächste Level der intelligenten Maschine</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Liebhart, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Robotic Process Automation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>006: Spezielle Computerverfahren</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die IT als Unterstützungsfunktion für die geschäftliche Tätigkeit eines Unternehmens ist um eine Technologie reicher. 2018 war das Jahr des Durchbruchs von Robotic Process Automation (RPA). Der Roboter ist die «virtualisierte Vollzeitarbeitskraft» von morgen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-04-20T07:52:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-04-20T07:52:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-19936</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-19936</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19936</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19936</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19936</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-2397</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Netzwoche</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Netzmedien</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22631</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-06-11T13:08:45Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Biocatalysis and biosynthesis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Buller, Rebecca</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>660.6: Biotechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The terms biocatalysis and biosynthesis refer to the use of enzymes (natural catalysts) or microorganisms to sustainably manufacture products in addition to classic chemical synthesis: biodegradable biocatalysts can be tailored by means of directed enzyme evolution for many areas of application that are still a challenge for traditional chemistry. Biocatalysis or biosynthesis are already being used in many industries, for example in the production of fine chemicals, in the flavour and fragrance industry or in the production of active agents. Much hope is placed on biocatalysis and biosynthesis for the utilisation of renewable resources as they foster a greater independence from fossil energy sources.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-06-11T13:08:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-06-11T13:08:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.satw.ch/en/technology-outlook-2021</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22631</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Technology Outlook 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Swiss Academy of Engineering Sciences SATW</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1637</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-24T14:12:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Residual stress and buckling patterns of free-standing yttria-stabilized-zirconia membranes fabricated by pulsed laser deposition</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Evans, Anna</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Prestat, Michel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tölke, R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schlupp, M. V. F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gauckler, L. J.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Safa, Yasser</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hocker, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Courbat, J.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Briand, D.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>de Rooij, N. F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Courty, D.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Pulsed Laser Deposition</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Buckling</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Micro-solid Oxide Fuel Cell</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Free-standing Membrane</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>530: Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The residual stress and buckling patterns of free-standing 8 mol.% yttria-stabilized-zirconia (8YSZ) membranes prepared by pulsed laser deposition and microfabrication techniques on silicon substrates are investigated by wafer curvature, light microscopy, white light interferometry, and nanoindentation. The 300 nm thin 8YSZ membranes (390 × 390 Micron) deposited at 25°C are almost flat after free-etching, whereas deposition at 700°C yields strongly buckled membranes with a compressive stress of -1,100 ± 150 MPa and an out-of-plane-displacement of 6.5 lm. These latter membranes are mechanically stable during thermal cycling up to 500°C. Numerical simulations of the buckling shape using the Rayleigh-Ritz-method and a Young’s modulus of 200 GPa are in good agreement with the experimental data. The simulated buckling patterns are used to extract the local stress distribution within the freestanding membrane which consists of tensile and compressive stress regions that are below the failure stresses. This is important regarding the application in, e.g., microsolid oxide fuel cell membranes which must be thermomechanically stable during microfabrication and device operation.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2017-11-30T15:07:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-11-30T15:07:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012-06-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1002/fuce.201200028</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1002/fuce.201200028</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1637</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1637</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1637</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1615-6846</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1615-6854</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Fuel Cells</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Wiley</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14256</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-26T10:36:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Effects of exercise and physical activity promotion : meta-analysis informing the 2018 EULAR recommendations for physical activity in people with rheumatoid arthritis, spondyloarthritis and hip/knee osteoarthritis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rausch Osthoff, Anne-Kathrin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Juhl, Carsten Bogh</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Knittle, Keegan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dagfinrud, Hanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hurkmans, Emalie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Braun, Juergen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schoones, Jan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vliet Vlieland, Theodora P. M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Niedermann, Karin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Rheumatoid Arthritis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Spondyloarthritis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Osteoarthritis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Physical activity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616.7: Krankheiten des Bewegungsapparates und Orthopädie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Objective: To evaluate the effectiveness of exercise and physical activity (PA) promotion on cardiovascular fitness, muscle strength, flexibility, neuromotor performance (eg, balance) and daily PA in people with rheumatoid arthritis (RA), spondyloarthritis (SpA) and hip/knee osteoarthritis (HOA/KOA).&#13;
&#13;
Methods: systematic review (SR) and meta-analysis (MA) were performed searching the databases PubMed/Medline, CENTRAL, Embase, Web of Science, Emcare and PsycInfo until April 2017. We included randomised controlled trials (RCTs) in adults (≥18 years) with RA, SpA and HOA/KOA, investigating the effects of exercise or PA promotion according to the public health PA recommendations by the American College of Sports Medicine. The time point of interest was the first assessment after the intervention period. If suitable, data were pooled in a MA using a random-effects model presented as standardised mean difference (SMD).&#13;
&#13;
Results: The SR included 63 RCTs, of which 49 (3909 people with RA/SpA/HOA/KOA) were included in the MA. Moderate effects were found of aerobic exercises and resistance training on cardiovascular fitness (SMD 0.56 (95% CI 0.38 to 0.75)) and muscle strength (SMD 0.54 (95% CI 0.35 to 0.72)), respectively, but no effect of combined strength/aerobic/flexibility exercises on flexibility (SMD 0.12 (95% CI -0.16 to 0.41)). PA promotion interventions produced a small increase in PA behaviour (SMD 0.21 (95% CI 0.03 to 0.38)).&#13;
&#13;
Conclusion: Exercises and PA promotion according to public health recommendations for PA improved cardiovascular fitness, muscle strength and PA behaviour, with moderate effect sizes in people with SpA, RA and HOA/KOA.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-01-09T12:47:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-09T12:47:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4962</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1136/rmdopen-2018-000713</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4962</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1136/rmdopen-2018-000713</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14256</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14256</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14256</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2056-5933</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>RMD Open</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>BMJ Publishing Group</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2278</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-19T04:00:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Treated versus non-treated subjects with depression from a 30-year cohort study : prevalence and clinical covariates</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hengartner, Michael Pascal</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Angst, Felix</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ajdacic-Gross, Vladeta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rössler, Wulf</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Angst, Jules</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Depression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Treatment seeking</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Prevalence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Distress</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gender</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616.8: Neurologie und Krankheiten des Nervensystems</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenzen.ch)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>The aim of this study was to determine prevalence rates of several components of depression (unipolar and bipolar major, minor, recurrent brief depression, and dysthymia) and to identify covariates of treatment. We analysed a representative population-based, long-term prospective cohort study from age 20 to 50. Across the seven semi-structured interviews, generalized estimating equations examined the associations between diagnoses and treatment status during the course. The results show that the mean annual treatment rate across 30 years in persons with MDE was 39.2%. The weighted treatment prevalence for any depressive disorder was 23.4% (15.7% for MDE, 4.3% for minor depressive disorders and 3.4% for non-diagnosed subjects). Persons were more likely to seek treatment as they grew older. Women with MDE had triple the treatment prevalence of men (23.8 vs. 7.4%). Variables of distress/suffering under depression (OR 1.36-1.52) and the number of diagnostic depressive symptoms (OR 1.47) were statistically significant predictors of treatment, as were episode duration (OR 2.21) and various variables assessing impairment due to depression (OR 4.65-8.02). In conclusion, only a minority of persons with depressive disorders seek professional treatment in the year of disorder onset. Women and subjects suffering from high levels of depressive symptoms, frequent episodes, long episode duration and consecutive high distress and impairment were more likely to seek treatment.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-01-30T13:33:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-30T13:33:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-03</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00406-015-0646-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2278</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/s00406-015-0646-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2278</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2278</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2278</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2278</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0940-1334</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1433-8491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>European Archives of Psychiatry and Clinical Neuroscience</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1309</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T13:56:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_51</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Der Berufseinstieg von Jugendlichen mit Schizophrenie in der Schweiz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kunert, Aline</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zenger, Muriel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>IPS Modell</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Jugendlicher</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schizophrenie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Berufseinstieg</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Erster Arbeitsmarkt</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615.8515: Ergotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Darstellung der Problematik: Bei Jugendlichen mit Schizophrenie ist der Einstieg ins Berufsleben durch Aspekte der Krankheit sowie gesellschaftliche Strukturen erschwert. Die Literatur deutet darauf hin, dass es in der Schweiz kein standardisierte Vorgehen zur Arbeitsrehabilitation schizophrener Jugendlicher gibt, welches dem Stand der Forschung entsprechen würde. Die Forschung besagt für Erwachsene mit Schizophrenie, dass das Individual Placement and Support Model (IPS) gute Ergebnisse erzielt.

Fragestellung: Kann das IPS Modell bei jungen Erwachsenen angewendet werden, die während der Lebensphase des Berufseinstiegs an Schizophrenie erkranken und welche besonderen Aspekte im Vergleich zur Behandlung von Erwachsenen sind zu beachten?
Methode: Eine Literaturrecherche wird vorgenommen und anhand von Ein- und Ausschlusskriterien werden vier Hauptstudien zur Beantwortung der Fragestellung festgelegt.

Relevante Ergebnisse: Zur Arbeitsrehabilitation von Jugendlichen Patienten mit Schizophrenie eignet sich ein angepasstes IPS Modell. Die Anpassungen ergeben sich aus weiteren Aspekten wie der Ausbildung, der finanziellen Situation der Jugendlichen, der Bedeutung der Familie sowie dem Mangel an Arbeitserfahrung.

Schlussfolgerung: Um den Berufseinstieg bei schizophrenen Jugendlichen in der Schweiz optimal zu unterstützen müsste das aktuelle Vorgehen entsprechend der Forschung angepasst werden. Insbesondere müsste der angepasste IPS Ansatz flächendeckend angewendet werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2017-07-27T08:36:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-07-27T08:36:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1308</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1308</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1309</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1309</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1309</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>75 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5358</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-14T15:29:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Innovative Fernerkundungslösungen im Umweltmonitoring</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ochsner, Pascal</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Geilhausen, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Laube, Patrick</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Döring, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rupf, Reto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Geoinformatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333.7: Landflächen, Naturerholungsgebiete</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>363: Umwelt- und Sicherheitsprobleme</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Umweltmonitoring hat die Erfassung sich verändernder Umweltbedingungen auf allen Raum- und Zeitskalen zum Ziel. Im Rahmen einer übergreifenden Zusammenarbeit von zwei Forschungsgruppen wird derzeit der Einsatz kostengünstiger Fernerkundungsdrohnen zum Monitoring ökologisch wertvoller Auengebiete erprobt. Die Auswertung von Luftbildern unterschiedlicher Zeitpunkte gewährt wertvolle Einblicke in die raumzeitliche Dynamik der ökologischen Prozesse.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-18T14:47:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-18T14:47:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-5358</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-5358</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://www.eqcharta.ch/index_htm_files/Transfer-1-2015-v7-IUNR.PDF</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5358</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Transfer</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19239</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-29T10:11:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Institutionenkonzepte und Familialität - Inwieweit beziehen sich im Schweizer Kontext SPF(H) Institutionen und Fachpersonen auf Angebote Früher Förderung/Hilfen?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Eberitzsch, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>371: Schulen und schulische Tätigkeiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-01-29T10:11:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-01-29T10:11:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19239</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19239</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19239</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Jahrestagung der DGFE-Sektion Sozialpädagogik und Pädagogik der frühen Kindheit, Lüneburg, Deutschland, 24. Mai 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11733</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-12-18T09:40:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Studierende als Brückenbauer zwischen Kulturen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Prandini, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Brückenbauer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kultur</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Competence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>303: Soziale Prozesse</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die gestiegenen Anforderungen einer internationalisierten Wirtschaftswelt haben Konsequenzen für die Ausbildung an Hochschulen. Mit Lernmethoden, die interkulturelle Kompetenzen fördern, können Studierende zu Brückenbauern zwischen den Kulturen ausgebildet werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-12T08:10:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-12T08:10:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11733</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11733</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.zhaw.ch/storage/sml/ueber-uns/zhaw-broschuere-competence-nr1.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11733</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2297-6140</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Competence</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16914</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T10:17:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Intensive home-based care : a look inside</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Knot-Dickscheit, Jana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tausendfreund, Tim</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-04-27T09:25:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-27T09:25:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16914</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16914</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16914</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:9789044126976</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Insideout: how interventions in child and family care work : an international source book</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>EUSARF XI, Groningen, Netherlands, 22-25 September 2010</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>KOP-serie</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Garant</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22308</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-04-22T08:50:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kommentar zu Art. 54 OR</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fischer, Willi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-04-22T08:50:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-04-22T08:50:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22308</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22308</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22308</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-03751-685-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Haftpflichtkommentar : Kommentar zu den schweizerischen Haftpflichtbestimmungen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Dike</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8915</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-24T10:54:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Mit Biss und Bravour : Lebenswege von Topmanagerinnen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Streuli, Elisa</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-08-08T11:20:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-08T11:20:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8915</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8915</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8915</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-280-05195-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>203 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Orell Füssli</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21237</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-28T08:22:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wohnen an Hauptverkehrsstrassen : Lebensqualität und Bewältigungsstrategien</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kaschlik, Anke</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Bewältigung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lebensqualität an Hauptstrassen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>307: Gemeinschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Wohnen trotz(t) Lärm? Lebensqualität und Bewältigungsstrategien Betroffener in lärmbelasteten Wohnlagen&#13;
Auswirkungen auf die Gesundheit durch Lärmbelastungen, (technische) Möglichkeiten der Lärmreduktion und auch Einschätzungen von Expert*innen über das Wohnen in lärmbelasteten Wohnlagen sind bekannt. Weniger bekannt sind die Einschätzungen und Bewältigungsstrategien der Betroffenen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-01-11T09:36:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-01-11T09:36:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21237</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21237</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21237</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Dortmunder Konferenz 2020 : Book of Abstracts</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>5. Dortmunder Konferenz „Räume neu denken - Planung in einer Welt im Wandel“, Dortmund, 17.-18. Februar 2020</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19775</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-04-06T09:42:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Social work education as a contribution to promote the development of professional identity</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Girschik, Katja</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wright, Anthony</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>361: Sozialarbeit und Sozialhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>378: Hochschulbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-03-19T07:23:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-03-19T07:23:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-06-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19775</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19775</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19775</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>EASSW Conference 2019 : Meanings of Quality of Social Work Education in a changing Europe, Madrid, Spain, 4-7 June 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14750</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-12T10:29:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Schreibförderdiagnostik in der beruflichen Bildung – zwischen angewandter Linguistik und Schreibdidaktik</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Liste Lamas, Elsa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Opacic, Aleksandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Konstantinidou, Triantafyllia Liana</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-01-29T15:50:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-29T15:50:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14750</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14750</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14750</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Schreibenplus 2019: Schreiben und Übergänge an der PH Zürich, Zürich, 24. Januar 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10042</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:53:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Digital Learning : Lernen in der Datenwolke</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Di Giusto, Flavio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Scherler, Patrik</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-08-30T10:56:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-30T10:56:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1377</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1377</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10042</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10042</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10042</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>KMU Business World</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Swisscom</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3802</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-01-29T07:27:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1075</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1074</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1076</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Glatt : Projekte für eine Stadt im Werden</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kurath, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Primas, Urs</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pfenninger, Reto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schregenberger, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Städtebau</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Krokodil</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Masterstudio</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>711: Raumplanung (Städtebau)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-14T13:23:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-14T13:23:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3802</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3802</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3802</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:987-3-906027-21-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>288 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Park Books</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15881</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T14:05:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Nutzer als Designer : Usability-Testing inkl. Eyetracking im Innovationsprozess der Firma BERNINA International AG</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Badras, Catherine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lohse, Kathrin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Laubner, Ulrike</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Eyetracking</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Technikkommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Produktinnovation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Usability-Testing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>620: Ingenieurwesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-03-07T14:40:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-07T14:40:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15881</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15881</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15881</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-18-302922-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Der Mensch im Mittelpunkt technischer Systeme</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>8. Berliner Werkstatt Mensch-Maschine-Systeme, Berlin, Deutschland, 7.-9. Oktober 2009</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Berichte aus dem Zentrum Mensch-Maschine-Systeme der Technischen Universität Berlin</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>VDI-Verlag</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5630</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-23T06:40:42Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Blasen-Agenda : Miktionstagebuch</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Köhler, Barbara</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>616: Innere Medizin und Krankheiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Harnverlust, Ausscheidungsmenge, Einlagenwechsel, Harndrang und Trinkmenge dokumentiert ein Patient in seinem Miktionstagebuch. So lassen sich Verhaltensänderungen besprechen, die Therapie planen und der Therapieerfolg beurteilen – ein Muss für einen professionellen Auftritt gegenüber Arzt und Patient.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-27T09:54:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-27T09:54:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5630</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5630</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5630</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1439-023X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1869-5515</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>physiopraxis</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Thieme</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13698</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T10:17:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Hebammenarbeit in der Situation des Schwangerschaftsabbruchs im zweiten und dritten Trimenon : eine Grounded-Theory-Studie mit Hebammen eines Schweizer Universitätsspitals</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hasenberg, Gabriele</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Workshopbeitrag</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-12-08T10:43:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-08T10:43:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013-05-03</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13698</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13698</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13698</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Forschungsworkshop der Hebammengemeinschaftshilfe e.V., Nürnberg, Deutschland, 5. Mai 2013</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18346</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T12:15:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The financial structure of international cartels : leverage, cash holdings and corporate governance</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Günster, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>van Dijk, Mathijs</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>338: Produktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-10-04T13:51:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-10-04T13:51:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18346</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18346</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18346</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>11th Annual International Industrial Organization Conference, Boston, USA, 17-19 May 2013</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4450</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-16T07:27:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Parity violating effects in the molecular anion CBrClF(-)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stohner, Jürgen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Parity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Violation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Carbanion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Molecular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>540: Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>We examine the influence of molecular parity violation on relative vibrational frequency shifts in the carbanion CBrClF−. The parity violating potential has been calculated following the method of Berger and Quack [J. Chem. Phys. 112 (2000) 3148] using a multi-configurational linear response approach. The vibrational frequency shifts have been determined in the separable harmonic (SHAA) and anharmonic (SAAA) adiabatic approximation. We find that CBrClF− shows larger (in absolute magnitude) relative frequency shifts compared to the neutral CHBrClF. The relative frequency shifts depend strongly on the vibrational wavefunction used to determine the expectation value of the parity violating potential. We determined also the energetic stability of CBrClF− with respect to electron detachment, Br− and Cl− abstraction and protonation to form CHBrClF.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T15:05:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T15:05:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2004-04-15</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijms.2004.01.015</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.ijms.2004.01.015</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4450</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4450</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4450</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1387-3806</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1873-2798</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>International Journal of Mass Spectrometry</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23072</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-04T03:01:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Transformative pathways : using integrated assessment models more effectively to open up plausible and desirable low-carbon futures</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Braunreiter, Lukas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>van Beek, Lisette</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hajer, Maarten</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>van Vuuren, Detlef</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Integrated assessment modelling</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Scenario</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Transformation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Low-carbon future</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Science-policy interface</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Stakeholder engagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>363: Umwelt- und Sicherheitsprobleme</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Integrated assessment models (IAM) and resulting scenarios have become increasingly institutionalised and relevant in the science-policy interface of climate policy. Despite their analytical strengths to conceive low-carbon futures, their co-evolution with the transnational science-policy interface of climate politics has also led to a focus on a specific set of techno-economic futures that are typically based on a relatively narrow set of assumptions. This deviates attention from alternatives that are hardly studied by IAMs, but might be more desirable from a societal perspective. We argue that research-based models and scenarios should support rather than narrow down deliberations on possible and desirable futures and provide an impetus to enact socially desirable change. Accordingly, we propose three future directions regarding the development and use of IAMs: 1) incorporate a plurality of perspectives on plausibility and desirability through iterative participatory engagement and worldview-based scenario exploration, 2) seek collaboration with the arts and humanities to expand the range of imagined futures beyond the status quo and 3) make projected futures more tangible and experiential so that diverse societal actor groups can understand and genuinely engage with them. By deploying the indisputable analytical strengths of IAMs optimally within these suggestions, we believe they can facilitate broader societal debates about transformative pathways to low-carbon futures.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-09-03T14:06:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-09-03T14:06:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.erss.2021.102220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23072</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.erss.2021.102220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23072</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23072</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23072</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23072</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2214-6296</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2214-6326</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Energy Research &amp; Social Science</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18317</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T13:56:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_16708</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Situationsanalyse zur Schaffung rauchfreier Spielplätze im Kanton Basel-Landschaft : eine themengeleitete Arbeit</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rüegg, Lisa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Passivrauchen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Rauchfrei</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Spielplatz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kinder</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gemeinden</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kanton Basel-Landschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610: Medizin und Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Einleitung: Von 8.5 Millionen Einwohner (BFS, 2017) in der Schweiz rauchen mehr als eineinhalb Millionen, und noch mehr rauchen passiv mit (Sucht Schweiz, 2015). Kinder gelten als besonders vulnerable Gruppe, da ihr Körper noch nicht ausgereift ist und deshalb die Giftstoffe schlechter abbauen (BZgA, 2015). Durch rauchfreie Spielplätze kann die Gesundheit der Kinder erhalten oder gefördert werden.

Ziel: Die kantonale Gesundheitsförderung möchte im gesamten Kanton Basel-Landschaft rauchfreie Spielplätze umsetzen. Dafür wird der Ist-Zustand analysiert und mittels eines partizipativen Ansatzes erste Argumente für Gemeinden ausgearbeitet. 
Methode: Zur Datenerhebung dient eine deskriptive Situationsanalyse mittels Bewertungsraster. Zudem findet eine partizipative Arbeitsmethode nach dem Vorbild der Structured Interview Matrix statt.

Ergebnisse: Im Kanton Basel-Landschaft herrscht nur in zwei von neun betrachteten Gemeinden ein Rauchverbot auf allen öffentlichen Spielplätzen. In der partizipativen Arbeitsmethode wünschen sich die Beteiligten für die Umsetzung von rauchfreien Spielplätzen eine positive Vision. Für die Umsetzung von rauchfreien Spielplätzen im Kanton BL werden mögliche Massnahmen und Stakeholder definiert. 
Schlussfolgerung: Die Arbeit nützt der Auftraggeberin als Grundlage für weitere Gespräche und Verhandlungen und soll als Auftakt für die Lancierung des Projekts dienen. Ein Ansatz auf mehreren Ebenen scheint dabei am vielversprechendsten zu sein.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-09-28T11:54:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-09-28T11:54:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-18317</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-18317</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18317</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18317</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18317</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>96 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23608</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-25T09:26:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Willingness to share data : contextual determinants of consumers' decisions to share private data with companies</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ackermann, Kurt Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Burkhalter, Linda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mildenberger, Thoralf</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Frey, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bearth, Angela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Consumer behaviour</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Willingness to share data</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Experiment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658: Allgemeines Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In the age of digitalization, customer and consumer data have become a valuable source of information for companies. However, to obtain these data, companies depend on peoples' willingness to share (WTS) their private data with them. By means of a large-scale online experiment with more than 20,000 participants, we investigated the extent to which peoples' WTS private data is affected by contextual factors. We complement and extend previous research by (i) simultaneously addressing several contextual factors that companies can largely control themselves, (ii) comparing their relative impacts on WTS, and (iii) explicitly examining interactions between these contextual factors in addition to their specific univariate effects. Concretely, we investigate contextual factors, such as the type of data requested, the purpose for which the data are used, the industry sector a corresponding company belongs to, the type of compensation offered for the shared data, and the degree to which the data allows for personal identification. Our data suggest that all these factors do affect peoples' WTS significantly, while there are also multiple significant interaction effects between these contextual factors. For instance, we found that a better intuitive match between the core business a company is engaged in and the type of data that is requested results in higher proportions of people who are willing to share the corresponding data with the corresponding company. Hence, companies may benefit from tuning their requests for consumer or customer data according to the specific context in which they operate.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-11-29T14:30:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-29T14:30:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1002/cb.2012</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23608</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1002/cb.2012</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23608</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23608</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23608</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23608</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1472-0817</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1479-1838</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of Consumer Behaviour</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Wiley</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17334</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-19T12:53:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Macht des Computerspielers : strukturelle Kopplung als Determinante spielbezogener Wirkungsprozesse</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lippuner, Florian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Gaming</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Computerspiel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Prävention</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Digitales Spiel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Biografie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>700: Künste und Unterhaltung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-06-19T13:50:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-06-19T13:50:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-5545</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-5545</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17334</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17334</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17334</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Digitale Spiele im Diskurs</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Medien im Diskurs</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>FernUniversität in Hagen</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16612</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-04-15T10:46:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Der Marktprozeß an Aktienbörsen : Bewertungseffizienz und Umverteilung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bienert, Horst</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Aktienkurs</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Aktienmarkt</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Anlagestrategie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bewertung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Aktie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Börse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kapitalmarkt</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kapitalmarkttheorie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Liquidität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wertpapier</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332.6: Investition</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-04-15T10:46:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-15T10:46:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1996</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-322-86634-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-322-86634-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16612</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16612</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16612</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-409-13288-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-322-86634-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>NBF Neue Betriebswirtschaftliche Forschung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>350 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Gabler</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17507</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-24T13:26:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The predisposing and precipitating risk factors for delirium in neurosurgery : a prospective cohort study of 949 patients</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zipser, Carl Moritz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Deuel, Jeremy</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ernst, Jutta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schubert, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>von Känel, Roland</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Böttger, Sönke</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Delirium</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Impact</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Interaction</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Neurosurgery</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Precipitating factor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Predisposing factor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Risk factor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>617: Chirurgie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Background: Delirium is the most common neuropsychiatric presentation during hospitalization. In neurosurgery, studies on predisposing and precipitating risk factors for the development of delirium are rare but required for the individual risk estimation.

Methods: Prospective cohort study in a tertiary university center. In total, 949 neurosurgical patients, 307 with and 642 without delirium, were included. Demographic factors, neurosurgery-related, neurological, and medical clusters were tested as predictors of delirium in multiple logistic regression analyses.

Results: The incidence of delirium in this cohort of neurosurgical patients was 32.4%. Compared to patients without delirium, those with delirium were significantly older, more cognitively and neurologically impaired, transferred from hospitals and nursing homes, admitted as emergencies, longer hospitalized (16.2 vs. 9.5 days; p &lt; 0.001), in greater need of intensive care management, and more frequently transferred to rehabilitation. Predisposing factors of delirium were stroke (OR 5.45, CI 2.12–14.0, p &lt; 0.001), cardiac insufficiency (OR 4.59, CI 1.09–19.26, p = 0.038), cerebral neoplasm (OR 1.53, CI 0.92–2.54, p = 0.019), and age ≥ 65 years (OR 1.47, CI 1.03–2.09, p = 0.030). Precipitating factors of delirium were acute cerebral injury (OR 3.91, CI 2.24–6.83, p &lt; 0.001), hydrocephalus (OR 3.10, CI 1.98–4.87, p &lt; 0.001), and intracranial hemorrhage (OR 1.90, CI 1.23–2.94, p = 0.004).

Conclusions: Delirium in acute neurosurgical patients was associated with longer hospitalization. Whereas common etiologies of delirium like infections and dementia, did not predict delirium, preexisting neurovascular and traumatic diseases, as well as surgery-related events seem important risk factors contributing to delirium in neurosurgery.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-07-17T09:07:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-07-17T09:07:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00701-019-03927-z</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/s00701-019-03927-z</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17507</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17507</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17507</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0001-6268</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0942-0940</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>31106393</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Acta Neurochirurgica</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5218</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-13T10:12:39Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>BICAR : neue Dimensionen urbaner Mobilität für die Stadt Winterthur</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dennig, Hans-Jörg</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Urban Mobility</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>BICAR</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>620: Ingenieurwesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T09:08:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T09:08:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5218</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5218</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5218</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Verein Energie bewegt Winterthur, 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24512</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-10T10:45:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Gesundheitskompetenz : eine wenig bekannte und unterschätzte Grösse?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wirth, Brigitte</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>613: Persönliche Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2022-03-10T10:45:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-03-10T10:45:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-10-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://blog.zhaw.ch/gesundheitsoekonomie/2021/10/14/gesundheitskompetenz-eine-wenig-bekannte-und-unterschaetzte-groesse/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24512</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Gesundheitsökonomie @ ZHAW</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7083</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-05-31T13:12:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Data Science für Lehre, Forschung und Praxis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stockinger, Kurt</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stadelmann, Thilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Datenmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Data Warehousing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Datenanalyse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenzen.ch)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Data Science ist in aller Munde. Nicht nur wird an Konferenzen zu Big Data, Cloud Computing oder Data Warehousing darüber gesprochen: Glaubt man dem McKinsey Global Institute, so wird es alleine in den USA in den nächsten Jahren eine Lücke von bis zu 190.000 Data Scientists geben. In diesem Kapitel beleuchten wir daher zunächst die Hintergründe des Begriffs Data Science. Dann präsentieren wir typische Anwendungsfälle und Lösungsstrategien auch aus dem Big Data Umfeld. Schließlich zeigen wir am Beispiel des Diploma of Advanced Studies in Data Science der ZHAW Möglichkeiten auf, selber aktiv zu werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-19T12:23:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-19T12:23:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3759</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1365/s40702-014-0040-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3759</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1365/s40702-014-0040-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7083</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7083</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7083</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1436-3011</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2198-2775</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>HMD Praxis der Wirtschaftsinformatik</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9444</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-08-23T06:21:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Der Dialog als Haltung und Methode : Literaturarbeit zu dialogischen Prinzipien aus der Perspektive der pädagogischen und psychologischen Tradition</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Steiner, Isabelle</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jossi, Martial</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-08-23T06:21:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-23T06:21:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Weiteres (textuelles Material)</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9444</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9444</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9444</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>50 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/487</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:43:13Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_52</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Effektivität der postoperativen Frühmobilisation nach Bankart-Läsion</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lenz, Daniela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nussbaumer, Sonja</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:05:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:05:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-487</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-487</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/487</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/487</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/487</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7152</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T11:20:42Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Proprietär oder doch lieber Standard? : eine Übersicht über verschiedene Embedded-Wireless-Technologien – Beitrag 3/6</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Meli, Marcel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gutzwiller, Pius</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Proprietär</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Batterielos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Drahtlos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Piezo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Drahtlose Systeme, die weder kompatibel mit Produkten anderer Hersteller noch nach einem anerkannten Standard entwickelt sind, bezeichnet man als proprietär. Um spezifische Vorteile hervorzuheben, verändert man eine oder mehrere Schichten des Kommunikations-Stacks. Dieser Artikel beleuchtet die Vor- und Nachteile proprietärer Funksysteme und stellt eine Anwendung vor.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-21T09:02:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-21T09:02:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014-06-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.polyscope.ch/archiv/2014/11/proprietaer-oder-doch-lieber-standard/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7152</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0032-4035</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0254-2234</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Polyscope</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Swiss Professional Media</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13123</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T12:31:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>SCA water quality workshop</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wellinger, Marco</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Yeretzian, Chahan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>663: Getränketechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-11-22T14:26:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-22T14:26:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13123</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13123</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13123</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Specialty Coffee Expo 2018, Seattle, USA, 19-22 April 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14221</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-18T08:35:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Fallstudie St. Galler Kantonalbank : Kapazitätsmanagement im Service Center</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Barattiero, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schlatter, Ueli</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.5: Produktionssteuerung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Optimierung der Auslastung durch Kapazitätsmanagement ist eine wesentliches Element der Operational Excellence und Kernkompetenz der Finanzverarbeitung bei der St. Galler Kantonalbank. Die vorliegende Fallstudie zeigt eindrücklich, wie die St. Galler Kantonalbank den «Prozessintelligenz-Loop» von der Schaffung der analytischen Voraussetzungen über die Steuerung der Prozessausführung hin zur kontinuierlichen Verbesserung schliesst und permanent weiterentwickelt. Auf dieser Reise wurden Belastungsspitzen entschärft, mehr Eigenverantwortung für die Mitarbeitenden gewonnen und eine höhere Zufriedenheit der Mitarbeitenden erreicht.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-01-07T15:23:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-07T15:23:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3427</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-662-55705-1_4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3427</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-662-55705-1_4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14221</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14221</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14221</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-662-55704-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-662-55705-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Prozessintelligenz</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/403</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:43:13Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_52</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Primär glenohumerale adhäsive Kapsulitis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lauber, Anastasia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Peverelli, Sandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:04:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:04:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-403</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-403</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/403</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/403</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/403</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14434</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-02T07:58:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Auslagerung der Aufgabenerfüllung im Kanton Luzern : interdisziplinäre Grundlagenstudie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lienhard, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Steiner, Reto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ladner, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wichtermann, Jürg</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Balsiger Betts, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Buchser, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Verwaltung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Outsourcing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>350: Öffentliche Verwaltung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-01-16T14:39:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-16T14:39:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14434</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14434</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14434</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3-906798-00-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>KPM-Schriftenreihe</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>150 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>KPM</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17443</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-12T10:28:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Small scale bioprocess optimization using soft sensors</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Maschke, Rüdiger</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>John, Gernot T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pretzner, Barbara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eibl, Dieter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>660.6: Biotechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The development and optimization of cell and microbial cultures is usually done in small scale vessel like shake flasks. However, these vessels lack the sensors and hence information provided by larger bioreactors like biomass concentration, oxygen saturation and pH-values. The proposed presentation will show approaches to overcome these hurdles for mammalian (CHO), animal (e.g. insect cells Sf9) and plant cell cultures as well as microbial fermentations. The first part covers measurement improvements for shake flasks with focus on back-scattered light for biomass growth monitoring and the utilization of sensor spots for a deeper insight into the “black box” shake flasks. In the second part, soft sensors based on engineering and biological characterizations of these vessels are introduced and explained, enabling researchers to predict process values and estimate growth curves. The last part consists of the application of mechanistic and kinetic models for an improved process understanding and an enhanced culture growth prediction</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-07-04T14:20:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-07-04T14:20:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://lifesciences.knect365.com/bpieurope/agenda/3#cell-culture-and-upstream-process-development_small-scale-bioprocess-optimization-using-soft-sensors</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17443</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>BioProcess International Europe, Vienna, Austria, 2-4 April 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21967</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-30T12:24:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Inklusive Begegnungs(t)räume co-kreativ gestalten : die ergotherapeutische Perspektive</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ballmer, Thomas Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schulze, Christina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wenger, Ines</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gantschnig, Brigitte</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Ergotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Inklusion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Öffentlicher Raum</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-03-12T13:18:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-03-12T13:18:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-03-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.inuas.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/INUAS2021_Book-of-Abstract_FINAL.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21967</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Book of Abstracts INUAS Konferenz 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>INUAS Konferenz 2021 "Urbane Transformationen: Ressourcen", Online, 3.-5. März 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>HM Hochschule München</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3491</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T10:33:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Open cloud computing interface : core</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Edmonds, Andrew</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nyrén, Ralf</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Papaspyrou, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Metsch, Thijs</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Cloudcomputing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Open Standards</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>OCCI</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The Open Cloud Computing Interface (OCCI) is a RESTful Protocol and API for all kinds of management tasks. OCCI was originally initiated to create a remote management API for IaaS model-based services, allowing for the development of interoperable tools for common tasks including deployment, autonomic scaling and monitoring. It has since evolved into a flexible API with a strong focus on interoperability while still offering a high degree of extensibility. The current release of the Open Cloud Computing Interface is suitable to serve many other models in addition to IaaS, including PaaS and SaaS.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-03-07T14:27:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-07T14:27:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the Open Grid Forum 2011</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>OCCI working group within the Open Grid Forum (OGF), Boulder, USA, 16-20 May 2011</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4428</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-16T07:27:04Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Fast realization of the modal vector fitting method for rational modeling with accurate representation of small eigenvalues</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gustavsen, Bjørn</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Heitz, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Signal processing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Admittance-based rational modeling of multiport systems is prone to error magnification in applications with high-impedance terminations. This problem is overcome by the modal vector fitting method (MVF) which is formulated in terms of modal components with inverse least-squares weighting by the eigenvalue magnitude. A direct realization of MVF is very demanding in computation time and memory requirements. This paper overcomes the performance deficiency via three steps: 1) the required number of MVF iterations is reduced by precalculating an improved initial pole set via conventional vector fitting with inverse magnitude weighting; 2) the pole identification step is calculated in an efficient manner by solving for only the few essential unknowns while exploiting the sparse matrix structure; and 3) the residue identification step is calculated efficiently by a row-wise solution procedure that takes advantage of symmetry. The approach is demonstrated to give large savings for the modeling of a frequency-dependent network equivalent.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T14:59:51Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T14:59:51Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1109/TPWRD.2008.2005462</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1109/TPWRD.2008.2005462</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4428</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4428</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4428</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0885-8977</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>IEEE Transactions on Power Delivery</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>IEEE</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13185</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T11:44:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The Kursk submarine disaster in view of resilience assessment</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Leksin, Alexey</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mock, Ralf Günter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Resilienz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Risikoassessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>350: Öffentliche Verwaltung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>363: Umwelt- und Sicherheitsprobleme</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In August 12, 2000, the Russian Oscar-class submarine Kursk (K-141) sank during a navy manoeuvre in the Barents Sea killing all 118 personnel on board. The vessel was powered by two nuclear reactors and carry nuclear missiles which can be armed. The disaster is well documented and encompasses many socio-technical elements influencing the sequence of events finally leading to wreckage. For this, the disaster is considered as an archetypical event which might highlight the advantages as well as the limitations of resilience assessment approaches, e.g. in comparison with established risk assessment methodology. For this the paper starts with results of a literature survey with resilience metrics and areas of technical applications. The Kursk disaster is reviewed by available literature and research reports by Root Cause Analysis. The causing aspects (events, procedures, human factors, etc.) are then structured and classified according to their relevance and impact on vessel’s resilience. In a next step, these aspects are contrasted to the risk assessment approach as defined, e.g. by ISO 31000. The methodological juxtaposition is intended to characterize the maturity level of resilience analysis in a real world framework as well as to elaborate major differences in validity of the underlying system analysis concepts. Finally, the pros and cons of the reviewing approach are discussed.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-23T09:23:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-23T09:23:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2749</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2749</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13185</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13185</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13185</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-0-8153-8682-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Safety and  reliability : societies in a changing world</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>28th European Safety and Reliability Conference (ESREL 2018), Trondheim, Norway, 17-21 June 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Taylor &amp; Francis</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2348</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-16T13:48:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Distribution of amino groups on a mesoporous silica surface after submonolayer deposition of aminopropylsilanes from an anhydrous liquid phase</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Salmio, Hanna</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brühwiler, Dominik</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Silica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mesopores</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Amine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Functionalization</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>540: Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The reaction of mesoporous silica MCM-41 with various aminopropylsilanes was investigated. The distribution of grafted amino groups after submonolayer deposition from anhydrous toluene was probed by fluorescein labeling in conjunction with photoluminescence spectroscopy and pore size analysis. Monoalkoxysilanes generally distributed more uniformly than monopodal and dipodal trialkoxysilanes. The outcome of the grafting reaction additionally depended on the nature of the amino group. Secondary amines grafted more efficiently than their primary analogues. Moreover, it was found that the polarity of the solvent strongly affects the distribution of the amino groups in the case of strongly interacting aminopropylsilanes.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-01-31T10:28:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-31T10:28:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1021/jp0651440</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1021/jp0651440</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2348</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2348</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2348</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1932-7447</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of Physical Chemistry C</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>American Chemical Society</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10616</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-07-05T14:53:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Unsicherheit : ein blinder Fleck der Ökonomie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>332: Finanzwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Immer wieder werden die Finanzakrobaten der Wall Street, Londons, Frankfurts und Zürichs mit Kasinospielern in eine Reihe gestellt. Diese Vergleiche sollen die moralische Anrüchigkeit ihres Berufsstandes hervorheben, bei näherem Hinsehen sind es aber eher die Kasinos, die um ihren Ruf ob dieser Gleichsetzung besorgt sein sollten.&#13;
&#13;
Betrachten wir zum Beispiel ein typisches Kasinospiel, Roulette. Ohne Manipulationen des Spieltisches und faule Tricks des Croupiers stehen die Chancen 18 zu 37, dass eine Wette auf die roten Felder den Einsatz verdoppelt. Den Gesetzen der Statistik folgend, wird der Kasinobetreiber bei dieser Wette im Durchschnitt gewinnen und der Spieler mit Verlusten den Saal verlassen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-17T09:07:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-17T09:07:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10616</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10616</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://www.oekonomenstimme.org/artikel/2010/08/unsicherheit-eine-blinder-fleck-der-oekonomie/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10616</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Ökonomenstimme</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>KOF Konjunkturforschungsstelle der ETH Zürich</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5100</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T10:11:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>From teaching translation to learning organization : co-emergence as a motor of institutional development</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Massey, Gary</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Emergentism</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Translationsdidaktik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Emergenz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Translation pedagogy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>For some time, attempts to bridge the “academy-industry divide” (Drugan, 2013) by professionalising learners have been a major concern of translator education, most clearly reflected in the widespread uptake of “authentic experiential learning” (Kiraly et al., 2016a) in the form of mentorships, work placements and intra-curricular learning scenarios such as student translation companies (e.g. Vandepitte, 2009) and project-based learning (e.g. Kiraly, 2005). A major focus falls on the integration of language-technology and project-management skills, which combined language industry and educational forums such as LIND-Web (2013) and Translating Europe (2014) consider key to narrowing the discrepancy between graduate skill sets and dynamic market needs. Their continued calls suggest that didactic initiatives undertaken so far require further improvement.
Epistemologically, authentic experiential learning has been rooted in social-constructivist (cf. Kiraly, 2000) and, later, co-emergentist (cf. Kiraly, 2012, 2013; Kiraly and Hofmann 2016) models of competence development, in which the overriding goal is the reflective practice (Schön, 1987) seen as essential to evolving expertise (cf. Ericsson et al., 1993; Shreve, 2006; Smith &amp; Ericsson, 1991). While social-constructivist approaches tend to stress guided collaborative learning at various levels of complexity in authentic, predominantly curricular settings, an important additional aspect of the co-emergentist perspective is its fractal, scalable nature both within and beyond the curriculum – extending from the classroom activities, units, modules and courses to the real-world clients who commission projects and the post-curricular communities of practice where graduates work.
There seems to be broad congruence between these models and approaches long proposed for organizational learning, most prominently Senge’s (1990/1999) concepts of holistic systems thinking, personal mastery, mental (re-)modelling, shared vision building and team learning. Yet, little attention has been paid by the expert institutions where translation curricula are designed and implemented to the scalability of co-emergent learning up to the organizational (and supra-organizational) level. This presentation will therefore sketch out potential and actual applications and implications of a co-emergent perspective on curricular design as a powerful motor of organizational development. Drawing on challenges identified, strategies implemented and operational measures taken at our institute, it will argue that only by creating and supporting an integrated framework for student and staff interactions with communities of translation practice, on the one hand, and with applied (action) research, on the other, that translator education institutions and their human resources can be sufficiently empowered to fulfil their transformative role.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T13:26:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T13:26:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-09-23</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5100</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5100</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5100</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Symposium: Best Practices, Challenges and New Horizons in the Teaching of Translation and Translation Technology, Surrey, Canada, 23 September 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11464</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-24T14:13:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Isn't it cute : an evolutionary perspective of baby-schema effects in visual product designs</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Miesler, Linda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leder, Helmut</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Herrmann, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Baby schema</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Anthropomorphism</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Product design</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Consumer Behaviour</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.5: Produktionssteuerung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Through applying an evolutionary approach, we examined affective consumer responses to facial features in product designs. Previous studies have suggested that consumers might perceive the fronts of cars similarly to how they perceive human faces, but how consumers respond on an affective level to evolutionarily significant features when they are part of artifacts such as product designs has not been thoroughly studied. Therefore, we studied affective responses to features of an important stimulus that is known to elicit affect and approach behavior: the baby schema. We tested whether the affective responses to this stimulus were generalized to product designs, and how stable these generalized responses were over repeated exposures. We manipulated car fronts – and faces as controls – in accordance with the baby schema (e.g., by enlarging the headlights/eyes). Combining facial electromyography with cuteness ratings to assess innate affective responses, we found that our participants (n = 57) showed more positive affective responses to the babyfaced car fronts than to the original stimuli, and that the effect of the babyschema features on positive affect was stable over two repeated exposures, thus did not show effects of fast habituation. These results confirm that consumers' affective responses to visual product designs are affected by evolutionarily-implemented features.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-04T14:30:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-04T14:30:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://ppcms.univie.ac.at/fileadmin/usermounts/lederh7/2011/MieslerLederHerrmann2011.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11464</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1994-036X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1991-3761</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>International Journal of Design</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>National Taiwan University of Science and Technology</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3130</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T11:57:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Nachfolgeregelung im Familienunternehmen : psychologische Aspekte</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lippmann, Eric</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Familienunternehmen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nachfolgeregelung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>158: Angewandte Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658: Allgemeines Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T10:54:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T10:54:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3130</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3130</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3130</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1661-3295</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Swiss Export Journal</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Swiss Export Verband</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16460</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-05-06T15:39:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_13970</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_13971</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Cocoa fruit processing methods and cocoa products obtained by the same</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hühn, Tilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>processing cocoa fruits</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>cocoa beans</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>wet grinding</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>664: Lebensmitteltechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Also published as: CO2018000199 (A2), CR20180085 (A), CU20180003 (A7), EP3345486 (A1), MX2018000244, (A), PE10282018 (A1), WO2017005373 (A1)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>patent submitter:ODC Lizenz AG, Stans CH</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Disclosed is a method for processing cocoa fruits, comprising the steps of: (a) adding water to cocoa beans to form a suspension; (b) wet grinding said suspension; (c) subjecting said suspension to a heat treatment at a temperature of 70°C or less; (d) separating the suspension into a water phase (heavy phase), a fat phase (light phase) and a solid phase, said fat phase comprising cocoa butter as a major component and solids and/or water as minor components and said solid phase comprising cocoa powder and water; and (e) separately processing the three phases, which optionally comprises: separating cocoa butter from the fat phase, separating cocoa powder from the solid phase, and separating cocoa aroma and a polyphenolic powder from at least the water phase; wherein the cocoa beans are non-depulped; or wherein cocoa pulp contained in cocoa fruits are separated from the cocoa beans in a depulping step, processed separately from the cocoa beans, and subsequently added to the suspension before or during any of steps (a), (b), (c), or (d). Further disclosed are methods of manufacturing of a cocoa product construction kit and chocolate or chocolate-like products comprising high amounts of nutritionally beneficial and useful components of the cocoa fruit, such as e.g. polyphenols, antioxidants, vitamins and/or sugars, making use of the above technique.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-04-04T09:42:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-04T09:42:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Patent</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>patentid:EP3114939(B1)</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16460</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16460</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16460</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8230</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T13:39:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Merkblatt 6 : Sedimentumleitstollen und künstliche Hochwasser</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Facchini, M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martín Sanz, E.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vetsch, D.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Robinson, C. T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Döring, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Siviglia, A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Scheidegger, C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Boes, R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>551: Geologie und Hydrologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>577: Ökologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Geschiebedurchgängigkeit wird durch Stauseen unterbrochen. Im Unterlauf führt dies zu einem Geschiebedefizit, mit negativen Folgen für die Ökologie und Morphologie der Fliessgewässer. Sedimentumleitstollen und künstliche Hochwasser sind Massnahmen, mit denen sich die Sedimentverfügbarkeit erhöhen und Geschiebedefizite mildern lassen. Das vorliegende Merkblatt beschreibt die beiden Massnahmen und erläutert sie anhand von Fallbeispielen. Zudem zeigt es auf, wie sie sich auf die Ökologie und Morphologie von Gewässern auswirken.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-17T14:04:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-17T14:04:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.bafu.admin.ch/dam/bafu/de/dokumente/wasser/uw-umwelt-wissen/merkblatt-6-sedimentumleitstollen-und-kuenstliche-hochwasser.pdf.download.pdf/merkblatt-6-sedimentumleitstollen-und-kuenstliche-hochwasser.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8230</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Merkblatt-Sammlung Wasserbau und Ökologie : Geschiebe- und Habitatsdynamik</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>8 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Bundesamt für Umwelt</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken completeListSize="24863" cursor="123">oai_dc////12400</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
