<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="static/style.xsl"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-06-08T16:55:42Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" resumptionToken="oai_dc////15300">https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/oai/request/</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8458</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T10:36:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>"Etwas schaffen, worauf man stolz sein kann." Kulturentwicklung am Beispiel der Emmi AG</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hoffmann, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Unternehmenswerte</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kulturentwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Unternehmenskultur</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Führungskräfteentwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Dieses Kapitel zeigt einen Ausschnitt aus der Erfolgsgeschichte von Emmi: Es beschreibt, wie das größte Schweizer Milchverarbeitungsunternehmen in einem raschen agrarpolitischen Wandel kontinuierlich eine Firmenkultur aufbaut und damit eine wichtige Basis für den nachhaltigen Unternehmenserfolg legt. Die Fallanalyse zeigt, mit welchen Herausforderungen Emmi konfrontiert ist, wie Kulturentwicklung bei Emmi erfolgt, welche Ergebnisse und Erfahrungen dabei gemacht wurden und welche Erkenntnisse für Kulturentwicklung daraus abgeleitet werden können. Basis ist ein Gespräch zwischen der Personalleiterin Emmi, Natalie Rüedi, Mitglied der Konzernleitung, mit Christoph Hoffmann vom IAP Institut für Angewandte Psychologie, verantwortlicher Projektleiter der begleitenden Führungsentwicklung. Es wird aufgezeigt, wie Emmi die Kultur gezielt beeinflusst und steuert, wie dazu Werte, Führungsgrundsätze und Instrumente erarbeitet wurden und welche Rolle die gezielte Führungsentwicklung dabei spielt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-24T15:12:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-24T15:12:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-40910-3_10</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-642-40910-3_10</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8458</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8458</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8458</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-642-40909-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-642-40910-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Unternehmenskultur aktiv gestalten : Praxisfälle aus Wirtschaft, öffentlichem Dienst, Kultur und Sport</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/128</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-18T09:04:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1091</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_19</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ammoniakimmissionsmessungen : Vergleich von Zürcher- und Radiello-Passivsammlern</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Locher, René</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Vergleich von Messmethoden</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Luftqualität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Robuste Regression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gam</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Air quality</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Comparison of measuring methods</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gam</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Robust regression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>363: Umwelt- und Sicherheitsprobleme</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The Swiss program for reducing ammonia emissions caused by agriculture has been evaluated since 1999 by monitoring ambient concentrations of ammonia. At the beginning, so-called Zuercher passive samplers were used for this purpose, which were replaced in 2004 by Radiello passive samplers.&#13;
&#13;
In this project the two measuring methods were compared. The data used were collected in a measuring campaign from 2003 to 2007, where both methods were simultaneously applied at eight different measurement sites. At five of these sites, the ammonia concentrations were determined additionally by so-called mini-denuders. Statistical analysis showed that the differences between the three measuring methods substantially depend on the measurement site and could not be attributed to other well-known quantities. No universal method could thus be developed which can be applied regardless of the site. It is therefore recommended not to use the data collected with the Zürcher passive sampler for trend analysis.&#13;
&#13;
As a byproduct of this work, standard deviation and coefficient of variation for repeated measurements could be determined as a (continuous) function of the ammonia concentration.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Immissionsmessungen von Ammoniak sind ein wichtiges Instrument der Erfolgskontrolle bei der Umsetzung der Massnahmen zur Reduktion der Ammoniak-Emissionen im Rahmen der aktuellen Agrarpolitik in der Schweiz. Seit Mitte 1999 werden deshalb vom BAFU und den Kantonen finanzierte Ammoniak-Messungen vorgenommen. Zu Beginn der Messungen wurden dafür die so genannten Zürcher-Passivsammler verwendet, welche um das Jahr 2004 durch Radiello-Passivsammler ersetzt wurden.

In dem hier beschriebenen Projekt wurden die beiden Messmethoden miteinander verglichen. Die dazu notwendigen Daten stammten aus einer Messkampagne von 2003 bis 2007, in welcher an acht Standorten mit beiden Methoden gleichzeitig gemessen wurde. An fünf Standorten davon wurden die Ammoniakkonzentrationen zusätzlich mittels Minidenudern bestimmt. Die statistischen Analysen zeigten, dass die Unterschiede zwischen den drei Messmethoden wesentlich vom Standort der Messungen abhängen. Da die Standortabhängigkeit nicht auf allgemein bekannte Grössen zurückgeführt werden konnte, konnte damit kein allgemein gültiges Verfahren entwickelt werden, welches unabhängig vom Standort angewendet werden kann. Es wird deshalb empfohlen, die mit dem Zürcher Passivsammler erhobenen Daten nicht für Trendanalysen zu verwenden.

Als Nebenprodukt dieser Arbeiten konnte für Mehrfachmessungen mittels Radiello-Passivsammler erstmals Standardabweichung und Variationskoeffizient als (kontinuierliche) Funktion der Ammoniakkonzentration bestimmt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>The Swiss program for reducing ammonia emissions caused by agriculture has been evaluated since 1999 by monitoring ambient concentrations of ammonia. At the beginning, so-called Zuercher passive samplers were used for this purpose, which were replaced in 2004 by Radiello passive samplers.

In this project the two measuring methods were compared. The data used were collected in a measuring campaign from 2003 to 2007, where both methods were simultaneously applied at eight different measurement sites. At five of these sites, the ammonia concentrations were determined additionally by so-called mini-denuders. Statistical analysis showed that the differences between the three measuring methods substantially depend on the measurement site and could not be attributed to other well-known quantities. No universal method could thus be developed which can be applied regardless of the site. It is therefore recommended not to use the data collected with the Zürcher passive sampler for trend analysis.

As a byproduct of this work, standard deviation and coefficient of variation for repeated measurements could be determined as a (continuous) function of the ammonia concentration.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2015-07-10T12:04:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-07-10T12:04:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-128</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-128</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/128</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/128</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/128</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-905745-73-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>IDP Environmetrics</dc:relation>
          <dc:format>37 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24433</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-04T04:04:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1315</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1463</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Phosphorrückgewinnung aus kommunalem Klärschlamm mittels hydrothermaler Karbonisierung und Säureauswaschung : Einfluss von Kohlendioxid-Eingasung auf den Prozess der Hydrothermalen Karbonisierung und der Vergleich verschiedener Nachweismethoden</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Meyer, Luca</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Klärschlamm</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mikrowellenaufschluss</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Phosphorrückgewinnung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>HTC</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Photometrische Phosphorbestimmung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>ICP-OES</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kohlendioxid-Eingasung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schwermetalle</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>660: Technische Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die immer knapper werdenden Vorräte an hochwertigem Phosphor stellen die Menschheit vor ein Problem. Um den weltweit steigenden Nahrungsbedarf auch in Zukunft zu decken, sind alternative Phosphorquellen unumgänglich. Eine Möglichkeit diesen Bedarf zu decken, besteht durch das Schliessen von Phosphorkreisläufen. Das im Abwasser anfallende Phosphor sollte zurückgewonnen und der Landwirtschaft in Form von Dünger zur Verfügung gestellt werden. Es sind viele verschiedene Varianten der Phosphorrückgewinnung bekannt und teilweise bereits im Einsatz. In dieser Arbeit wird untersucht, welchen Vorteil die Kombination von zwei verschiedenen Varianten der Phosphorrückgewinnung bringt. Dabei handelt es sich um die hydrothermale Karbonisierung, welches den Klärschlamm karbonisiert und den Phosphor in das Prozesswasser überführt und das Budenheimer-Verfahren, bei welchem der Phosphor des Klärschlammes, bei einer Eingasung von CO2, gelöst und ebenfalls in das Prozesswasser überführt wird. Neben der Kombination dieser beiden Verfahren und einer Erfolgskontrolle, wurden verschiedene Phosphornachweismethoden und eine Brennwertanalyse vorgenommen. Die Auswertungen der Kombination der beiden Verfahren mittels ICP-OES hat ergeben, dass mit der Eingasung von CO2 während der hydrothermalen Karbonisierung doppelt so viel Phosphor ins Prozesswasser überführt werden kann. Dabei handelt es sich jedoch um lediglich 0.2 % des im Ausgangsmaterial enthaltenen Phosphor. &#13;
Bei den Nachweismethoden wurde untersucht, ob sich die Resultate der ICP-OES Messung, der photometrischer Bestimmung nach Hach Lange und der photometrischen Phosphorbestimmung mit Ammoniummolybdat, signifikante Unterschiede aufzeigen. Die Auswertung der Resultate hat ergeben, dass keine signifikanten Unterschiede feststellbar sind und sich demzufolge alle Nachweismethoden, abgesehen vom Preis und dem Aufwand, gleich gut zur Phosphorbestimmung eignen. Die abschliessende Brennwertanalyse hat ergeben, dass der Brennwert der bearbeiteten Klärschlammkohlen genug hoch ist, dass sich die Kohlen weiterhin als alternatives Brennmaterial eignet.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>The increasingly scarce reserves of high-quality phosphorus pose a problem for mankind. Alternative sources of phosphorus are indispensable to meet the increasing global demand for food in the future. One way of meeting this demand is to close phosphorus cycles. The phosphorus produced in wastewater should be recovered and made available to agriculture in the form of fertilizer. Many different variants of phosphorus recovery are known and some are already in use. In this paper it will be investigated which advantage the combination of two different variants of phosphorus recovery brings. These are the hydrothermal carbonisation, which carbonises the sewage sludge and transfers the phosphorus into the process water, and the Budenheimer process, in which the phosphorus of the sewage sludge is dissolved and also transferred into the process water. In addition to the combination of these processes and a success control, various phosphorus detection methods and a calorific value analysis were carried out. The evaluation of the combination of the two methods using ICP-OES has shown that with the gasification of CO2 during hydrothermal carbonisation twice as much phosphorus can be transferred into the process water. However, this is only 0.2 % of the phosphorus contained in the starting material. &#13;
The detection methods examined whether the results of the ICP-OES measurement, the photometric determination according to Hach Lange and the photometric phosphorus determination with ammonium molybdate show significant differences. The evaluation of the results has shown that no significant differences are detectable and therefore all detection methods, apart from price and effort, are equally suitable for phosphorus determination. The final calorific value analysis has shown that the calorific value of the processed sewage sludge coal is high enough that the coal is still suitable as an alternative fuel.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-03-02T14:24:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-03-02T14:24:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-24433</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-24433</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24433</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24433</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24433</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>68 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6483</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-16T07:27:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Optimierung von Neubauten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hubbuch, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.2: Facility Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>690: Hausbau und Bauhandwerk</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-04T12:35:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-04T12:35:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6483</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6483</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6483</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>In puncto: die Fachzeitschrift für Facility Management</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Facility Management Schweiz</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9599</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T10:12:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Methodische Überlegungen zur indirekten Teilliquidation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Buchser, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jau, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>IWR</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Liquidaion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Nach der aktuellen Rechtsprechung des Bundesgerichts zur indirekten Teilliquidation realisiert der Verkäufer einer Beteiligung selbst dann einen steuerbaren Ertrag im Sinne von Art. 20 Abs. 1 lit. c DBG, wenn die von der verkauften Gesellschaft ausgeschütteten Mittel zum Verkaufszeitpunkt bei ihr nicht vorhanden waren. Dieses Ergebnis entspricht indessen nicht dem wirtschaftlichen Ertragsbegriff, wie er sich aus teleologischer Auslegung des Gesetzes ergibt. Auch kann dem Gesetz keine Grundlage für derartige steuersystematische Zugriffe entnommen werden. Die Ergebnisse der bundesgerichtlichen Rechtsprechung lassen sich überdies weder durch Lückenfüllung noch den Rückgriff auf das Instrument der Steuerumgehung begründen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-24T11:12:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-24T11:12:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9599</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9599</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9599</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1422-3481</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Archiv für Schweizerisches Abgaberecht</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Editions Weblaw</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13910</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T07:21:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Brave new web : emerging design principles and technologies as enablers of a global SOA</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schroth, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Christ, Oliver</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Emerging design principle</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>IEEE Conference</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>New web</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>SOA</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Web services have experienced great interest during the last years as they were expected to play a key role as enablers of seamless application-to-application integration both within company boundaries and on a global, cross-organizational scale. As a technical foundation for the realization of service-oriented architectures (SOAs), Web services encapsulate complexity inherent to individual applications and allow for their loose coupling. However, a truly global mesh of such services has not yet become reality due to various reasons. Novel technologies and design principles are currently about to emerge which allow human users to use, customize, combine, interconnect and finally expose Web-based content or functionality as new resources which are often referred to as mash-ups. In this article, we provide an overview of existing mash-ups as well as tools and platforms that empower users to build them in a highly efficient and intuitive fashion. Statistical data and case studies are leveraged to examine new ways of resource provision and consumption and also the relevance of upcoming intermediaries. Finally, we investigate remaining research challenges on the path to a truly global SOA.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-12-17T09:18:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-17T09:18:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1109/SCC.2007.32</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1109/SCC.2007.32</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13910</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13910</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13910</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:0-7695-2925-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>IEEE International Conference on Services Computing (SCC 2007)</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>IEEE International Conference on Services Computing (SCC 2007), Salt Lake City, USA, 9-13 July 2007</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>IEEE</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15927</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-22T13:11:32Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Anti-Schwarze-Rassimsus : juristische Untersuchung zu Problem und Handlungsbedarf</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Naguib, Tarek</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pärli, Kurt</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bircher, Nadine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Licci, Sara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schärer, Salome</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>341: Völkerrecht und Europarecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>An der dritten Weltkonferenz gegen Rassismus im Jahre 2001 verlangten die Staaten aus Süd-, West- und Zentralafrika von den europäischen und amerikanischen Ländern Entschädigungszahlungen für das Unrecht, das Schwarze Menschen durch den transatlantischen Sklavenhandel und die Diskriminierung weltweit erfahren mussten. In der Folge richtete die damalige Menschenrechtskommission der Vereinten Nationen eine Arbeitsgruppe aus Expertinnen und Experten ein und beauftragte diese, die Zusammenhänge zwischen der Geschichte des Kolonialismus und dem gegenwärtigen Rassismus gegenüber Menschen afrikanischer Herkunft in Afrika und in der Diaspora vertieft zu untersuchen (UN Working Group). Das Gremium hat die Aufgabe, Massnahmen zu empfehlen, mit denen rassistische Diskriminierung bekämpft werden können. Angesichts der Herausforderungen, die sich im Kampf gegen den Anti-Schwarze-Rassismus ergeben, verabschiedete auch der Ausschuss zur Überwachung des internationalen Übereinkommens zur Beseitigung jeder Form von Rassendiskriminierung eine Allgemeine Bemerkung Nr. 34, in der er die Vertragsstaaten dazu anhält, die Diskriminierung von Menschen afrikanischer Herkunft mit spezifischen Mitteln zu bekämpfen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-03-08T08:06:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-08T08:06:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.ekr.admin.ch/pdf/ZHAW_Studie_Anti_Schwarze_Rassismus_2017.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15927</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>196 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Eidgenössischen Kommission gegen Rassismus</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5219</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-12T11:25:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Industrie 4.0 für die Siedlungsentwässerung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rüst, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Industrie 4.0</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Siedlungsentwässerung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sewage System</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Internet of Things</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>620: Ingenieurwesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>670: Industrielle und handwerkliche Fertigung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T09:12:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T09:12:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5219</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5219</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5219</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>VSA-Fachtagung: «Abwassermesstechnik im Zeitalter der Digitalisierung», Glattbrugg, 8. März 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Verband Schweizer Abwasser- und Gewässerschutzfachleute</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3549</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-03-08T13:13:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Image und Identität des Facility Managements : was denkt die Schweiz und die FM-Branche über sich?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Coenen, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>von Felten, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Böhm, Manuel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Identität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Facility Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Image</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.2: Facility Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-08T13:13:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-08T13:13:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3549</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3549</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3549</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Komplettanbieter im Facility Management : Marktübersicht Schweiz und Österreich</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>RESO</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header status="deleted">
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22823</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-01T09:49:47Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16462</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-05-06T15:39:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_13970</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_13971</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Chocolate, chocolate-like products, chocolate construction kit and methods for preparing the same</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hühn, Tilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Chocolate</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>chocolate-like products</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>chocolate construction kit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>663: Getränketechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Also published as: AU2016289316 (A1), BR112018000433 (A2), CA2991343 (A1), CN108024552 (A), CO2018000416 (A2), CR20180083 (A), CU20180004 (A7), DK3114940 (T3), EP3308650 (A1), ES2669996 (T3), HRP20180657 (T1), HUE038295 (T2), JP2018520702 (A), KR20180030568 (A), LT3114940 (T), MX2018000235 (A), PE10292018 (A1), PH12018500039 (A1), PL3114940 (T3), PT3114940 (T), RS57155 (B1), SI3114940 (T1), US2018192665 (A1), WO2017005371 (A1)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>patent submitter:ODC Lizenz AG, Stans CH</dc:description>
          <dc:description>The method for processing fermented or incubated cocoa beans comprises the steps of: adding water to fermented or incubated cocoa beans or nibs to form a suspension; wet grinding said suspension; subjecting said suspension to a heat treatment at a temperature of 70°C or less; separating the suspension into a water phase (heavy phase), a fat phase (light phase) and a solid phase, said fat phase comprising cocoa butter as a major component and solids and/or water as minor components and said solid phase comprising cocoa powder and water; and separately processing the three phases, which comprises: neutralizing and/or removing acetic acid formed during fermentation or formed or added prior to or during an incubation of the cocoa beans via the water phase, and optionally separating cocoa butter from the fat phase, separating cocoa powder from the solid phase, and separating cocoa aroma and a polyphenolic powder from at least the water phase.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-04-04T09:52:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-04T09:52:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Patent</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>patentid:EP3114940(B1)</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16462</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16462</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://register.epo.org/espacenet/regviewer?AP=15002046&amp;CY=EP&amp;LG=en&amp;DB=REG</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16462</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23576</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-29T09:44:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Characterizing CHO cell lines with SFR vario : what online measured data can tell about your cell culture</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Maschke, Rüdiger</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pretzner, Barbara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>John, Gernot T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eibl, Dieter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>CHO cell culture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Shake flask</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mammalian cell</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Growth rate determination</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Online shake flask measurement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>660.6: Biotechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>There are numerous CHO cell lines with different properties. They need to be characterized before starting a production process, to ensure the cells are suitable for the planned application. The SFR vario is a multiparameter monitoring platform for shake flask culture and delivers online data for oxygen, pH and biomass. In this report we give a few examples on how this online monitoring device can be used to characterize precultures of CHO cell lines before starting a bioreactor run.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-11-29T09:44:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-29T09:44:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.presens.de/knowledge/publications/application-note/characterizing-cho-cell-lines-with-sfr-vario-1723</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23576</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>PreSens Publications</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>PreSens Precision Sensing</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5527</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-26T10:36:39Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>SEPAWA Fachgruppe Reinigung und Pflege : von der Vielfalt der Rohstoffe und deren Auswirkungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kimmel, Tobias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hofmann, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leiblein, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Rohstoff</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Waschmittel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nachhaltigkeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Reinigungsmittel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>648: Haushaltsführung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Im Frühjahr fand in Rapperswil die jährlich wiederkehrende Vortragsveranstaltung der ­SEPAWA-Fachgruppe «Professionelle Reinigung &amp; Pflege» statt. Die Veranstaltung unter dem Titel «Klein, aber oho! – Rohstoffe machen’s möglich» befasste sich mit der besonderen ­Bedeutung von ­Rohstoffen, deren Anforderungen und deren Applikation aus verschiedenen ­Blickwinkeln. Erster Teil des Rückblicks auf die Veranstaltung.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-24T14:42:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-24T14:42:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5527</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5527</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5527</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2190-6378</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Rationell reinigen + mop Schweiz</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Holzmann Medien</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15937</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T14:06:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The thin win : implicit preference for slim models in advertising</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hari, Jürg</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Forestier, Céline</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Implicit Association Test</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Werbung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>659: Werbung und Öffentlichkeitsarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Much of human behaviour is influenced by non-conscious, uncontrolled, unobserved processes in memory (i.e. implicit processes). Implicit methods have some attractiveness for practitioners, but they are not widely used in commercial marketing research. This research therefore, intends to expand knowledge on consumer research using methods studying implicit processes. The popular debate over slim models in advertising serves as a real world situation for the Implicit Association Test (IAT). A picture / word format was used for this IAT study. Pairs of attractive / less attractive key visuals for advertising (4 brands) were produced using commercially available software. The two pictures included a women, a product logo and some background. We only manipulated the size of the women (slim and well-rounded).&#13;
&#13;
The study with 60 participants confirms the "what is beautiful is good"-stereotype on the implicit level. Both, males and females clearly favoured slim models over well-rounded models. Also, the study finds no correlation between explicit, stated preferences and the implicit preference. In conclusion, this study demonstrates the usefulness of the IAT for studying consumer behaviour. Its application in management practice is strongly encouraged.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-03-08T08:33:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-08T08:33:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://marketing.conference-services.net/resources/327/2958/pdf/AM2012_0131_paper.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15937</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Academy of Marketing Conference 2012, Southampton, United Kingdom, 2-5 July 2012</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15574</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-12-16T12:34:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Statistische Analyse von Unfallzahlen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Deublein, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hafsteinsson, Helgi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Frey, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dettling, Marcel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meier, Lukas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kalisch, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>363: Umwelt- und Sicherheitsprobleme</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Forschungsprojekt VSS 2016/511/ auf Antrag des Schweizerischen Verbandes der Strassen- und Verkehrsfachleute (VSS)</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-21T14:21:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-21T14:21:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.astra.admin.ch/dam/astra/de/bilder/Abteilung_Strassenverkehr_allgemein/2018-07-31_VSS1634_Schlussbericht_Statistische_Analyse_von_Unfallzahlen.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15574</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>117 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Bundesamt für Strassen</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7491</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T12:55:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Conceptual design of future children's hospitals in Europe : the role of caregivers in transferring new concepts from theory into practice</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ehrich, Jochen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Molloy, Eleanor</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kerbl, Reinhold</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pettoello-Mantovani, Massimo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vural, Mehmet</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gerber-Grote, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>362.11: Krankenhäuser und verwandte Einrichtungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-28T14:47:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-28T14:47:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpeds.2016.12.017</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.jpeds.2016.12.017</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0022-3476</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1097-6833</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>The Journal of Pediatrics</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10644</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-09-17T12:31:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Rezeption und Wirkung der Kampagne Crash Kurs NRW</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hackenfort, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bresges, André</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Weber, Jeremias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hofmann, Uwe</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Traffic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Unfälle</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Verkehrssicherheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kampagne</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>363: Umwelt- und Sicherheitsprobleme</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>380: Kommunikation und Verkehr</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Der Anstoß zu Crash Kurs NRW stammt aus England. Im Dezember 2008 haben zwei Mitarbeiter der nordrhein-westfälischen Polizei dort an einer „Bühnenveranstaltung“ in der Aula einer Schule der Grafschaft Staffordshire (in Mittelengland, etwa 1 Mio. Einwohner) teilnehmen können. Das dortige Crash Course Team, bestehend aus zwei hauptamtlichen und zwei nebenamtlichen Akteuren, präsentierte selbst erlebte Unfallsituationen aus der Sicht von Opfern, Tätern, Hinterbliebenen und Helfern auf sehr emotionale Weise vor 15- bis 16-jährigen Schülerinnen und Schülern. Unterstützt wurden die Vorträge durch Bildmaterial und Videospots. Die Veranstaltung dauerte etwas mehr als eine Stunde.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-17T12:31:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-17T12:31:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-658-01130-7_10</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-658-01130-7_10</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10644</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10644</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10644</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-658-01130-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-658-01129-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Verkehrssicherheitskommunikation : Beiträge der empirischen Forschung zur strategischen Unfallprävention</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6405</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:40:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>FM und Energieoptimierung beginnt in der Planungsphase</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hubbuch, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>333.79: Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.2: Facility Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-01T09:58:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-01T09:58:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6405</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6405</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6405</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Schweizer Energiefachbuch 2002</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Künzler Bachmann</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14983</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T08:08:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Public Relations und Öffentlichkeitsarbeit : Einführung in die Grundlagen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Szyszka, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Öffentlichkeitsarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Public Relations</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>659: Werbung und Öffentlichkeitsarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-02-05T15:26:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-05T15:26:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14983</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14983</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14983</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-322-91232-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-322-91231-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Öffentlichkeitsarbeit für Nonprofit-Organisationen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Gabler</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15060</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T13:39:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Movement patterns in spatio-temporal data</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gudmundsson, Joachim</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Laube, Patrick</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wolle, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>500: Naturwissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>2nd edition</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-05T18:19:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-05T18:19:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-17885-1_823</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-319-17885-1_823</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-319-17884-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-319-17885-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Encyclopedia of GIS</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17042</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-19T13:27:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Voluntary pooling of genetic risk : a health insurance experiment</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mimra, Wanda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nemitz, Janina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Waibel, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Health insurance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Genetic risk</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pooling</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Effort</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>360: Soziale Probleme und Sozialversicherungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610: Medizin und Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Scientific and technological advances increasingly allow for better tailoring of health insurance plans to individual health risk profiles. This development questions the sustainability of health plans that feature strong cross-subsidization across different health risk types and health behaviors. An important observation is that the willingness to cross-subsidize risks in health plans might depend on whether the risk is uncontrollable by individuals, such as genetic risk, or modifiable via health behaviors. This paper provides the results of an experiment on the willingness to pool genetic risk in health insurance. Subjects' overall health risk has an assigned, uncontrollable genetic risk part that differs across individuals as well as a behavioral risk part, which can be reduced by costly effort. Participants can decide between a pooling, community-rated group insurance scheme and an insurance with a fully individually risk-adjusted premium. In the experimental variation, the group insurance scheme either includes behavioral risk or separates it out via individual premium discounts. Although we observe social preferences for pooling, only a low level of actual genetic risk pooling emerges across the experimental conditions. This is due to both large heterogeneity in social preferences for pooling across subjects, and the dynamics of the willingness to pay for group insurance in the different experimental markets. Thus, our results indicate that mandatory pooling might be needed if, under the veil of ignorance, a society nevertheless wishes to pool certain forms of heterogeneous risk exposure, such as genetic risk.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-05-09T13:38:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-05-09T13:38:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17042</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17042</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17042</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>45th Annual Seminar of the European Group of Risk and Insurance Economists (EGRIE), Nuremberg, Germany, 17-19 September 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23438</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-04-26T03:05:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Beteiligung junger Menschen im Alltag der stationären Kinder- und Jugendhilfe verstehen und fördern : die Aktionsbox "Wie wir das sehen"</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rohrbach, Julia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eberitzsch, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Keller, Samuel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Heimerziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sichtweise junger Menschen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Beteiligung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Partizipation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Aktionsbox</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kinder- und Jugendhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.7: Jugendhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-11-10T08:14:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-10T08:14:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23438</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23438</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23438</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23438</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23438</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0943-4992</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Evangelische Jugendhilfe</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Evangelischer Erziehungsverband</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3089</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-25T08:03:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Viele, viele bunte Smarties</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Liebhart, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Smart City</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>IoT</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>307: Gemeinschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die spanische Stadt Santander macht es vor: 12 000 intelligente Sensoren in der ganzen Stadt verteilt – und schon wird eine Vielzahl smarter Anwendungen möglich, die das Leben der geplagten Städter verbessern. M2M heisst das Zauberwort.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T10:09:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T10:09:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4167</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4167</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3089</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3089</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3089</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-2397</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Netzwoche</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Netzmedien</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5581</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-13T13:29:39Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Inkontinenz, das verschwiegene Leiden : präsentiert an der Antrittsvorlesung zur Professur ZFH</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Köhler, Barbara</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Beckenbodentraining</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Tabuisierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Inkontinenz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616: Innere Medizin und Krankheiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-25T14:13:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-25T14:13:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-12-15</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Vorlesung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5581</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5581</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5581</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14843</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-04T12:57:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Grow or die: the strategic importance of M&amp;A : a scenario analysis for the heavy industry</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kucza, Gunther</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.1: Organisation und Finanzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-01-31T11:24:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-31T11:24:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14843</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14843</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14843</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>International ESCE Conference, Paris, France, 28-30 Januar 2009</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13213</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-24T14:11:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Process optimization for improved adhesion in the grafting of triethoxyvinylsilane on VLDPE via reactive extrusion</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schaible, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meincke, Olaf</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schulthess, Adrian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brändli, Christof</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Reactive extrusion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Adhesive</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Silane</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Grafting</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>VLDPE</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>660: Technische Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The grafting of triethoxyvinylsilane (TEVS) onto very low density polyethylene (VLDPE) via reactive extrusion was investigated with an emphasis on the temperature and amount of initiator used for the reaction. Two different peroxides (Luperox 101 and Peroxan PK 295P) were used as single initiators for the grafting reaction with and without an additional thermal stabilizer. Infrared spectra of the resulting polymers showed that grafting efficiency was high over the analysed temperature range from 120°C to 210°C. A new and more sensitive method, based on head space gas chromatography with mass spectrometry (head space GC–MS), was used to determine optimal grafting efficiencies. Above 160°C, the grafting efficiency for both initiators was greater than 80%. In general, grafting with the more reactive peroxide (P295) yielded more highly functionalized polymers. Optimization of the grafting process reduces the amount of unreacted grafting material, minimizing levels of free volatile components and reducing energy consumption. Melt viscosities were also analysed to identify unwanted side reactions. In general, compared to polymers produced with P295, those made with Luperox 101 exhibited more rapidly increasing complex viscosity with increasing amounts of initiator. T-peel adhesion tests were used to demonstrate the use of silane-grafted VLDPE as an adhesive on metal substrates. The T-peel strengths of modified VLDPE samples were between 0.6 and 2.6 N/mm, depending on the process conditions and the choice of initiator. The T-peel strength of Peroxan PK 295P was less dependent on initiator content, resulting in a more robust system for use in reactive extrusion technologies.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-23T10:45:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-23T10:45:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-27</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eurpolymj.2018.07.046</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.eurpolymj.2018.07.046</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13213</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13213</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13213</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0014-3057</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>European Polymer Journal</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3381</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-24T14:10:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Basler interdisziplinäre Sprechstunde für Eltern von Säuglingen und Kleinkindern : Konzept und empirische Ergebnisse</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>von Wyl, Agnes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Watson, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Glanzmann, René</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>von Klitzing, Kai</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Eltern-Säuglings-Psychotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Frühkindliche Regulationsstörung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Temperament</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Postpartale Depression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The Basel clinic for parents with infants and toddlers is a special interdisciplinary service. The authors present the concept and practice of treatment. Further they show the results of documentation and evaluation. In most cases regulation and sleeping disorders are treated. Temperament ratings made by the mothers of the treated children exhibit more difficult behaviour in comparison to a normal sample. These ratings had no correlation with the mothers’ depression scores which rank much higher than the control group. The outcome ratings by the psychotherapists show that despite the short duration of the treatment and severe cases therapeutical success could be achieved. This outlines the importance of such specialized services for early infant crying and other disturbances of the early childhood.

Die Basler interdisziplinäre Sprechstunde für Eltern von Säuglingen und Kleinkindern ist ein spezialisiertes interdisziplinäres Angebot. Die Autoren stellen das Konzept und die Behandlungspraxis vor. Außerdem werden Ergebnisse der Dokumentation und Evaluation dargestellt. Es zeigte sich, dass vor allem Regulations- und Schlafstörungen behandelt werden. Mütterliche Temperamentseinschätzungen zeigen, dass sich die behandelten Kinder deutlich von einer Normstichprobe unterscheiden, also schwieriger sind. Dabei korrelierte diese Einschätzung der Mütter nicht mit ihrer depressiven Befindlichkeit. Die depressive Befindlichkeit der Mütter ist deutlich über der einer Vergleichsgruppe. Eine Einschätzung des Behandlungserfolges durch die TherapeutInnen zeigt, dass vielfach mit relativ kurzer Behandlungsdauer ein Therapieerfolg erreicht werden konnte, und dies trotz der oft schwierigen Fälle. Dies unterstreicht die Bedeutung eines spezialisierten Behandlungsangebotes für Schreibabys und andere Probleme des frühen Kindesalters.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-03-01T11:07:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-01T11:07:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/20.500.11780/3049</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/20.500.11780/3049</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3381</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3381</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3381</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0032-7034</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2196-8225</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Praxis der Kinderpsychologie und Kinderpsychiatrie</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12329</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-16T07:28:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Frankia canadensis sp. nov., isolated from root nodules of Alnus incana subspecies rugosa</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Normand, Philippe</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nouioui, Imen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pujic, Petar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fournier, Pascale</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dubost, Audrey</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schwob, Guillaume</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Klenk, Hans-Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nguyen, Agnès</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Abrouk, Danis</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Herrera-Belaroussi, Aude</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pothier, Joël F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pflüger, Valentin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fernandez, Maria P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>570: Biologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Strain ARgP5T, an actinobacterium isolated from a root nodule present on an Alnus incana subspecies rugosa shrub growing in Quebec City, Canada, was the subject of polyphasic taxonomic studies to clarify its status within the genus Frankia. 16S rRNA gene sequence similarities and ANI values between ARgP5T and type strains of species of the genus Frankia with validly published names were 98.8 and 82 % or less, respectively. The in silico DNA G+C content was 72.4 mol%. ARgP5T is characterised by the presence of meso-A2pm, galactose, glucose, mannose, rhamnose (trace), ribose and xylose as whole-organism hydrolysates; MK-9(H8) as predominant menaquinone; diphosphatidylglycerol, phosphatidylinositol and phosphatidylglycerol as polar lipids and iso-C16 : 0 and C17 : 1ω8c as major fatty acids. The proteomic results confirmed the distinct position of ARgP5T from its closest neighbours in Frankia cluster 1. ARgP5T was found to be infective on two alder (Alnus glutinosa and Alnusalnobetula subsp. crispa) and on one bayberry (Morella pensylvanica) species and to fix nitrogen in symbiosis and in pure culture. On the basis of phylogenetic (16S rRNA gene sequence), genomic, proteomic and phenotypic results, strain ARgP5T (=DSM 45898=CECT 9033) is considered to represent a novel species within the genus Frankia for which the name Frankia canadensis sp. nov., is proposed.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-30T14:30:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-30T14:30:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1099/ijsem.0.002939</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1099/ijsem.0.002939</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12329</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12329</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12329</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1466-5026</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1466-5034</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>International Journal of Systematic and Evolutionary Microbiology</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Microbiology Society</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5944</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-14T15:12:56Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Integrated enzyme reactors with whole cells</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Yildirim, Selçuk</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Franco, T. T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Witholt, B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kohler, H. E.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schmid, A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>660: Technische Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-17T14:03:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-17T14:03:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2004-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5944</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5944</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5944</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>12th International Biotechnology Symposium and Exhibition, Santiago, Chile, 17-22 October 2004</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6337</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-14T12:24:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Medienwelt im Umbruch : wie sind die Auswirkungen auf die (Partei-)Politik?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stücheli-Herlach, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Organisationskommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Politische Kommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Demokratie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Medienkompetenz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>303: Soziale Prozesse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>320: Politik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Das so genannte dritte Zeitalter der politischen Kommunikation ist angebrochen. Die politische Arena ist geprägt durch Medialisierung, Pluralisierung und Professionalisierung. Das hat Konsequenzen für unseren Umgang mit der Demokratie. Sie ist konfrontiert mit neuen Möglichkeiten, aber auch mit Gefährdungen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-05-31T14:15:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-31T14:15:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6337</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6337</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6337</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Veranstaltungsreihe 2011/2012 der Neuen Helvetischen Gesellschaft Gruppe Bern, Bern, 14. Februar 2012</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9733</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-05T13:36:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wie sich die Dienstleistungswirtschaft durch Daten wandelt</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Meierhofer, Jürg</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Heinatz, Gundula</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Dienstleistung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Digitalisierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ecosystem</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>338: Produktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Dieses Werk ist lizenziert unter einer Creative Commons Namensnennung 3.0 Schweiz Lizenz (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/ch/)</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-27T13:03:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-27T13:03:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3949</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3949</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.societybyte.swiss/2018/07/24/von-der-digitalisierung-zur-dienstleistungswirtschaft/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9733</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2504-4672</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>SocietyByte</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>BFH-Zentrum Digital Society</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19279</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-30T04:02:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1315</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1463</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Umweltbildung in den St. Beatus-Höhlen : Entwicklung eines interaktiven Schulangebotes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Toffolon, Lara</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>St. Beatus-Höhlen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>St. Beatus-Höhle</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Höhle</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Umweltbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ausserschulischer Lernort</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bildungskonzept</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bildungsangebot</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die St. Beatus-Höhlen am Thunersee sind seit jeher ein bekanntes Ausflugsziel für Gross und Klein. Die Karsthöhle mit ihren wunderschönen Grotten, Tropfsteinen und dem rauschenden Höhlenbach wird jedes Jahr von vielen Schulklassen aus der ganzen Schweiz als faszinierendes Ausflugsziel besucht. Die Lehrpersonen können mit ihren Klassen entweder an einer öffentlichen Führung oder wenn mehr Budget vorhanden ist, an einer privaten Führung teilnehmen. Zusätzlich besteht die Möglichkeit selbständig die Ausstellung im Höhlenmuseum mit einem Audioguide zu besuchen und auf dem Drachenspielplatz zu picknicken. Ein zusätzliches schulisches Angebot mit Aufgaben und Arbeitsblättern für die Schüler und Schülerinnen gibt es bisher nicht. Seit einigen Jahren wurde dies vermehrt von Lehrpersonen gewünscht, auch mit einem gewissen Lehrplanbezug. Dieser ist für die Lehrperson eine Entscheidungshilfe und legitimiert den Angebotsbesuch gegenüber den Eltern und der Schulleitung.&#13;
In dieser Arbeit wird ein Bildungskonzept entwickelt, mit dem Ziel ein solides Planungsinstrument für ein neues schulisches Angebot in den St. Beatus-Höhlen zu schaffen. Das Konzept basiert auf einem Leitfaden und legt Wert auf das handlungs- und lösungsorientierte Vermitteln. Zuerst wurde der Bedarf für ein Angebot zum Thema Höhle abgeklärt, um auf die Bedürfnisse der Zielgruppe einzugehen. Das Konzept soll zeitgemäss und nachhaltig sein, darum basiert es auf dem Lehrplan 21. Auf diese Weise können Lehrpersonen das Angebot als Teil ihrer Unterrichtsgestaltung benutzen. Neben dem Bildungskonzept wurde ein Beispiel für ein Arbeitsdossier gegeben, welches die St. Beatus-Höhlen für Schulklassen zur Vor- oder Nachbereitung anbieten können. Dieses orientiert sich an anderen Arbeitsdossiers, welche in anderen Umweltbereichen eingesetzt werden.&#13;
Aus dem Konzept kristallisierte sich heraus, dass in naher Zukunft ein neues spannendes Angebot für Schulklassen mit der bereits jetzt vorhandenen Infrastruktur entstehen könnte.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-01-29T13:03:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-01-29T13:03:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-19279</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-19279</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19279</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19279</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19279</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>101 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17758</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-27T08:34:51Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die auftragsrechtliche Haftung des Steuerberaters : modelltheoretische Überlegungen zum ökonomische Nutzen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hanebrink, Jens</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-07-25T14:06:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-07-25T14:06:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17758</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17758</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17758</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7255-7310-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Ohne jegliche Haftung : Beiträge zum schweizerischen Haftpflicht- und Schuldrecht : Festschrift für Willi Fischer zum 65. Geburtstag</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schulthess</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2323</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-26T10:36:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Modification and qualification of a stirred single-use bioreactor for the improved expansion of human mesenchymal stem cells at benchtop scale</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jossen, Valentin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kaiser, Stephan C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schirmaier, Carmen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hermann, Jacqueline</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tappe, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eibl, Dieter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Siehoff, Ann</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>van den Bos, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eibl-Schindler, Regine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Computational fluid dynamics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Particle image velocimetry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Stirred single-use bioreactor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Human mesenchymal stem cell expansion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>660: Technische Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-01-31T09:33:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-31T09:33:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2323</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2323</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2323</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2048-9145</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2048-9153</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Pharmaceutical Bioprocessing</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Pulsus Group</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5645</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-14T15:28:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Von Geometrieförderung über Hiphop-Kurse zu freiem Spiel : Im Brennpunkt : Tagesschulen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Chiapparini, Emanuela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stohler, Renate</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bussmann, Esther</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Soziale Arbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Tagesschule</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ausserschulische Angebote</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ausserschulische Bildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Freizeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bildungsprozess</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schule</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schulische Leistung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pädagogische Zuständigkeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wohlbefinden</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Förderungsangebot</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Informelle Bildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Non-formale Bildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>371: Schulen und schulische Tätigkeiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>An Tagesschulen verbringen Kinder einen Teil ihrer Freizeit in der Schule. Diese «Zusatzzeit» gilt es so zu gestalten, dass sie sich wohlfühlen, aber auch Bildungsprozesse initiiert werden können. Die Soziale Arbeit ist gefordert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-27T12:10:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-27T12:10:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3603</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3603</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5645</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5645</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5645</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Sozial : Magazin der ZHAW Soziale Arbeit</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23817</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-12-23T04:03:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>JUNCO : Jugendliche und die Coronazeit – eine Untersuchung im Dt.-Nl. Grenzgebiet</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Weigand, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Baier, Dirk</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Janssen, Lothar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Levels, Mark</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schils, Trudie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bles, Per</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>305: Personengruppen (Alter, Herkunft, Geschlecht, Einkommen)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-12-22T13:53:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-12-22T13:53:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23817</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23817</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23817</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23817</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23817</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-9821584-1-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>82 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Lem- und Bildungsakademie Mönchengladbach</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24924</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-05-07T03:08:47Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ökofaktoren für marine Fischressourcen in Ökobilanzen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Itten, René</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stucki, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Ökobilanz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Life Cycle Assessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fisch</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fish</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ressource</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Resource</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Life Cycle Impact Assessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>LCIA</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>LCA</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>LCI</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wildfang</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Catch</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fischzucht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Aquaculture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333: Bodenwirtschaft und Ressourcen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Für die Nutzung von marinen Fischressourcen und dem durch Überfischung verursachten Biodiversitätsverlust fehlten bisher Vorgehensweisen zur Bewertung in Single-Score-Wirkungsabschätzungsmethoden wie der Methode der ökologischen Knappheit. Diese Lücke kann insbesondere im Bereich der Ernährung zu deutlich unterschätzten Umweltauswirkungen von Fischmenüs führen im Vergleich zu Fleischmenüs und vegetarischen Alternativen. &#13;
Ziel dieser Studie war die Entwicklung eines Ansatzes zur Berechnung von Ökofaktoren für marine Fischressourcen sowie die Aufnahme dieser Ökofaktoren in die Studie «Ökofaktoren Schweiz 2021 gemäss der Methode der ökologischen Knappheit». Der in diesem Bericht beschriebene Ansatz fokussiert ausschliesslich auf den vom Menschen induzierten Druck auf die unterschiedlichen marinen Fischressourcen. Auswirkungen auf die Ökosystemqualität wie auch durch die Ausbreitung von invasiven Arten sind mit dem gewählten Ansatz vorerst ausgeschlossen.&#13;
Der Charakterisierungsfaktor (CF) nach dem in dieser Studie vorgeschlagenen Charakterisierungsmodell basiert auf der Bestandsgrösse der verschiedenen Fischbestände sowie deren Regenerationsrate. Das vorgeschlagene Charakterisierungsmodell erlaubt daher die Unterscheidung verschiedener Fischarten in unterschiedlichen Fangregionen.&#13;
Zusätzlich zur Bewertung von marinen Fischressourcen werden ebenfalls Ansätze zur Integration von Beifang und Rückwurf in Abhängigkeit der Fangmethode sowie der Fischart vorgeschlagen. Ebenfalls werden Ansätze zur Berücksichtigung der Ökofaktoren für marine Fischressourcen bei der Produktion von Fischmehl und -öl vorgeschlagen und diskutiert.&#13;
Der Einbezug der Ökofaktoren für marine Fischressourcen sowie des Beifangs und Rückwurfs als auch die Anwendung der Ökofaktoren auf die indirekt genutzten Fischressourcen für die Herstellung von Fischmehl- und öl, welches in der Fischzucht verwendet wird, führt zu einem deutlichen Anstieg der Gesamtumweltbelastung von Fischprodukten. Dieser Anstieg führt dazu, dass Fischmenüs mit Fisch aus Wildfang in Abhängigkeit der Fischart und Fangregion eine Umweltauswirkung aufweisen können, welche bis zu 150-mal höher ist als mit der bisherigen Bewertung.&#13;
Die neuen Ökofaktoren für marine Fischressourcen ermöglichen eine differenzierte Bewertung der unterschiedlichen Fischarten unter Berücksichtigung der Fangregion und schliessen eine wichtige Lücke bei der Bewertung von verschiedenen Menüoptionen in der Gastronomie.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-05-06T13:26:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-05-06T13:26:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-05-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2650</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2650</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24924</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24924</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24924</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>46 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8413</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T10:53:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Longitudinal changes in everyday life after home modifications for people aging with disabilities</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Petersson, Ingela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kottorp, Anders Börje Mauritz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bergström, Jakob</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lilja, Margareta</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Regression analysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Architectural accessibility</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Disabled Person</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Environment design</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Occupational therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615.8515: Ergotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Objective: To investigate longitudinal impacts of home modifications on the difficulty of performing everyday life tasks for people aging with disabilities, and to investigate whether other factors had any additional impacts on difficulty in everyday life tasks for people receiving home modifications. &#13;
Methods: The sample consisted of 103 persons aging with disabilities and in need of home modifications, divided into an intervention group and a comparison group. The data were first subjected to Rasch analysis and a random coefficient model was used. &#13;
Results: Participants in the intervention group reported a significantly lower level of difficulty in everyday life tasks compared with those in the comparison group. One confounding factor, number of months waiting for home modification, had an impact on difficulty in everyday life. &#13;
Conclusion: Home modifications are effective in decreasing difficulty in performing everyday life tasks up to six months after the installation. Furthermore, to be effective home modifications need to be installed in a timely fashion. For each consecutive month the person waited for their home modification the difficulty of performing everyday life tasks increased. Therefore, it is important that home modifications be installed as soon as possible after the need has been identified.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-23T12:10:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-23T12:10:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1080/11038120802409747</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1080/11038120802409747</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8413</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8413</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8413</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1103-8128</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1651-2014</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>18821447</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Scandinavian Journal of Occupational Therapy</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Taylor &amp; Francis</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6855</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T15:30:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Pflanzenbehandlungsmittel-Markt weiter rückläufig</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hilber, Urs</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>630: Landwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-13T11:21:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-13T11:21:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1998</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6855</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6855</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6855</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1023-2958</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Obst- und Weinbau</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Verein Publikationen Spezialkulturen</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23697</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-04-08T13:39:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Stress, cognitive, emotional and ergonomic demands in interpreting and translation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gieshoff, Anne Catherine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lehr, Caroline</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hunziker Heeb, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Translation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Interpreting</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Meta-review</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Stress</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>155: Differentielle Psychologie und Entwicklungspsychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The autonomic nervous system is responsible for modulating peripheral functions in the human body and consists of sympathetic and parasympathetic branches. Its activation affects, among other things, heart rate, respiratory rate, salivation, perspiration, pupillary dilation, and blink rate. For some years now, physiological measurements have found their way into interpreting and translation studies to investigate, in particular, cognitive, emotional and ergonomic demands and stress in translating, interpreting and post-editing. We conducted a meta-review of publications from 1990 until 2020 in order to investigate the relevance of (a) the four constructs of emotional, cognitive and ergonomic demands and physiological stress and of (b) physiological data for translation and interpreting research. With our selection of search terms, we identified 369 publications investigating one of the four constructs, of which 28 use physiological data. Analysis of the 28 studies shows a tendency towards triangulating physiological with other types of data, which reflects the complexity of the investigated tasks and constructs. Moreover, there seems to be an effort to increase sample size, which is an important step towards more robust results in quantitative research in the field.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-12-11T11:27:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-12-11T11:27:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1075/cogls.00084.gie</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1075/cogls.00084.gie</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23697</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2213-8722</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2213-8730</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Cognitive Linguistic Studies</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>John Benjamins</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13851</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-26T10:58:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Passing and passing on in the digital world : issues and solutions for the digital estate</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brucker-Kley, Elke</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Keller, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pärli, Kurt</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pedron, Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schweizer, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Studer, Melanie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wohland, Pia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Digital inheritance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Digital estate planning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Digital legacy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mortality rates</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>What happens to the large volume of information on social media and other Internet platforms after our death? Even while alive it is extremely difficult for anyone to control the storage and dissemination of personal data on the Internet. How and why should we therefore try to make arrangements regarding what happens to this data when we pass away? Our next of kin do not usually know much about our various online activities, nor do they have access to the passwords necessary to deactivate profiles and delete or move information. At the same time, platform providers follow different practices, and their terms and conditions vary considerably. This paper summarizes the results of an interdisciplinary research project1 aimed at clarifying the many open questions there are in connection with this topic and proposes an extended perspective on how the many facets of this subject might be approached.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-12-13T15:47:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-13T15:47:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://www.iadisportal.org/ijwi/papers/2013112103.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13851</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-972-8939-82-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1645-7641</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the IADIS International Conference on e-Society 2013</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>IADIS International Conference on e-Society 2013, Lisbon, Portugal, 13-16 March 2013</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>IADIS International Journal on WWW/Internet</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>IADIS</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8913</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T13:39:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>20 years of surface ozone measurements at El Tololo, Chile (2200 m asl)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Anet, Julien Gérard</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Emmenegger, Lukas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Steinbacher, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Buchmann, Brigitte</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>551: Geologie und Hydrologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>PICO presentation (EGU2016-17820), held on Tuesday, 19 April 2016 (AS3.12)</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-08T08:47:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-08T08:47:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-04-19</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU2016/EGU2016-17820.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8913</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Geophysical Research Abstracts</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>EGU General Assembly 2016, Vienna, Austria, 17–22 April 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13475</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-04T12:56:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The whole picture : integrating site and network dimensions in site roles</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Scherrer, Maike</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Deflorin, Patricia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Thomas, Simone</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fischl, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Manufacturing network</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Network</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Operation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Picture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Site classification framework</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Site role</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Dimension</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.1: Organisation und Finanzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In this chapter, we develop a site classification framework that combines manufacturing site advantages with manufacturing  network-level targets. This framework is the  first step for a company-specific site role portfolio. The framework helps to visualise site strengths and weaknesses from a capability- and knowledge-based perspective. Further, it highlights the site’s contribution to the network  targets and combines site- and network-level dimensions. To develop the site classification framework, we extend  Ferdows’ (1997) introduced dimensions of location advantages and competences with the interconnection  of  sites from a knowledge-based view.  We use a single case  study to refine the theoretically derived framework. We add to existing theory because we apply a multi-level perspective and derive methods to measure a sites contribution to the network. In addition, we provide global site managers with a helpful visualisation tool.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-12-04T13:46:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-04T13:46:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4471-5646-8_2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-1-4471-5646-8_2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13475</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13475</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13475</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-4471-5645-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-4471-5646-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>International operations networks</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6210</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-13T08:58:45Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Breaking the wall of antiquanted patient catering : pitch</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Züger, Gabriela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>640: Hauswirtschaft und Familienleben</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-29T13:52:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-29T13:52:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6210</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6210</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6210</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Falling Walls Lab 2016, Zürich, 21. September 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11650</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-07-01T13:50:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Clinical Assessment von Hebammen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Eggenschwiler, Ruth Esther</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Klinisches Assessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-10-11T12:19:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-11T12:19:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11650</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11650</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11650</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1422-4526</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1662-5862</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Hebamme.ch</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schweizerischer Hebammenverband</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3368</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T09:11:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Positionspapier Mental Health bei Kindern und Jugendlichen : neuere Forschungsergebnisse aus Epidemiologie und Therapie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>von Wyl, Agnes</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616.89: Psychische Störungen, klinische Psychologie und Psychiatrie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-01T09:44:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-01T09:44:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-08-19</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3368</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3368</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3368</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>5. Internationale Konferenz zu Familien und Kindern von psychisch belasteten Eltern, Basel, 17-19 August 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5113</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-07T13:20:04Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>COLING 2004: Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on Computational Linguistics</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Yuste, Elia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jekat, Susanne Johanna</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pantli, Anna-Katharina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Massey, Gary</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Computerlinguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Datenbank</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Terminologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>CAT</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>410.285: Computerlinguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T13:47:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-11T13:47:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Proceedings</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5113</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5113</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5113</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:1-932432-48-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>2nd International Workshop on Language Resources for Translation Work, Research and Training, 20th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING), Geneva, Switzerland, 23-27 August 2004</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>1398 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4389</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T10:33:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Flow-time estimation in dynamic job shops with priority scheduling using a hybrid modelling approach</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sigrist, Jörg</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Heitz, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Industrial engineering</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Planning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Production</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>338: Produktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>A new approach for due date assignment in dynamic job shops with priority scheduling is presented. The future temporal development of the production system, eventually determining the flow-time of a job, is governed by both the processing of the jobs already present in the system as well as the processing of future arriving jobs. We combine a simulation-like approach for the already known jobs with a stochastic model describing the influence of future arriving jobs. The resulting model is a hybrid system dynamics model that can be solved numerically, leading to estimates for the flow-time of all available jobs.&#13;
In a simulation study, we compare the new approach with other popular methods known in literature. Our results indicate that the new method significantly outperforms all other studied methods in terms of accuracy of the estimates, in most cases by at least a factor of two. Furthermore, the effect of priority scheduling can be modelled correctly, yielding good estimates for jobs of different priorities.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T09:45:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T09:45:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1896</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1896</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4389</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4389</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4389</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>MITIP 2008 : proceedings 10th international conference on the modern information technology in the innovation processes of the industrial enterprises</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>MITIP 2008, 10th International Conference on the Modern Information Technology in the Innovation Processes of the Industrial Enterprises, Prague, Czech Republic, 12-14 November 2008</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>University of West Bohemia</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20970</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-06-03T08:20:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The effects of investigative sanctioning systems on wrongdoing, reporting, and helping : a multiparty perspective</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Chui, Celia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Grieder, Manuel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Behavioral ethics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>False accusation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Internal reporting</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Moral judgment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.402: Interne Organisation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Over the past two decades, organizations have established sanctioning systems as an important component of their ethical infrastructures to detect and punish wrongdoing. However, empirical knowledge about the overall effectiveness of such systems remains limited. Existing studies have mostly adopted a single-party perspective even though many wrongdoing situations involve dynamic multiparty interactions between actors, recipients, and observers of wrongdoing. Moreover, most existing research has emphasized an economic perspective—that sanctioning systems only affect behavior because of economic considerations while crowding out ethical ones. In this research, we develop a moral and normative perspective of sanctioning systems. Using a novel experimental game design, our study focuses on the investigative dimension of sanctioning systems to examine their psychological and behavioral effects in actor–recipient–observer wrongdoing interactions. Findings reveal that investigative sanctioning systems influence wrongdoing, reporting, and helping behaviors as well as alter ethical and normative considerations, such that as systems become stronger, wrongdoing behaviors are judged as more unethical and perceived as less typical than when weaker systems are in place. These moral judgments and norm perceptions mediate the effect of investigative sanctioning system strength on wrongdoing behavior. Our research extends previous empirical and theoretical work on sanctioning systems by applying a more holistic perspective and by demonstrating that highly effective systems can serve as important behavioral guides because they activate and alter moral and normative considerations about wrongdoing.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-12-03T10:55:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-12-03T10:55:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-04-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1287/orsc.2019.1340</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1287/orsc.2019.1340</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20970</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20970</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20970</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1047-7039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1526-5455</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Organization Science</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Institute for Operations Research and the Management Sciences</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14193</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-26T06:25:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Früherkennung von axialer Spondyloarthritis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Niedermann Schneider, Karin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tschupp, Katrin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Bechterew</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Axiale Spondyloarthritis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616.7: Krankheiten des Bewegungsapparates und Orthopädie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In der Schweiz verstreichen nach den ersten Symptomen durchschnittlich drei Jahre, bis eine axiale Spondyloarthritis (M. Bechterew) erkannt wird. PhysiotherapeutInnen können mit einem sorgfältigen Clinical Reasoning zur Früherkennung beitragen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-01-04T15:28:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-04T15:28:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14193</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14193</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14193</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1660-5209</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Physioactive</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Physioswiss</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2550</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-22T12:56:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Low back pain risk factors associated with persistence, recurrence and delayed presentation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Melloh, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Elfering, Achim</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stanton, Tasha R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barz, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Aghayev, Emin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Röder, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Theis, Jean-Claude</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Back pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Prognosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Occupational</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Inception cohort</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Risk factors</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Resources</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>617.5: Orthopädische Chirurgie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-02-01T13:20:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-01T13:20:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1633</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.3233/BMR-130445</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1633</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.3233/BMR-130445</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2550</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2550</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2550</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1053-8127</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of Back and Musculoskeletal Rehabilitation</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>IOS Press</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2700</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-16T13:48:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Mechanical catalysis on the centimetre scale</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Miyashita, Shuhei</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Audretsch, Christof</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nagy, Zoltán</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Füchslin, Rudolf Marcel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pfeifer, Rolf</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Magnetic catalysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Enzyme</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Inhibitor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Conformation change</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Autocatalysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Reaction phase</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>540: Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>572: Biochemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Enzymes play important roles in catalysing biochemical transaction paths, acting as logical machines through the morphology of the processes. A key challenge in elucidating the nature of these systems, and for engineering manufacturing methods inspired by biochemical reactions, is to attain a comprehensive understanding of the stereochemical ground rules of enzymatic reactions. Here, we present a model of catalysis that can be performed magnetically by centimetre-sized passive floating units. The designed system, which is equipped with permanent magnets only, passively obeys the local causalities imposed by magnetic interactions, albeit it shows a spatial behaviour and an energy profile analogous to those of biochemical enzymes. In this process, the enzyme units trigger physical conformation changes of the target by levelling out the magnetic potential barrier (activation potential) to a funnel type and, thus, induce cascading conformation changes of the targeted substrate units reacting in parallel. The inhibitor units, conversely, suppress such changes by increasing the potential. Because the model is purely mechanical and established on a physics basis in the absence of turbulence, each performance can be explained by the morphology of the unit, extending the definition of catalysis to systems of alternative scales.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-08T10:39:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-08T10:39:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1651</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1098/rsif.2014.1271</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1651</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1098/rsif.2014.1271</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2700</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2700</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2700</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1742-5689</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of the Royal Society Interface</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>The Royal Society</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5493</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T09:11:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Applications of PTR-ToF-MS on coffee</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Yeretzian, Chahan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gloess, Alexia N.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wieland, Flurin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zurfluh, Barbara</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Roasting</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Coffee</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>On-line</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>PTR-TOF-MS</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>663: Getränketechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Over the last decade, PTR-MS has made major contributions to the progress in coffee research. The research group Analytic and Analytical Technologies at the Zurich University of Applied Sciences in Wädenswil, has established over the last two years a strong research focus on the science of coffee. In this frame, PTR-ToF-MS is used in concert with complementary analytical technologies, to address applied research projects. &#13;
&#13;
Here we report on a series of on-going projects, where PTR-ToF-MS plays a significant role. We outline how PTR-ToF-MS data are being integrated into extensive analytical studies, to achieve a more comprehensive understanding of the subject under study. This includes (i) fundamental investigations on the temperature dependence of partition coefficients of volatile flavor compounds (ii) on-line process monitoring and (iii) the development of a predictive model for coffee sensory profiles.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-23T14:35:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-23T14:35:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5493</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5493</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5493</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-902719-88-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Contributions : 5th International Conference on Proton Transfer Reaction Mass Spectrometry and ist Applications</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>5th International Conference on Proton Transfer Reaction Mass Spectrometry and ist Applications, Obergurgl, Austria, 26 January - 2 February 2011</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Innsbruck University Press</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23554</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-22T12:57:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Collaboration on training : industry and academia</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Massey, Gary</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Perez, Emilia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mion, Enrico Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferraresi, Adriano</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gene, Viveta</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Translator education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Translator training</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Translation teacher competence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Professional translation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Language industry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Online event with panel presentations and follow-up discussions.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>This panel presents and discusses selected examples of and best practices for collaboration projects between industry and academia partners. What skill profiles are most language service providers looking for? The panel chair sets the scene by presenting recent findings in the field of MT post-editing training and proposing a set of best practices for professionals involved in post-editing activities. The panel members then present aspects of competences and profiles in the workplace, new translation industry roles and  training gaps, the training of students and of pofessional translators, and becoming a trainer.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-11-22T12:57:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-22T12:57:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://ec.europa.eu/info/events/2021TEF_en</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23554</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Translating Europe Forum 2021: Collaboration in Times of Automation, Brussels (online), 3-5 November 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24250</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-18T04:03:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1315</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1463</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Winterfütterung des Rotmilans : Zusammenhang zwischen dem Auftreten und der Winterfütterung des Rotmilans (Milvus milvus) in Wädenswil und Umgebung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sahli, Roland</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Rotmilan</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schweiz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Milvus milvus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Greifvogel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Winterfütterung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vogelzählung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wädenswil</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schönenberg</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Zürich</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>590: Tiere (Zoologie)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Der Bestand von Rotmilanen (Milvus milvus) hat in der Schweiz während den letzten Jahren stark zugenommen. In anderen Ländern wie Deutschland, Frankreich und Spanien sind die Bestände gleichgeblieben oder haben sogar abgenommen. Die Gründe für die Zunahme sind nicht zweifelsfrei geklärt. Jagdverbote und eine Einschränkung von schädlichen Pestiziden haben den Beständen sicherlich geholfen. Der Rotmilan ist ein Kurzstreckenzieher und überwintert normalerweise auf der Iberischen Halbinsel und Südfrankreich. In den letzten Jahren überwintern aber immer mehr Tiere in ihrem Brutgebiet, so auch in der Region Wädenswil im Kanton Zürich. Möglicherweise auf Grund von Fütterungen durch Menschen und den zunehmenden schneefreien Wintern, müssen sie nicht ziehen. Die Frage stellt sich, ob es einen Zusammenhang zwischen den Vorkommen des Rotmilans und den Fütterungen in Wädenswil gibt.&#13;
Mit einer wöchentlichen extensiven Zählung wurde ermittelt, dass über den Herbst/Winter 2018 sich durchschnittlich 16 Rotmilane pro Begehung im Untersuchungsgebiet befinden. Im November erreichte die Zählung Spitzen von bis zu 68 Tieren, wobei Doppelzählungen nicht ausgeschlossen sind. Mittels intensiver Zählung wurde das Aktivitätsmuster von einzelnen Tieren beobachtet. Es stellte sich heraus, dass Rotmilane zwei Drittel der Beobachtungszeit mit Ruhen verbringen. Mit einer Umfrage in der lokalen Bevölkerung wurde untersucht, wo die Rotmilane gefüttert werden. In der Nähe dieser Fütterungsstandorte haben sich die Tiere auf Schlafbäumen zusammengefunden. Zu guter Letzt wurde ein Anfütterungsversuch durchgeführt. Dabei wurde Fleisch aus ausgelegt und die Zeit gemessen, bis der erste Rotmilan das Futter entdeckte. Es dauerte zwei Stunden, bis ein Rotmilan vom Fleisch frass, nachdem schon ein Mäusebussard (Buteo buteo) gefressen hatte.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>The population of red kites (Milvus milvus) in Switzerland has increased sharply in recent years. In other countries, such as Germany, France and Spain, populations have remained stable or even decreased. The reasons for the increase are not clear. Hunting bans and restrictions on harmful pesticides have certainly helped the populations. The red kite is a shortdistance migrant and usually hibernates on the Iberian Peninsula and in southern France. In recent years, however, more and more animals have hibernated in their breeding area, including in the region of Wädenswil of Canton Zurich. Possibly due to feeding by humans and the increasing snow-free winters, they do not have to migrate. The question arises as to whether there is a connection between the occurrence of the red kite and feeding in Wädenswil.&#13;
An extensive weekly census showed that an average of 16 red kites were present in the study area over the autumn/winter of 2018. In November the census reached peaks of up to 68 animals, but double censuses are not excluded. The activity pattern of individual animals was observed by means of intensive censuses. It turned out that red kites spend two thirds of the observation time resting. A survey of the local population investigated where the red kites were fed. Near these feeding sites the animals gathered on sleeping trees. Last but not least, a feeding experiment was carried out. Meat was laid out and the time measured until the first red kite discovered the food. It took two hours for a red kite to eat from the meat after a buzzard (Buteo buteo) had eaten.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-02-17T10:46:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-02-17T10:46:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-24250</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-24250</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24250</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24250</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24250</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>39 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23257</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-10-06T12:29:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Proceedings of the Swiss Text Analytics Conference 2021</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Benites, Fernando</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tuggener, Don</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hürlimann, Manuela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cieliebak, Mark</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vogel, Manfred</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Text analytics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Natural language processing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Computational linguistics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>006: Spezielle Computerverfahren</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>410.285: Computerlinguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>SwissText is an annual conference that brings together text analytics experts from industry and academia. It is organised by the Swiss Association for Natural Language Processing (SwissNLP) in collaboration with the University of Applied Sciences and Arts Northwestern Switzerland (FHNW) as well as the Zurich University of Applied Sciences (ZHAW) and the data innovation alliance. SwissText 2021 was part of the Networking Event Series – Natural Language Processing funded by InnoSuisse, the Swiss Innovation Agency. It is supported by more than 10 universities and scientific associations.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-10-06T12:29:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-10-06T12:29:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-09-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Proceedings</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2957/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23257</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1613-0073</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Swiss Text Analytics Conference – SwissText 2021, Online, 14-16 June 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>CEUR Workshop Proceedings</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9209</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-28T09:38:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Nachfolgeregelung in Familienunternehmen : mit Assessments richtig vorbereiten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Siano, Roberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schmücker, Janine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Assessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nachfolgeregelung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-08-17T13:03:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-17T13:03:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9209</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9209</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9209</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0473-2839</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Organisator</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Galledia</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3869</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T14:34:37Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Zustandsregler in Gebäudeleitsystemen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Glattfelder, A. H.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Büchi, Roland</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Farruggio, David</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Regelungstechnik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Beobachter</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Modellierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kalman-Filter</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>620: Ingenieurwesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Das hier vorgestellte Verfahren berechnet aus der in einem Raum gemessenen Lufttemperatur mit Hilfe eines Beobachters die Wandtemperaturen. Mit Klimaanlagen die Wandtemperaturen zu regeln, ist deshalb vorteilhaft, weil über 90% der Wärmeenergie in den Wänden gespeichert ist.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-03-15T09:28:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-15T09:28:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1994</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3869</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3869</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3869</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>SGA Bulletin</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schweizerische Gesellschaft für Automatik</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2370</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-18T09:41:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Caution and compliance in medical encounters : non-interpretation of hedges and phatic tokens</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Albl-Mikasa, Michaela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Glatz, Elisabeth</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hofer, Gertrud</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sleptsova, Marina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Cultural expressions</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hedges</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Phatic tokens</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Medical interpreting</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The paper is based on the Swiss research project ‘Interpreting in Medical Settings: Roles, Requirements and Responsibility’, which was supported by a grant of the Swiss Commission for Technology and Innovation (KTI) and carried out by an interdisciplinary team comprising medical specialists from the University Hospital of Basel (Marina Sleptsova and colleagues) and interpreting studies/applied linguistics researchers from the Zurich University of Applied Sciences (ZHAW) (Gertrud Hofer and colleagues). It explores 12 transcribed video-taped interpreted authentic conversations between German speaking doctors/medical staff and patients of Turkish or Albanian origin. The analysis finds that culture-specific expressions produced by the patients occur rarely and do not pose any interpreting problems. By contrast, phatic tokens and hedges play an important role in medical personnel’s presentation of their interactional, trust building, diagnostic and therapeutic intentions. Although essential elements in communication in that they are geared at building patients’ compliance and establishing doctors’ safeguards, these expressions are rarely or inconsistently rendered by the interpreters. It is argued that, while medical interpreters may have plausible reasons not to render these expressions, they would still need to be made aware of the significance of such pragmatic aspects of communication in training courses and/or pre-encounter briefings. More generally, empirical research – similar to that on questioning style and questioning techniques – should focus more on the exploration of discourse markers, meta-discourse comments and rapport-building expressions of different types of utterance and discourse practices in healthcare interpreting settings.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-01-31T13:17:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-31T13:17:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2370</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2370</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2370</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1836-9324</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Translation &amp; Interpreting</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>University of Western Sydney</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21019</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-22T12:56:14Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Digital maternal health booklets : do they help reaching migrant populations</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zysset, Annina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dratva, Julia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>302.23: Medien</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610: Medizin und Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-12-11T13:50:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-12-11T13:50:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-10-13</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21019</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21019</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21019</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>WCPH2020 : 16th World Congress in Public Health : Public health for the future of humanity, online, 12-16 October 2020</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23439</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-10T08:14:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>"Wie wir das sehen" - die Sichtweise fremdplatzierter Kinder als Ausgangspunkt für Qualitätsentwicklung : eine Studie zur Partizipation im stationären Setting</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Keller, Samuel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rohrbach, Julia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Heimerziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sichtweise junger Menschen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Beteiligung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Partizipation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kinder- und Jugendhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.7: Jugendhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Panel: Perspektiven junger Menschen auf Partizipation in der stationären Kinder- und Jugendhilfe</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-11-10T08:14:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-10T08:14:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-04-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23439</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23439</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23439</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Europäische Gesellschaft(en) zwischen Kohäsion und Spaltung - Trinationale Tagung der DGSA, OGSA und SGSA, Online, 23.-24. April 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8001</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-20T06:25:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Onlinejournalismus zwischen Emanzipation und Reproduktion</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wyss, Vinzenz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Onlinejournalismus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>070: Nachrichtenmedien, Journalismus und Verlagswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-07-12T14:46:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-12T14:46:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3-03777-034-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Informationsgesellschaft Schweiz</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Seismo</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17511</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-09T08:55:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ausdrücke in Anführungszeichen als Verfestigungen : Überlegungen zu quantitativen und qualitativen Aspekten distanzierenden Sprachgebrauches</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dreesen, Philipp</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Language ideology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sprachideologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Postcolonial</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Metasprache</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Korpuslinguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Diskurslinguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>401.4: Lexikologie und Terminologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Sonderheft: Sprachliche Verfestigungen und sprachlich Verfestigtes</dc:description>
          <dc:description>This study raises the question of whether formulaic expressions always consist of at least two words. It is argued that pragmatics should also consider paraverbal graphematical signs. Some present German expressions are emphased in quotation marks for political and possibly critical reasons (e. g. „Drittes Reich“, „zivilisiert“). They form their own kind of formulaicity, because it is not quotation. The identification of quotations is only one function of quotation marks. Other meta-pragmatic functions of quotation marks are – if at all – only contextual and often not distinct. This includes, for example, the so-called „application with reservation“ and the „term with reservation“, as examples from the German colonial period show (e. g. „wild“, „dunkler Welttheil“). For this reason, corpus-based analyses of these formulaic expressions will also require contextual interpretations in the future.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-07-17T09:19:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-07-17T09:19:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-5538</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.13092/lo.96.5532</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-5538</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.13092/lo.96.5532</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1615-3014</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Linguistik Online</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Bern Open Publishing</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1999</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T07:20:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>“What's the story?” : career construction in theory and practice</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schreiber, Marc</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schindler, Nicola</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>158: Angewandte Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>331: Arbeitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-01-15T15:09:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-15T15:09:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1999</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1999</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1999</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>IAEVG International Conference 2015, International Association for Educational and Vocational Guidance IAEVG, Tsukuba, Japan, 18-21 September 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7607</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T11:44:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Seven challenges to media development and FoMe</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Spurk, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Journalism</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Media development</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Development cooperation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>070: Nachrichtenmedien, Journalismus und Verlagswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-07-05T14:05:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-05T14:05:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7607</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7607</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7607</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Jubiläumsveranstaltung 10 Jahre Forum Medien und Entwicklung: «Challenges ahead: new requirements on impact, the digital agenda and the post 2015 framework», Bonn, 5 November 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1423</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T11:20:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1075</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1074</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1076</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>A visual imprint of moving air : methods, models, and media in architectural sound photography, ca. 1930</dc:title>
          <dc:title>A visual imprint of moving air</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fischer, Sabine von</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Architecture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sound</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Photography</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Models</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Architectural Science</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Architectural Acoustics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>720: Architektur</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Prompted by an archival finding from the laboratory of Franz Max Osswald, Switzerland's first academic expert in applied acoustics, Sabine von Fischer explores the schlieren technique for photographing sound in sectional models. A Visual Imprint of Moving Air: Methods, Models, and Media in Architectural Sound Photography, ca. 1930 examines how images were used to communicate findings in the emerging discipline of architectural acoustics. In Osswald's persistent experiments in visualizing the invisible phenomena of sound, the social, the technical, and the aesthetic were inseparable. Using photography, Osswald adhered to the paradigm of mechanical objectivity, yet his visual experimenting with phenomena of spatial sound possibly demonstrates an awareness that the senses cannot be excluded from scientific methods. The shadows of moving air in the sound photographs make claims toward their scientific authority, their aesthetic appeal, and their social function as expert tools.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2017-11-08T09:28:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-11-08T09:28:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1362</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1525/jsah.2017.76.3.326</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1362</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1525/jsah.2017.76.3.326</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1423</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1423</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1423</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0037-9808</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2150-5926</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>University of California Press</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10234</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T11:47:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>L'identità e la comunicazione : due concetti chiave per la Chiesa armeno-cattolica</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Suvada, Adrienne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Genocidio</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Armenia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Identità</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Comunicazione</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>200: Religion</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>L’identità e la comunicazione sono due concetti fondamentali per ogni istituzione. Il caso della Chiesa armeno-cattolica mostra l’esempio di un’identità molto forte e da un aiuto di come utilizzare la comunicazione per mantenere l’unità. La comunicazione è un elemento integrativo per questa chiesa, nonostante tutte le difficoltà. Può contribuire a rendere più efficace la sua azione. Le radici e l’identità, come anche l’unità, sono aspetti fondamentali e la comunicazione può contribuire ad integrare i diversi gruppi della Chiesa armeno-cattolica. La comunicazione deve avere un ruolo attivo nella Chiesa armeno-cattolica. In tal modo si riesce a consolidare i propri punti di forza basandosi sull’identità e si potrebbe diventare un modello anche per le altre Chiese orientali.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-05T14:58:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-05T14:58:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10234</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10234</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10234</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0009-7632</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>it</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Città di Vita</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Città di vita</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6400</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T11:47:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>MUMMY in the field</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Balfanz, Dirk</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tazari, M. R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Windlinger Inversini, Lukas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Facility management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Informationsmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mobile Arbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.2: Facility Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Das Projekt MUMMY hat in 2005 eine Reihe von Feldtests durchlaufen, um die realen Auswirkungen des mobilen Informationsmanagement in den jeweiligen Geschäftsprozessen zu evaluieren. Die Ergebnisse dieser Feldtests im Bereich Facility Management werden in diesem Artikel zusammengefasst. Die Evaluation basiert auf Datenerhebungen während der Tests, sowie Interviews mit Benutzern und zuständigen Prozess-Managern.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-01T09:53:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-01T09:53:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6400</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6400</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6400</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0936-2770</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2199-9880</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Computer Graphics Topics</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>INI-GraphicsNet</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8220</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T11:57:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Der Nordische Streifenfarn auf Findlingen : eine Flaggschiffart für die Findlingsflora im Mittelland und Jura</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hepenstrick, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>580: Pflanzen (Botanik)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Im Mittelland und Jura kommt der Nordische Streifenfarn ausschliesslich auf silikatischen Findlingen vor. Das wechselvolle Schicksal dieser bedrohten Vorkommen ist geprägt von Bauwirtschaft, Botanikern und Bouldern. Wer will kann auf Schatzsuche gehen und historische Fundorte vom Nordischen Streifenfarn auf Findlingen wieder entdecken.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-17T13:49:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-17T13:49:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2031</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2031</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Unr.intern</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15067</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:30:32Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Market survey on the potential and market acceptance of an electronic platform to facilitate (re)insurance administration : the "Rüschlikon Initiative"</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schmeiser, Hato</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zeier Röschmann, Angela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Process Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Administration</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Reinsurance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Insurance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332.38: Versicherungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-02-06T08:58:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-06T08:58:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://www.ivw.unisg.ch/_/media/internet/content/dateien/instituteundcenters/ivw/studien/rueschlikon_initiative_marketsurvey.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15067</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>31 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Universität St.Gallen</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4197</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T10:17:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>ECROPOLIS : Transparency in sensory properties and consumer expectations in organic food</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Barylko-Pikielna, Nina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bendini, Alessandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bongartz, Annette</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Buchecker, Kirsten</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cezanne, Marie-Louise</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gallina Toschi, Tullia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kostyra, Eliza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kremer, Stefanie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kretzschmar-Rüger, Ursula</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Obermowe, Tim</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Reichl, Pascale</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Spiller, Achim</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Organic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sensory</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Consumer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sensorik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>664: Lebensmitteltechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-22T16:01:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-22T16:01:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4197</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4197</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4197</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>First International Conference on Organic Food Quality and Health Research, Prague, Czech Republic, 18-20 May 2011</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2465</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-25T07:10:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Zur Geschichte und Zukunft des Phantoms in der Hebammenausbildung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Loytved, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dörig, Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hammer, Kristin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Das geburtshilfliche Phantom dient bereits seit mehr als 300 Jahren der Ausbildung von Fachpersonen in der Geburthilfe (Dörig 2013). Seine Entwicklung wurde in einer Zeit des Notstands an lebenden «Lehrobjekten» vorangetrieben. In diesem Beitrag wird keine Chronologie der jeweiligen Phantome sowie ihrer Entwicklerinnen und Entwickler angestrebt, sondern untersucht, wie der Unterricht am geburtshilflichen Phantom ablief, und gefragt, welche Auswirkung die Übungen am Phantom auf die realen Gebärsituationen haben konnten. Daraus werden Fragen an den Unterricht heute und ein Ausblick auf die Zukunft entwickelt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-01T08:01:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-01T08:01:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4086</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4086</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2465</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2465</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2465</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1422-4526</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1662-5862</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Hebamme.ch</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Schweizerischer Hebammenverband</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1425</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-04-19T11:47:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Flächiges Queren in Ortszentren - langfristige Wirkung und Zweckmässigkeit</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ghielmetti, Marco</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Steiner, Rolf</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leitner, Jakob</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hackenfort, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Diener, Sarah</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Topp, Hartmut</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Deregulation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sicherheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Unfall</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fussgängerstreifen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>363: Umwelt- und Sicherheitsprobleme</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>620: Ingenieurwesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>711: Raumplanung (Städtebau)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Forschungsprojekt SVI 2011/023 im Auftrag der Schweizerischen Vereinigung der Verkehrsingenieure und Verkehrsexperten (SVI)</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2017-11-08T09:42:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-11-08T09:42:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1425</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1425</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1425</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Forschungsberichte SVI</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>193 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Bundesamt für Strassen</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19976</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:30:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Editorial : AI and financial technology</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Giudici, Paolo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hochreiter, Ronald</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Osterrieder, Jörg</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Papenbrock, Jochen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schwendner, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332: Finanzwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-04-30T08:57:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-04-30T08:57:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-11-15</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.3389/frai.2019.00025</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-19976</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.3389/frai.2019.00025</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-19976</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19976</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19976</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19976</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2624-8212</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Frontiers in Artificial Intelligence</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Frontiers Research Foundation</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2490</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T10:32:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Von der Wehemutter zur Hebamme</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Loytved, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fischer, C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-02-01T09:18:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-01T09:18:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2490</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2490</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2490</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Jubiläumssymposium: 250 Jahre Hebammenschule Heidelberg, Akademie für Gesundheitsberufe, Heidelberg, Deutschland, 24. September 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8935</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-12T11:48:14Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Exsolution and integration of nanosized SMART catalysts for next generation SOFC anodes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Burnat, Dariusz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Holzer, Lorenz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Franken, Tanja</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mai, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Heel, Andre</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Anodes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Perovskite</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Smart Material</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>SOFC</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>B1104</dc:description>
          <dc:description>La-doped strontium titanate (LST) materials are widely recognized among other alternative anodes as good electronic conductors with high tolerance to redox cycles, but with insufficient catalytic activity. However, doping of LST with quasi-stable metal ions (e.g. Ni, Co) allows a selective exsolution of these metals from the bulk onto the materials surface and thus increasing the catalytic activity. &#13;
Previously we have demonstrated our SMART material concept with selfregeneration effect, in which nano-sized nickel catalyst is repeatedly exsolved from and incorporated back into the La0.2.Sr0.7Ti0.95Ni0.05O3-d (LSTN) perovskite host structure. Nickel nanoparticles are exsolved from LST at SOFC anode conditions and nickel is reincorporated at high pO2, during a redox cycle. This turns redox cycles - the weakness of conventional Ni/YSZ anodes - into an advantage and regenerates the material. The authors present recent advances of the SMART material catalysts based on LSTN. We demonstrate that upon harsh heat treatment (T = 1200°C) depending on the location and site at least three types of nickel particles being generated LSTN: a) fine particles with presumably high catalytic activity (dp &lt; 15 nm) b) large particles located on grain facets up to 150 nm c) large particles located on grain boundaries above 100 nm. Also at 1200°C a significant growth of nickel crystallites can be observed, which is however reversed by redox cycling at T = 900°C. Even large particles (dp &gt;150 nm), generated on the facets of grains are reversibly incorporated into the LSTN host matrix (Fig. 1), while those large ones located at the grain boundaries underwent an oxidation to NiO. Temperature programmed reduction has proven unchanged REDOX reversibility of LSTN materials upon 9 redox cycles a temperature of 900°C, suggesting catalytic reversibility.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-09T12:45:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-09T12:45:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8935</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8935</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8935</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-905592-23-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of 13th European SOFC &amp; SOE Forum 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>13th European SOFC &amp; SOE Forum 2018, Lucerne, 3-6 July 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3150</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:00:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Intervertebral disc regeneration : small and large scale systems</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bono, Epifania</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mauth, Corinna</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Franscini, Nicola</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Durner, Roland</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Boos, Norbert</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Graf-Hausner, Ursula</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Regeneration</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Disc</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Intervertebal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610: Medizin und Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Objectives: The intervertebral disc (IVD) degeneration is an aberrant cell-mediated response to progressive structural failure. One of the major causes of the back pain, the IVD degeneration affects about 60% of the population, increasing the costs of the health system. Although the problem of disc degeneration has been approached from many sides, from orthopaedic surgery to molecular biology, it remains unsolved. The present study suggests a tissue engineering alternative to the current surgical therapies, focusing its attention on the regeneration of the nucleus pulposus and on the standardization of its in vitro basic methods. The first objective of this investigation is to analyze the potentiality of an injectable biomaterial combination as carrier for autologus disc cells in the IVD augmentation process. Moreover, in order to reduce the costs of tissue engineering, the second objective of this study regards the establishment of an automated system able to isolate, propagate and characterize in large scale human primary disc cells.&#13;
&#13;
Methods: Disc-like cells were isolated by enzymatic digestion from intervertebral disc tissue, harvested during discectomy, and expanded in monolayer cultures before seeding onto a three dimensional system. The cells were seeded onto a macroporous scaffold and subsequently encapsulated into a hydrogel. The viability of cells as well as their capability to proliferate, migrate into the biomaterial combination and synthesize the extracellular matrix was detected by cell and biochemical assays at different culture time points. Moreover, disc cells were genotypically characterized analysing by RT-PCR the expression pattern of specific genes. The disc cell isolation and the monolayer cultures procedures were furthermore performed with the automated liquid handling robot supplied from Tecan® (Tecan® freedom EVO®).&#13;
&#13;
Results: Disc-like cells were able to adhere and proliferate onto the three dimensional system showing a homogenous distribution into the surrounding hydrogel structure after few days of culture. Cells synthesized the required extracellular matrix and re-acquired their original genotypic features indicating their redifferentiation in vitro.&#13;
The automated isolation of primary disc-like cells from human biopsies showed comparable results to the manual one. The isolated cells compared for the number, viability and morphology with the manual processing. Furthermore, cells seeded and maintained in bidimensional culture by the robot revealed the same morphology and growth rate of manually treated cells.&#13;
&#13;
Conclusions: This study indicates that the three dimensional developed structure can be a valid system for the treatment of early-stages IVD degeneration. Moreover, the current results obtained with the EVO® robot suggests its feasibility in the automated isolation of disc cells from human biopsy and its propagation in large scale for a future clinical application.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T11:17:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T11:17:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3150</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3150</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3150</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>12th Annual Seminar &amp; Meeting - Ceramics, Cells and Tissues, Faenza, Italy, 1 May 2009</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7001</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-21T12:56:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Der Bitcoin-/Bitcoin-Cash-Hardfork : die auftragsrechtliche Ablieferungspflicht bei Kryptowährungs-Dienstleistungen im Lichte der bundesgerichtlichen Rechtsprechung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jacquemart, Nicolas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meyer, Stephan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>343: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Sachen-, Finanz-, Steuer- und Wirtschaftsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-18T08:27:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-18T08:27:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1661-7673</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Gesellschafts- und Kapitalmarktrecht</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Dike</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12961</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T12:30:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Bewertung von Kooperationen zwischen Staat und Privaten in der staatstheoretischen Diskussion der Schweiz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Abegg, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Public private partnership</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>350: Öffentliche Verwaltung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-11-16T15:18:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-16T15:18:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5771/9783845229959-177</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.5771/9783845229959-177</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12961</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12961</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12961</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-8329-6358-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Wandel der Staatlichkeit und wieder zurück? : die Einbeziehung Privater in die Erfüllung öffentlicher Aufgaben (Public Private Partnership) in/nach der Weltwirtschaftskrise</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Public Private Partnership, Speyer, Deutschland, 16.-20. September 2009</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Verwaltungsressourcen und Verwaltungsstrukturen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Nomos</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8148</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-24T10:53:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Caprifoliaceae : Geissblattgewächse</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Honetschläger, Nils</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vögeli, Moritz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Pflanzenkenntnis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>580: Pflanzen (Botanik)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-07-16T12:31:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-16T12:31:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8148</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8148</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8148</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Schweizer Staudengärten</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>120 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Gesellschaft Schweizer Staudenfreunde</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16644</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-14T13:37:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Matura exam : formal responsibilities and quality</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller Werder, Claude</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>378: Hochschulbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-04-15T13:39:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-15T13:39:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16644</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16644</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16644</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Education Reform Initiative of South Eastern Europe (ERI SEE) Workshop, Sofia, Bulgaria, 11-12 Dezember 2008</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18384</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-11T13:45:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kommentar zu Art. 52 ZGB SchlT</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kley, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Seferovic, Goran</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-10-11T13:45:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-10-11T13:45:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18384</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18384</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18384</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-280-07353-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>ZGB : Kommentar : Schweizerisches Zivilgesetzbuch</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Orell Füssli Kommentar</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Orell Füssli</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17060</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-05-09T14:20:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kommentar zu Art. 698 OR</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tanner, Brigitte</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Gesellschaftsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Aktienrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-05-09T14:20:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-05-09T14:20:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7255-7214-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Zürcher Kommentar; Band Obligationenrecht. Art. 698-726 und 731b OR : die Aktiengesellschaft. Generalversammlung und Verwaltungsrat. Mängel in der Organisation</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schulthess</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20921</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-11-26T14:55:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Children at risk : vulnerability and well-being from an international perspective</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tausendfreund, Tim</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brink, Ida Ofelia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gabriel, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Kindeswohl</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kinderwelten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kinderrechte</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vulnerabilität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Well-Being</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Children's Worlds</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Children's rights</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vulnerability</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>305: Personengruppen (Alter, Herkunft, Geschlecht, Einkommen)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-11-26T14:55:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-11-26T14:55:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-11-17</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://youtu.be/iK1VGwCD9Ro?t=1010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20921</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Children’s Worlds 2020, Webinar, 17 November 2020</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11582</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:39:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Explaining the energy performance gap in professionally managed buildings</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Janser, Marcel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Energy Performance Gap</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Real Estate Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Procurement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Business Models</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Behaviour Change</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333.79: Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-10-10T11:30:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-10T11:30:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the 5th European Conference on Behaviour and Energy Efficiency</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>5th European Conference on Behaviour and Energy Efficiency (BEHAVE 2018), Zurich, 5-7 September 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21110</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-14T15:27:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_20708</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_20926</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>TRANSFER, Ausgabe 1/2015</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>ZHAW Life Sciences and Facility Management</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>000: Allgemeines und Wissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-12-30T15:33:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-12-30T15:33:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Zeitschriftenheft</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-21110</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-21110</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21110</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21110</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21110</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15243 &amp;&amp; Haltbarkeit von Lebensmitteln simulieren</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5358 &amp;&amp; Innovative Fernerkundungslösungen im Umweltmonitoring</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20926</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>12 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5254</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T08:08:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Denkstimmung der Skepsis : ein Beschreibungsansatz zur Entstehung der Diskurslinguistik</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dreesen, Philipp</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Diskurs</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Linguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sprachwissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wissenschaftstheorie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wissenschaftssoziologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>000: Allgemeines und Wissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>401.4: Lexikologie und Terminologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Im Beitrag wird gezeigt, dass die Genese der germanistischen Diskurslinguistik in der Anfangsphase als Etablierung einer im Paris der 1960er Jahre initialisierten und später verstetigten Denkstimmung der Skepsis verstanden werden kann. Darunter wird v.a. das radikale Hinterfragen von bis dato akzeptierten Prämissen und Praktiken der Erkenntnisgewinnung verstanden. Elemente dieser Skepsis sind bis heute in der etablierten Diskurslinguistik nachweisbar. Der Fleck'sche Ausdruck der "Denkstimmung" eignet sich hier, diese Entwicklung zu erfassen und zu beschreiben.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T14:13:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T14:13:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5254</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5254</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5254</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-503-17747-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Denkstile in der deutschen Sprachwissenschaft : Bausteine einer Fachgeschichte aus dem Blickwinkel der Wissenschaftstheorie Ludwik Flecks</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Philologische Studien und Quellen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Erich Schmidt</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21434</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-28T09:49:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Art. 234</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Heinzmann, Michel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pasquier, Bruno</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>347: Zivilprozessrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-01-28T09:49:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-01-28T09:49:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21434</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21434</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21434</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7190-4150-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Petit commentaire CPC : Code de procédure civile</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Helbing &amp; Lichtenhahn</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4027</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-28T09:39:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Advanced Practice Nurse (APN) in einem geriatrischen Konsiliardienst</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Thoma, Martina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Händler-Schuster, Daniela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mahrer Imhof, Romy</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-19T09:39:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-19T09:39:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1024/1662-9027/a000062</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1024/1662-9027/a000062</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1662-9027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2235-4271</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>NOVAcura</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Hogrefe</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16374</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T11:47:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Directed evolution of carbon–hydrogen bond activating enzymes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Frey, Raphael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hayashi, Takahiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Buller, Rebecca</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>660.6: Biotechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>As industrial biocatalysis is maturing, access to enzymatic activities beyond chiral resolutions, asymmetric ketone reductions and reductive aminations is gradually becoming reality. Especially the utilization of carbon-hydrogen bond (C-H) activating enzymes is very attractive as they catalyze a variety of chemically extremely challenging transformations. Because of their intrinsic complexity, the use of these enzymes in manufacturing has been limited. However, recent advances in enzyme engineering and bioinformatics have led to activity improvements for native and non-native substrates, the introduction of new-to-nature chemistries and the identification of promising novel enzyme families. Looking forward, the use of automation and advanced computer algorithms will help to streamline the evolution process of C-H activating enzymes leading to more robust and active biocatalysts.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-03-28T13:25:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-28T13:25:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.copbio.2018.12.004</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.copbio.2018.12.004</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16374</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16374</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16374</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0958-1669</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1879-0429</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>30583278</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Current Opinion in Biotechnology</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14486</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-20T09:51:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Progressive multiple sequence alignment with indel evolution</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Maiolo, Massimo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zhang, Xiaolei</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gil, Manuel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Anisimova, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Dynamic programming</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Indel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Phylogeny</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Poisson process</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Probability</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sequence alignment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Algorithms</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Molecular evolution</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>INDEL mutation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>572: Biochemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Background: Sequence alignment is crucial in genomics studies. However, optimal multiple sequence alignment (MSA) is NP-hard. Thus, modern MSA methods employ progressive heuristics, breaking the problem into a series of pairwise alignments guided by a phylogeny. Changes between homologous characters are typically modelled by a Markov substitution model. In contrast, the dynamics of indels are not modelled explicitly, because the computation of the marginal likelihood under such models has exponential time complexity in the number of taxa. But the failure to model indel evolution may lead to artificially short alignments due to biased indel placement, inconsistent with phylogenetic relationship.

Results: Recently, the classical indel model TKF91 was modified to describe indel evolution on a phylogeny via a Poisson process, termed PIP. PIP allows to compute the joint marginal probability of an MSA and a tree in linear time. We present a new dynamic programming algorithm to align two MSAs –represented by the underlying homology paths– by full maximum likelihood under PIP in polynomial time, and apply it progressively along a guide tree. We have corroborated the correctness of our method by simulation, and compared it with competitive methods on an illustrative real dataset.

Conclusions: Our MSA method is the first polynomial time progressive aligner with a rigorous mathematical formulation of indel evolution. The new method infers phylogenetically meaningful gap patterns alternative to the popular PRANK, while producing alignments of similar length. Moreover, the inferred gap patterns agree with what was predicted qualitatively by previous studies. The algorithm is implemented in a standalone C++ program.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-01-22T14:31:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-22T14:31:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4775</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12859-018-2357-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4775</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1186/s12859-018-2357-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14486</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14486</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14486</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1471-2105</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>30241460</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>BMC Bioinformatics</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>BioMed Central</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7261</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T08:08:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Entwicklung im Waldgrenzökoton : Verjüngung der Bergföhre</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Krüsi, Bertil</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sieber, Pascal</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Forest Rejuvenation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pinus montana</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Timberline Ecotone</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Swiss National Park</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>580: Pflanzen (Botanik)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Während Jahrhunderten wurde die klimatisch bedingte, obere Grenze des Waldes durch die Beweidung mit Haustieren nach unten verschoben. Seit der Gründung des SNP vor rund 100 Jahren ist der Umkehrprozess im Gang: Der Wald dehnt sich wieder aus, in der Gründungszeit des SNP weitgehend ungestört, dann unter dem Einfluss steigender Rothirschzahlen und in den letzten Jahrzehnten unter dem Einfluss des Klimawandels. Allgemein wird angenommen, dass die Ausbreitung des Waldes durch die globale Erwärmung beschleunigt und durch den Rothirsch gebremst wird.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-25T14:12:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-25T14:12:01Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7261</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7261</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7261</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-258-07801-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Atlas des Schweizerischen Nationalparks : die ersten 100 Jahre</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Nationalpark-Forschung in der Schweiz</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Haupt</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6113</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T14:51:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Sustainable regional development in the Swiss alps with an indicator based certification procedure for label regions : the project FUNalpin</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carabias-Hütter, Vicente</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Renner, Erich</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Boesch, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Certification</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Regional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sustainable</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>338.927: Umweltökonomie und nachhaltige Entwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The intended main results will be regional policy recommendations, with the long-term objective of contributing to a sustainable development of alpine regions. Core element is outlining the concept of "Label region", both in the context of justification (i.e. reasoning about trends, aims and goals) and in the context of operation (i.e. establishing operational tools, like an indicator-based certification procedure). So far, through a sustainability goal analysis an adequate set of indicators for sustainable regional development has been set up.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-05-25T12:28:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-25T12:28:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6113</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6113</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6113</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>2nd International Young Scientist Conference, Interdisciplinary Mountain Research, Stelvio National Park, Italy, 29 September - 4 October 2004</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18168</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-05-25T06:36:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Change and stability in the media use of Swiss adolescents since 2012</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Suter, Lilian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Waller, Gregor</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bernath, Jael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Külling, Céline</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Willemse, Isabel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Süss, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Media use</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Adolescents</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Youth</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Leisure</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-09-12T09:01:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-09-12T09:01:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18168</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18168</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18168</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-96100-094-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the media psychology division : 11th conference of the media psychology division 2019, German Psychological Society</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>MediaPsych 19, Chemnitz, Germany, 4-6 September 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>University Press</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1996</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:53:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Handbuch Fragebogen zur Erfassung der beruflichen Interessen (ORVIS-R)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schreiber, Marc</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nüssli, Natalie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Spiegelberg, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>158: Angewandte Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>331: Arbeitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-01-15T15:06:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-15T15:06:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1539</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1539</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1996</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1996</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1996</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>34 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12589</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:01:04Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1075</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1074</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1076</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Architecture : a question of design technique</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schurk, Holger</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>720: Architektur</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-11-07T09:54:51Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-07T09:54:51Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12589</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12589</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12589</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:9782930301402</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the four EAAE-ENHSA subnetwork workshops on architectural theory, Hasselt (2006), Trondheim (2007), Lisbon (2008), Fribourg (2009)</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>EAAE-ENHSA Subnetwork Workshops on Architectural Theory, Hasselt (2006), Trondheim (2007), Lisbon (2008), Fribourg (2009)</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>European Association of Architectural Education (EAAE)</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20277</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-20T09:51:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>How (not) to measure bias in face recognition networks</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Glüge, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Amirian, Mohammadreza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Flumini, Dandolo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stadelmann, Thilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Deep learning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Convolutional neural network</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fairness</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>006: Spezielle Computerverfahren</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Within the last years Face Recognition (FR) systems have achieved human-like (or better) performance, leading to extensive deployment in large-scale practical settings. Yet, especially for sensible domains such as FR we expect algorithms to work equally well for everyone, regardless of somebody's age, gender, skin colour and/or origin. In this paper, we investigate a methodology to quantify the amount of bias in a trained Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) model for FR that is not only intuitively appealing, but also has already been used in the literature to argue for certain debiasing methods. It works by measuring the "blindness" of the model towards certain face characteristics in the embeddings of faces based on internal cluster validation measures. We conduct experiments on three openly available FR models to determine their bias regarding race, gender and age, and validate the computed scores by comparing their predictions against the actual drop in face recognition performance for minority cases. Interestingly, we could not link a crisp clustering in the embedding space to a strong bias in recognition rates|it is rather the opposite. We therefore offer arguments for the reasons behind this observation and argue for the need of a less naive clustering approach to develop a working measure for bias in FR models.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-07-20T08:02:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-07-20T08:02:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-09-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-20277</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-58309-5_10</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-20277</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-030-58309-5_10</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20277</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20277</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20277</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Artificial Neural Networks in Pattern Recognition</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>9th IAPR TC 3 Workshop on Artificial Neural Networks for Pattern Recognition (ANNPR'20), Winterthur, Switzerland, 2-4 September 2020</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Lecture Notes in Computer Science</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20499</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-06-03T08:20:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wearable technology acceptance in health care based on national culture differences : cross-country analysis between Chinese and Swiss consumers</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Yang Meier, Dong</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barthelmess, Petra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sun, Wei</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Liberatore, Florian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>610: Medizin und Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Background:&#13;
The advancement of wearable devices and growing demand of consumers to monitor their own health has influenced the medical industry. Healthcare providers, insurers, and global technology companies intend to develop more wearable devices incorporating medical technology and to target consumers worldwide. However, acceptance of these devices varies considerably among consumers of different cultural backgrounds. Consumer willingness to use healthcare wearables is influenced by multiple factors that are of varying importance in various cultures. How social and cultural factors affect wearable technology acceptance in healthcare is an area where there is insufficient knowledge.&#13;
&#13;
Objective:&#13;
This paper examines the intention to adopt healthcare wearables and the differences in the underlying motives and usage barriers of Chinese and Swiss consumers adopting healthcare wearables.&#13;
&#13;
Methods:&#13;
A new model for acceptance of healthcare wearables was conceptualized by incorporating predictors of different theories such as technology acceptance, health behavior, and privacy calculus based on an existing framework of wearables acceptance. To verify the model, a web-based survey in both Chinese and German was conducted in China and Switzerland, which produced 201 valid Chinese and 110 valid Swiss respondents, and their responses were included in the results. A multigroup PLS path analysis was applied to the survey data.&#13;
&#13;
Results:&#13;
The analyses of the data revealed that performance expectancy (PE), social influence (SI), hedonic motivation (HM), and effort expectancy (EE) positively affect behavioral intention (BI) of consumers to adopt wearables; functional congruence (FC), health consciousness (HC), and perceived privacy risk (PPR) did not demonstrate any significant impact on BI. While the multigroup analysis indicated HC as a factor affecting only the BI of the Chinese respondents positively, the factors affecting only the BI of the Swiss respondents proved to be EE and HM. PE asserts more influence on the BI of the Swiss respondents, while SI was of more influence on the BI of the Chinese respondents. Overall, the Chinese consumers displayed considerably higher BI than the Swiss. These discrepancies are explained by differences in national culture.&#13;
&#13;
Conclusions:&#13;
This paper is one of the first studies to investigate consumers’ intention to adopt wearables from a cross-cultural perspective. This provides a theoretical and methodological foundation for future research, as well as practical implications for global vendors and insurers developing and promoting healthcare wearables with appropriate features in different countries. The testimonial and support by physicians, evidence of measurement accuracy, as well as easy handling of healthcare wearables would be useful in promoting the acceptance of wearables in Switzerland. The opinions of in-group members, involvement of Chinese employers, multifunctional apps providing credible healthcare advices and solutions in cooperation with healthcare institutions would increase acceptance among the Chinese.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-09-17T12:51:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-09-17T12:51:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.2196/18801</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-20499</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.2196/18801</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-20499</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20499</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20499</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20499</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1438-8871</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>33090108</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of Medical Internet Research</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>JMIR Publications</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2915</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-16T13:48:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Targeted polypharmacology : discovery of a highly potent non-hydroxamate dual matrix metalloproteinase (MMP)-10/-13 inhibitor</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Senn, Nicole</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ott, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lanz, Jan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riedl, Rainer</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Drug design</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Humans</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Matrix metalloproteinase 10</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Matrix metalloproteinase 13</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Matrix metalloproteinase inhibitors</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Molecular models</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Polypharmacology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Structure-activity relationship</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>572: Biochemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615: Pharmakologie und Therapeutik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) play a key role in many diseases like cancer, atherosclerosis or arthritis. Interest in MMP inhibition has been revitalized very recently as the knowledge on the underlying network of biological pathways is steadily growing. On the basis of this new insight into the relevance of MMP-10 and MMP-13 within the MMP network and the ban of hydroxamate inhibitors from clinical development, the discovery of non-hydroxamate multitarget drugs against specific MMPs is of foremost interest. Here, we disclose the discovery of a very potent and selective non-hydroxamate MMP-10/-13 inhibitor. The high potency (IC50of 31 nM [MMP-10] and 5 nM [MMP-13]) and selectivity over MMP-1, -2, -3, -7, -8, -9, -12, and -14 enable this compound to decipher disease causing MMP networks and to generate new treatment options through targeted polypharmacology.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-21T13:22:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-21T13:22:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.7b01001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.7b01001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2915</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2915</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2915</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0022-2623</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>28953404</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of Medicinal Chemistry</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>American Chemical Society</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7210</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T10:17:32Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Zukunft des Marktes für soziale Dienstleistungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Steinebach, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Soziale Dienstleistungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Privatisierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Finanzierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Marktfähigkeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Unternehmer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Existenzgründung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gesundheitsberufe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Soziale Berufe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-22T11:29:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-22T11:29:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1998-10-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7210</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7210</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7210</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Fachtagung «Existenzgründung in sozialen Berufen und Gesundheitsberufen», Stuttgart, Deutschland, 16. Oktober 1998</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken completeListSize="24863" cursor="153">oai_dc////15400</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
