<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="static/style.xsl"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-06-08T16:54:16Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" resumptionToken="oai_dc////4800">https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/oai/request/</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23500</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-14T04:03:32Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Vorbilder und Inspirationen für Gründerinnen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Süss, Natalie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Filser, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>305: Personengruppen (Alter, Herkunft, Geschlecht, Einkommen)</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.1: Organisation und Finanzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Frauen sind im Startup-Sektor immer noch stark untervertreten. Die «Female Founder Initiative» will dies ändern. Bereits 300 Unternehmerinnen wurden so unterstützt. Jüngst hat Eva Parth dos Santos mit ihrer Firma Mint Girls davon profitiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-11-13T12:50:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-13T12:50:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23500</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23500</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.zhaw.ch/storage/sml/ueber-uns/sml-magazin-competence-2021.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23500</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2297-6140</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2297-6159</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Competence</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22727</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-06-24T03:01:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Place attachment theory</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Inalhan, Goksenin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Yang, Eunhwa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Weber, Clara</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>155: Differentielle Psychologie und Entwicklungspsychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>331: Arbeitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>This chapter explores current thinking about place attachment in the workplace. Place attachment describes the emotional bond between person and place. In the field of environmental psychology, place attachment has been identified as a significant predictor of an individual’s decision to act in a physical environment. However, the construct of place attachment has received scant attention in extant management literature. However, organisations are often forced to modify their places of work and relocate employees in response to new business strategies. The impact of these changes on people and work are rarely considered. People exhibit varied responses to such changes, with drastic changes requiring careful adjustments to address ‘emotional’ transitions. Can place attachment provide a useful concept for guiding workplace decisions? This chapter seeks to expose the gaps in our understanding of ‘attachment’ as a phenomenon. It recognises possible overlaps in environmental psychology and change management literature, as well as gaps between them, and considers how both fields can contribute to understand the workplace and the workspace.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-06-23T12:45:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-06-23T12:45:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1201/9781003128830-16</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-22727</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1201/9781003128830-16</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-22727</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22727</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22727</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22727</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>A Handbook of Theories on Designing Alignment between People and the Office Environment</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Routledge</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14950</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-12T13:17:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Designing for consistency of evaluation in Enterprise Governance of IT (EGIT)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hitz, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Corporate governance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>ISO 38500</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>IT alignment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>IT governance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658: Allgemeines Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Many researches have dedicated their work in IT Governance and numerous methods, techniques and tools for making decisions to align IT to a business strategy were proposed in the last decade. In the meantime new digital business models developed rapidly and aligning business with IT have become more difficult ever. Governance frameworks are widely used to reduce complexity in the decision making process and organisations tend to use several topic related governance frameworks beside IT Governance. Different governance frameworks are related, dependent and interact under each other and since they all have their own method of measurement and evaluation, the interaction suffers of a lack of data consistency or they do not take all dimensions of decision making into account. Furthermore the lack of consistency is caused by definition of governance frameworks itself and lead to concurring goals among governing bodies. My work proposes a design goal for a method of measurement by (1) critically review the existing state of art of measurement and evaluation concepts of governance frameworks by following a comprehensive review of the normative literature dealing with the measurement aspects of IT Governance and (2) analysing a dataset (n=51) of a preliminary study done in spring 2017 with Swiss companies and (3) introduce design principles for data collection in order to gather consistency of evaluation in Enterprise Governance of IT (EGIT).</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-04T15:33:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-04T15:33:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Research Colloquium 2018, Winterthur, 23. Mai 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6758</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-06-11T17:17:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wie Nachrichten entstehen :  Vorlesung gehalten an der Universität Eichstätt, Lehrstuhl für Journalistik</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Perrin, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Walter, Hömberg</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>IAM-Tagungsbeitrag</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>070: Nachrichtenmedien, Journalismus und Verlagswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-11T17:17:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-11T17:17:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1999-01-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Vorlesung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6758</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6758</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6758</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8906</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T13:39:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Evaluation of the ECHAM family radiation codes performance in the representation of the solar signal</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sukhodolov, T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rozanov, E.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Shapiro, A. I.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Anet, J.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cagnazzo, C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Peter, T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schmutz, W.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>500: Naturwissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Solar radiation is the main source of energy for the Earth's atmosphere and in many respects defines its composition, photochemistry, temperature profile and dynamics. The magnitude of the solar irradiance variability strongly depends on the wavelength, making difficult its representation in climate models. Due to some deficiencies in the applied radiation codes, several models fail to show a clear response in middle stratospheric heating rates to solar spectral irradiance variability; therefore, it is important to evaluate model performance in this respect before doing multiple runs. In this work we evaluate the performance of three generations of ECHAM (4, 5 and 6) solar radiation schemes by a comparison with the reference high-resolution libRadtran code. We found that all original ECHAM radiation codes miss almost all solar signals in the heating rates in the mesosphere. In the stratosphere the two-band ECHAM4 code (E4) has an almost negligible radiative response to solar irradiance changes and the six-band ECHAM5 code (E5c) reproduces only about half of the reference signal, while representation in the ECHAM6 code (E6) is better – it misses a maximum of about 15% in the upper stratosphere. On the basis of the comparison results we suggest necessary improvements to the ECHAM family codes by the inclusion of available parameterizations of the heating rate due to absorption by oxygen (O2) and ozone (O3). Improvement is presented for E5c and E6, and both codes, with the introduced parameterizations, represent the heating rate response to the spectral solar irradiance variability simulated with libRadtran much better without a substantial increase in computer time. The suggested parameterizations are recommended to be applied in the middle-atmosphere version of the ECHAM-5 and 6 models for the study of the solar irradiance influence on climate.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-08T08:42:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-08T08:42:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4651</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-7-2859-2014</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4651</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.5194/gmd-7-2859-2014</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8906</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8906</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8906</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1991-9603</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1991-959X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Geoscientific Model Development</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Copernicus</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23199</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-12-09T15:20:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Evaluation II Familystart Zürich : Abschlussbericht</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zsindely, Piroska</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Grylka, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Hebamme</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hebammennetzwerk</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wochenbettbetreuung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Versorgungssicherheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Hintergrund: Der gemeinnützige Verein Familystart Zürich wurde 2015 gegründet und setzt sich für die Sicherstellung der postpartalen Versorgung durch Hebammen und Pflegefachfrauen im Kanton Zürich ein. Er arbeitet dabei mit fünf Spitalpartnern im Raum Zürich und Winterthur, für welche er eine Vermittlungsgarantie gewährt. Familystart Zürich verfügt über eine webbasierte Applikation, die genutzt wird, um die Familien anzumelden und zu vermitteln. Nach einer ersten externen Evaluation 2018 werden in einer zweiten Evaluation folgende Themen beleuchtet: das Benutzererleben der Webapplikation sowie das Erleben des Anmelde- und Vermittlungsprozesses durch die betroffenen Stakeholder, die Eruierung von Optimierungs- und Weiterentwicklungsmöglichkeiten sowie der Vergleich der Vermittlungszeiten 2020 mit den Daten der letzten Evaluation.&#13;
&#13;
Methode: Die Evaluation wurde in zwei Modulen durchgeführt: Modul 1 beinhaltete teilstrukturierte Einzelinterviews und ein Fokusgruppengespräch mit Stakeholdern von Familystart Zürich. Je fünf Elternteile, Vereinsmitglieder, Spitalpartnervertreterinnen und die Geschäftsstelle von Familystart Zürich wurden befragt. Die Interviews wurden transkribiert und mittels qualitativer Inhaltsanalyse ausgewertet. Modul 2 beinhaltete die Auswertung der Anmeldedaten aller Familien, die zwischen dem 01.01.2020 und 31.12.2020 bei Familystart Zürich angemeldet wurden oder sich selbst angemeldet hatten. Die quantitativen Daten wurden deskriptiv mit dem Statistikprogramm R 4.0.3 ausgewertet.&#13;
&#13;
Ergebnisse: Die Aussagen der befragten Stakeholder wurden in vier Hauptkategorien mit jeweils mehreren Unterthemen zusammengefasst: «Gründe für Mitgliedschaft bei Familystart Zürich», «Erleben des Anmelde- und Vermittlungsprozesses, «Optimierungsmöglichkeiten des Anmelde- und Vermittlungsprozesses und «Weiterentwicklung». Die befragten Nutzerinnen und Nutzer von Familystart Zürich zeigten grosses Vertrauen in den Anmelde- und Vermittlungsprozess, sie wünschten sich aber teilweise, dass der Prozess transparenter wäre und dass sie bereits vor den Vermittlungen einen Eindruck der Vereinsmitglieder erhalten könnten. Als wichtig erwies sich im Prozess der Informationsaustausch über die zu vermittelnden Fälle zwischen den beteiligten Stakeholdern. Es besteht ein deutlicher Bedarf, diesen auszubauen. Die Netzwerkarbeit von Familystart Zürich wird durch die Vereinsmitglieder sehr geschätzt und in diesem Bereich erkannten die Stakeholder viel Entwicklungspotenzial. Die bestehende Webapplikation wurde durch die Vereinsmitglieder mehrheitlich für nützlich befunden, zeigt aber im Bereich der Tätigkeiten der Geschäftsstelle Weiterentwicklungsbedarf. Weiter konnten Daten von 3'311 Familien, die über Familystart Zürich angemeldet wurden, ausgewertet werden. Das Durchschnittsalter der Frauen lag bei 32.5 Jahren, sie waren zu zwei Dritteln Erst-gebärende und über 90% hatten ihr Kind in einem Partnerspital geboren. Die Mehrheit der Frauen war ausländischer Herkunft. Im Vergleich zu 2016 zeigte sich die Verschiebung von der mehrheitlich nachgeburtlichen Anmeldung zur Anmeldung mehrheitlich noch während der Schwangerschaft. Die mediane Vermittlungszeit verbesserte sich von über 26 Stunden im Jahr 2016 zu wenig mehr als 4 Stunden im Jahr 2020.&#13;
&#13;
Diskussion und Empfehlungen: Das Vertrauen in den Anmelde- und Vermittlungsprozess von Familystart Zürich durch die Stakeholder kann als gross beurteilt werden und wurde durch die kurzen Vermittlungszeiten auch bestätigt. Vier Hauptempfehlungen wurden formuliert: 1) Es wird empfohlen, das etablierte Angebot von Familystart Zürich unbedingt aufrecht zu erhalten. 2) Dem Bedürfnis nach erhöhter Transparenz und Nahbarkeit der Vereinsmitglieder wird empfohlen mithilfe der Weiterentwicklung der IT-Strukturen nachzukommen. Nach erfolgter Vermittlung einer Hebamme könnte ein Steckbrief dieses für die Familie nahbarer machen. 3) Es wird empfohlen, die bereits aufgewendeten Ressourcen der Netzwerkarbeit weiter auszubauen und neben dem interdisziplinären Vereinsnetzwerk auch lokale Netzwerke für die Familien zu fördern. 4) Schliesslich zeigte sich, dass die vorhandenen IT-Strukturen den gesteigerten Anforderungen des Vereins nicht mehr gerecht werden können. Es wird die Weiterentwicklung zu einem Content Management System empfohlen, welches dem Verein ermöglicht, eigenständig Qualitätsmanagement durchzuführen sowie Nutzeroberfläche und Inhalte selbstständig zu bearbeiten.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-09-24T14:07:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-09-24T14:07:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-09-15</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23199</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23199</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23199</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23199</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23199</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>37 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18912</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-01T12:46:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Debatte um den öffentlichen Rundfunk in der Schweiz : mit «NoBillag» gegen das gesellschaftliche Solidaritätsprinzip</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wyss, Vinzenz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Saner, Mirco</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Service Public</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>NoBillag</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Diskursanalyse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>SRG</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>070: Nachrichtenmedien, Journalismus und Verlagswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Kaum eine politische Vorlage der letzten Jahre hat in der Schweiz die Gemüter so erhitzt wie die „NoBillag“-Initiative zur Abschaffung der Rundfunkgebühren. Bezeichnend für die öffentliche Debatte dazu war eine Vielzahl von partizipierenden Akteuren, auch aus der Zivilgesellschaft. Der Impetus der Initianten entsprang libertärem Gedankengut und traf vordergründig den herrschenden Zeitgeist. Die ungewöhnlich lange Dauer des Abstimmungskampfes verdeutlichte den Stimmbürger*innen jedoch schließlich die argumentativen Schwächen und die radikalen gesellschaftlichen Konsequenzen dieses politischen Vorstoßes. Als wesentliches Learning ist festzuhalten, dass es bei medienpolitischen Debatten um die Weiterentwicklung des öffentlichen Rundfunks zukünftig nicht mehr genügt, institutionalisierte politische Kräfte hinter sich zu wissen, sondern dass es gelingen muss, auch Akteure der Zivilgesellschaft argumentativ zu erreichen. Dafür wird eine elaborierte Medienkompetenz unerlässlich sein.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-12-13T14:10:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-12-13T14:10:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.17879/jcsw-2019-2499</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.17879/jcsw-2019-2499</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18912</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18912</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18912</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-402-10992-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0075-2584</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Jahrbuch für Christliche Sozialwissenschaften</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Westfälische Wilhelms-Universität Münster</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11416</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T14:06:12Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Intercultural education : educating students towards a universal morality</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Konstantinidou, Triantafyllia Liana</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-10-04T12:46:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-04T12:46:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11416</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11416</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11416</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>AME 36th Annual Conference, St. Louis MO, USA, 4-6 November 2010</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Association for Moral Education (AME)</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23606</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-29T14:14:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kein Mietvertrag ohne bestimmbaren Mietzins</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stohwasser, Stephanie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Auch bei einem konkludent abgeschlossenen Mietvertrag oder bei einer Gegenleistung in der Form einer Sach- bzw. Arbeitsleistung muss die Höhe des Mietzinses zumindest bestimmbar sein.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-11-29T14:14:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-29T14:14:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23606</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23606</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23606</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1663-8549</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>ius.focus</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Helbing &amp; Lichtenhahn</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22816</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-29T13:39:04Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Impact of mislabelling on deep learning</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dettling, Marcel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Walser, Manuel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Frey, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Deep Learning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mislabelling</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sports analytics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>006: Spezielle Computerverfahren</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>700: Künste und Unterhaltung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-07-16T07:56:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-07-16T07:56:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-07-13</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22816</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22816</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22816</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>63rd ISI World Statistics Congress, virtual, 11-16 July 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10905</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T11:00:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>LIHLITH : improving communication skills of robots through lifelong learning</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Agirre, Eneko</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marchand, Sarah</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rosset, Sophie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Peñas, Anselmo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cieliebak, Mark</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>006: Spezielle Computerverfahren</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-09-20T13:34:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-20T13:34:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://ercim-news.ercim.eu/images/stories/EN114/EN114-web.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10905</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0926-4981</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1564-0094</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>ERCIM News</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>European Research Consortium for Informatics and Mathematics</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10759</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-07-02T14:03:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Streitschlichtung und Mediation GB aus einer rechtlichen Perspektive</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Naguib, Tarek</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Geistige Behinderung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Zivilrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mediation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>349: Rechtsvergleichung und ausländisches Recht</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Der vorliegende Beitrag stützt sich auf das vom Verfasser für die Fachstelle Égalité Handicap gehaltene Referat auf der Tagung „Streitschlichtung und Mediation von und mit Menschen mit geistiger Behinderung“, welche vom 2.-3. Februar 2007 in Köln stattfand.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-18T13:35:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-18T13:35:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10759</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10759</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10759</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1869-6708</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Spektrum der Mediation</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Metzner</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19914</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-01T07:02:45Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Stundenlohnstudie : stabile Ergebnisse</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brunner, Beatrice</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kraft, Esther</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>331: Arbeitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Zu Beginn des Jahres hat die ZHAW im Auftrag der FMH eine Studie zu den Stundenlöhnen von Ärztinnen und Ärzten im Vergleich zu anderen akademischen Berufsgruppen veröffentlicht. Nun liegt die überarbeitete Auflage der Studie vor. Da für die FMH Transparenz und eine verlässliche Datengrundlage die Basis für eine sachliche, faktenbasierte und lösungs­orientierte Diskussion der Ärzteeinkommen sind, präsentiert der folgende Artikel die neuen Ergebnisse und nimmt ­Bezug zur Erhebung MAS (Medical Ambulatory – ­Structure) des Bundesamtes für Statistik BFS.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-04-16T07:59:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-04-16T07:59:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.4414/saez.2019.18487</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-19914</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.4414/saez.2019.18487</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-19914</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19914</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19914</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19914</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0036-7486</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-4004</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Schweizerische Ärztezeitung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>EMH Schweizerischer Ärzteverlag</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24828</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-04-22T03:06:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Campus-Tag der Biodiversität : Rück- und Ausblick einer wiederkehrenden Feier des Artenreichtums</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Seiler, Hallie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Treichler Bratschi, Regula</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dengler, Jürgen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Biodiversität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Campus Grüental</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333: Bodenwirtschaft und Ressourcen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>577: Ökologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Im September 2021 kamen wieder Dutzende von Freund/-innen der Biodiversität zusammen, um auf dem Campus Grüental aufregende Entdeckungen zu machen. Mittels sieben verschiedener Kartiergruppen konnte die Gesamtartenliste auf 740 Arten erweitert werden. Wir können nur davon träumen, welche Tier- oder Pflanzenarten wir bei der nächsten Durchführung im Juni 2022 finden werden – hilfst Du bei der Suche mit?</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-04-21T08:05:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-04-21T08:05:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-04-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-24828</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-24828</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24828</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24828</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24828</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>IUNR Magazin</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9254</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T14:34:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Zwanzig Jahre Rassismusstrafnorm : ein Blick in die Rechtspraxis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Naguib, Tarek</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Reimann, Giulia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Hate Speech</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Diskriminierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Rassismus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Rassendiskriminierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>342: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Staats- und Verwaltungsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Für Menschen, die von Rassismus betroffen sind, ist die Rassismusstrafnorm wichtig, weil sie Unrecht benennt. Interessenorganisationen und die Strafrechtswissenschaft sehen in ihr einen Beitrag zur Stärkung antirassistischer Werte. Allerdings hat sie auch Schwächen: Die Durchsetzung ist nicht durchgehend gewährleistet, einzelne Rechtsfragen müssen noch geklärt werden. Die Staatsanwaltschaften und Gerichte entscheiden nicht in allen Fragen einheitlich. Zudem kann mit dem Strafrecht struktureller Rassismus nur ungenügend erfasst werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-20T14:06:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-20T14:06:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9254</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9254</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://www.ekr.admin.ch/pdf/Tangram_35.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9254</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Tangram</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Eidgenössische Kommission gegen Rassismus</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9327</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T10:12:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Vergesslichkeit im Alter - wie weiter? Angehörigensicht</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hediger, Hannele</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>616.8: Neurologie und Krankheiten des Nervensystems</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-08-21T15:38:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-21T15:38:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014-09-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9327</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9327</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9327</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Vortragsreihe: Lebensfragen im Alter, Winterthur, 29. September 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Departement Soziales (Bereich Alter und Pflege) der Stadt Winterthur, Pro Senectute</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2176</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-18T08:35:47Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>PromoS - Process model for non-medical support services in hospitals</dc:title>
          <dc:title>Version 1.0 – based on German original</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gerber, Nicole</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tschümperlin, Carina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hofer, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.2: Facility Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Since the introduction of the Diagnosis-Related Group/SwissDRG at the latest, interest in process considerations has risen in Swiss hospitals. The desired outcome is twofold; to achieve greater effectiveness and efficiency and to provide more accurate cost allocations for the generation of uniform benchmarking indicators. The goal was therefore to develop a process metamodel which can be used for all areas of non-medical support processes [FM in HC] while still leaving enough scope for individual adaptations for the various health institutions and organizations. In addition, it had to be ensured that the (partial) process definitions allow the precise implementation of the KPIs defined in the Key Performance Catalogue and that the KPIs can be assigned to (partial) processes. On the basis of existing process literature and documentation from the four project hospital partners, the process modeling of all FM in HC support processes was carried out using the consortial research approach in several iterative expert rounds together with the project business partners. The result is a process metamodel and concrete process models for all FM in HC support processes. The principle is based on the Plan-Do-Study-Act principle of the Deming Cycle and shows the three levels of support processes, sub-processes and process steps. Please also refer to the services listed in the performance catalogue for non-medical support services [LekaS]. The process model PromoS, together with the code catalogue KenkaS and the application catalog ApplikaS, is part of the reference model for non-medical support services in hospitals RemoS and basis for the guidelines on the use of SAP for Facility Management in Healthcare LesapS and the Assessment, Simulation and Benchmarking tool for Facility Management in Health Care. All topics mentioned are documented separately in detail and can be called up and downloaded with reference to the other documents at https://www.zhaw.ch/en/lsfm/institutes-centres/ifm/about-us/hospitality-management/fm-in-healthcare/remos/.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-01-24T15:19:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-24T15:19:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2176</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2176</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2176</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>86 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/17550</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-18T07:15:42Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Grundkenntnisse Wirtschaft und Recht : Betriebswirtschaft, Volkswirtschaft, Recht</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Balmer-Zahnd, Rahel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brunetti, Aymo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Friedli, Vera</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Adrian W.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Renato</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brunetti, Aymo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>300: Sozialwissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-07-19T08:27:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-07-19T08:27:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-02-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/17550</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/17550</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/17550</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-0355-0648-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>304 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>hep-Verlag</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23673</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-12-09T04:03:39Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Midwives’ perception of advantages of health care at a distance during the COVID-19 pandemic in Switzerland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gemperle, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Grylka-Baeschlin, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Klamroth-Marganska, Verena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ballmer, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gantschnig, Brigitte E.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pehlke-Milde, Jessica</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Telehealth</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Video conferencing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Remote care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Perception</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>COVID-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Midwifery</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Objective: To explore midwives' perceptions of the advantages of telemedicine during the COVID-19 pandemic in Switzerland.&#13;
&#13;
Design: Cross-sectional study based on an online survey using quantitative methods.&#13;
&#13;
Setting: Midwives working in Switzerland.&#13;
&#13;
Participants: Self-selected convenience sample of 630 members of the Swiss Federation of Midwives.&#13;
Measurement&#13;
&#13;
Open questions on advantages of health care at a distance and workrelated characteristics were used in the online questionnaire. The information was coded and integrative content analysis was applied.&#13;
&#13;
Findings: A good half of the respondents associated telemedicine with either an advantage beyond the pandemic (“Reduced workload”, “Improved health care provision”, “Greater self-care of clients”), while the others saw a pandemic-related advantage (“Protection from COVID-19”, “Maintaining care/counseling in an exceptional situation”), or no advantage at all. Older, more experienced midwives were less likely to see an advantage beyond the pandemic. The motive “Reduced workload” was positively associated with professionals aged younger than 40 years and midwives with up to 14 years of professional experience, and “Protection from COVID-19” was more likely cited by midwives aged 50 and more and by midwives working solely in hospitals. Midwives who stated “Maintaining care” and “Improved health care provision” as motives to embrace telemedicine were more likely to experience health care at a distance as a positive treatment alternative.&#13;
&#13;
Key conclusion: Midwives’ perceptions of the advantages of health care at a distance vary substantially with age and years of professional experience, as well as workrelated characteristics. Further research is necessary to acquire a sound understanding of underlying reasons, including the sources of the general attitudes involved. Implication for practice: Understanding the differences in perceptions of health care at a distance is important in order to improve the work situation of midwives and the health care they provide to women and families. Different sensitivities represent an important source in the ongoing discussion about the future use of telemedicine in health care.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-12-08T15:56:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-12-08T15:56:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.midw.2021.103201</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23673</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.midw.2021.103201</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23673</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23673</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23673</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23673</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0266-6138</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1532-3099</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Midwifery</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5359</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T11:52:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Vor-denken, Nach-denken : Geschichte und neuste Arbeiten von Ove Arup und Partner</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hagen-Hodgson, Petra</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>720: Architektur</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-18T14:50:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-18T14:50:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1993</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3584</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5169/seals-60854</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3584</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.5169/seals-60854</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5359</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5359</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5359</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0257-9332</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0005-6529</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Werk, Bauen + Wohnen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Verlag Werk</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3946</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-03-15T14:45:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Implementierung der Hospizidee im St. Josefs-Heim, München-Haidhausen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Orth, C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alsheimer, M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Koppitz, Andrea Luise</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Isfort, M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-15T14:41:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-15T14:41:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3946</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3946</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3946</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Eigenverlag</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5229</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-04-12T09:34:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Internet nel lavoro editoriale : risorse, strumenti, strategie per redattori, traduttori e per chi lavora con il testo</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Maneri, Gina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riediger, Hellmut</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>070: Nachrichtenmedien, Journalismus und Verlagswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T09:34:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T09:34:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5229</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5229</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5229</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-88-7075-628-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>it</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>I mestieri del libro</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>193 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Editrice Bibliografica</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4903</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T12:55:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Markenpersönlichkeit : Entwicklung eines Instrumentes zur Analyse von Markenkommunikation und Markenbeziehungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Waller, Gregor</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Süss, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bircher, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bolt, Isabelle</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Studer, Sybille</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Krummenacher, Claudia Wüest</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Marketing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Werbepsychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Medienpsychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Marke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Brand</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kommunikation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>659: Werbung und Öffentlichkeitsarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Zusammenarbeit mit Heartcore AG, Agentur für Markenwirkung, Zürich und By Heart, Werbeagentur, Zürich.&#13;
Forschungsbericht zur Projektphase 2004.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-06T11:13:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-06T11:13:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2005-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2004</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2004</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4903</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4903</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4903</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>88 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>HAP Hochschule für Angewandte Psychologie</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12195</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-10-21T10:16:44Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>ECM microenvironment unlocks brown adipogenic potential of adult human bone marrow-derived MSCs</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>H. Lee, Michelle</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Goralczyk, Anna G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kriszt, Rókus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ang, Xiu Min</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Badowski, Cedric</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Li, Ying</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Summers, Scott A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Toh, Sue-Anne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Yassin, M. Shabeer</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Shabbir, Asim</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sheppard, Allan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Raghunath, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>571: Physiologie und verwandte Themen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610: Medizin und Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Key to realizing the diagnostic and therapeutic potential of human brown/brite adipocytes is the identification of a renewable, easily accessible and safe tissue source of progenitor cells, and an efficacious in vitro differentiation protocol. We show that macromolecular crowding (MMC) facilitates brown adipocyte differentiation in adult human bone marrow mesenchymal stem cells (bmMSCs), as evidenced by substantially upregulating uncoupling protein 1 (UCP1) and uncoupled respiration. Moreover, MMC also induced ‘browning’ in bmMSC-derived white adipocytes. Mechanistically, MMC creates a 3D extracellular matrix architecture enshrouding maturing adipocytes in a collagen IV cocoon that is engaged by paxillin-positive focal adhesions also at the apical side of cells, without contact to the stiff support structure. This leads to an enhanced matrix-cell signaling, reflected by increased phosphorylation of ATF2, a key transcription factor in UCP1 regulation. Thus, tuning the dimensionality of the microenvironment in vitro can unlock a strong brown potential dormant in bone marrow.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-26T14:11:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-26T14:11:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4752</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1038/srep21173</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4752</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1038/srep21173</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12195</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12195</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12195</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2045-2322</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Scientific Reports</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Nature Publishing Group</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3978</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T09:26:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Das Internet und das "Unerwünschte"</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Süss, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-16T08:14:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-16T08:14:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1998</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3978</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3978</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3978</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Kinder, Schule, Internet : ein Ratgeber für Pädagogen und Eltern</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>LMVZ</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24481</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-04T13:48:12Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Öffentliches Verfahrensrecht</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wiederkehr, René</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>342: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Staats- und Verwaltungsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Rechtsprechung leistet einen wichtigen Beitrag zur Entwicklung des öffentlichen Verfahrensrechts. Den unterschiedlichen Verfahrensordnungen in Bund und Kantonen liegen ähnliche Grundsätze zugrunde, die weitgehend von der Rechtsprechung entwickelt worden sind. Die vorliegende Publikation zielt darauf, diese Grundsätze anhand von ausgewählten Urteilen zu erörtern und zu kommentieren. Anhand der Gerichtspraxis lassen sich wesentliche Verfahrenselemente aufzeigen, die vielen Prozessordnungen gemeinsam sind und deren Gesamtheit zentrale Bestandteile des öffentlichen Verfahrensrechts ausmachen. Insgesamt betrachtet soll das Case Book den Transfer zwischen Theorie und Praxis erleichtern. Es richtet sich insbesondere an Studierende, aber auch an Juristinnen und Juristen, die in der Praxis tätig sind.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-03-04T13:48:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-03-04T13:48:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24481</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24481</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24481</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7272-3783-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Stämpfli's Casebook SCB</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>XXIV, 328 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Stämpfli</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10678</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T09:27:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Börse ist kein Kasino</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>ZWP</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332.6: Investition</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Vergleiche der Börse mit einer Spielbank laufen ins Leere. An den Märkten spielt die Subjektivität eine wichtige Rolle. Die Forschung ist aber unterdessen darauf konzentriert, immer kompliziertere Modelle zu bauen, anstatt dies zu respektieren.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-17T14:13:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-17T14:13:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009-08-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10678</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10678</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10678</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0376-6829</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Neue Zürcher Zeitung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Neue Zürcher Zeitung</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/60</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-18T09:04:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1070</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_11</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Linguistic diversity in cooperative work processes of task-oriented teams</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Manchen Spörri, Sylvia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hohenstein, Christiane</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Kooperation In Arbeitsprozessen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sprachliche Diversität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Interkulturelle Teams</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lingua Franca</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Cooperation In Work Processes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Intercultural Teams</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lingua Franca</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Linguistic Diversity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>400: Sprache und Linguistik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Due to the internationalisation of companies and the immigration into Switzerland, Swiss companies today employ people from different backgrounds and with different mother tongues on all hierarchy levels. Thus, multilingual teams are becoming more common. The lingua franca, or common working language in these teams is often English or German; for many team members these are foreign or second languages. So far, research has paid too little attention to the linguistic challenges multilingual teams face and to the strategies they employ to efficiently master their communicative tasks.&#13;
&#13;
Even though several studies within organisational psychology and small group research look at the relationship between cultural diversity and group performance, they limit interculturality to values and ethnicity without or only implicitly taking into account language, thus neglecting its impact. On the other hand, communication in teams is being researched linguistically, but not from the angle of communicative efficiency and teamwork optimisation. Consequently, language diversity and strategies of coping with language diversity in team communication are mostly absent in psychological research and communicative efficiency is only a minor subject in organisational psychology.&#13;
&#13;
The main goal is to analyse how communicative efficiency in multilingual company-internal teams is attained. Our research question is whether communicative efficiency depends on the team’s ability to manage its diversity of languages, i.e. to master specific linguistic and communicative challenges in the company appropriately.&#13;
&#13;
Since the project is at the intersection of linguistic communication and team performance in organisations, it calls for an approach that combines linguistic methods with methods of organisational psychology and that is based on action theory and functional-pragmatic communication analysis as a common framework, combining qualitative and quantitative approaches. The data from two partner companies serve as case studies which are compared in a contrastive design.&#13;
&#13;
The findings of the study will help our partners in practice to foster multilingual teams and to establish a best-practice model that may be adapted for the use with other teams. This contrastive design with two partners in practice each having their own specific linguistically diverse work groups, enables an exemplary approach to linguistically diverse work groups, which are most common in this form in a large number of Swiss companies. As contrastive case studies they therefore help to gain new insights into the research area.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Sowohl durch die zunehmende Internationalisierung als auch durch Migrationsbewegungen in die Schweiz arbeiten Teams in Unternehmen auf allen hierarchischen Stufen vermehrt in sprachdiversen Konstellationen. Oftmals werden Deutsch oder Englisch als lingua franca zur Verständigung verwendet.
In dem vorliegenden Projekt wird untersucht, welche kommunikativen Probleme sich durch die Sprachdiversität von Teams ergeben und welche Bewältigungsstrategien diese entwickeln, um die kommunikative Effizienz in Teamsitzungen sicherzustellen. Diese Fragestellungen werden sowohl aus linguistischer Perspektive als auch aus organisationspsychologischer Sicht bearbeitet. In zwei betrieblichen Fallstudien werden in einem transdisziplinären Design Teamsitzungen mit funktional-pragmatischen Methoden analysiert und mit organisationalen Rahmenbedingungen sowie individuellen Bewältigungsstrategien in Beziehung gesetzt.
Erste Ergebnisse zeigen, dass in Abhängigkeit von der individuellen Erfahrung in der Zusammenarbeit in sprachdiversen Teams, von der Teamkonstellation und in Abhängigkeit von der Sprachpolitik des Unternehmens Mitarbeitende Kommunikationsstrategien entwickeln, welche zum einen zur kommunikativen Effizienz beitragen. Dazu gehören z.B. das Aushelfen mit Vokabeln, mehrmaliges Erklären oder fehlertolerantes Verhalten. Zum anderen verursachen sie aber auch dysfunktionale Effekte wie unsachgemässe Vereinfachungen, ungenaue Auftragsvergabe durch Moderator/innen und fehlende Partizipation der Mitarbeitenden an Sitzungen und Entscheidungen. Durch den transdisziplinären Ansatz können komplexe Zusammenhänge und positive und negative Effekte der kommunikativen Strategien aufgezeigt werden. Funktionierende Strategien sollen den Praxispartnern und weiteren Betrieben als Best-Practice Modelle dienen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Due to the internationalisation of companies and the immigration into Switzerland, Swiss companies today employ people from different backgrounds and with different mother tongues on all hierarchy levels. Thus, multilingual teams are becoming more common. The lingua franca, or common working language in these teams is often English or German; for many team members these are foreign or second languages. So far, research has paid too little attention to the linguistic challenges multilingual teams face and to the strategies they employ to efficiently master their communicative tasks.
Even though several studies within organisational psychology and small group research look at the relationship between cultural diversity and group performance, they limit interculturality to values and ethnicity without or only implicitly taking into account language, thus neglecting its impact. On the other hand, communication in teams is being researched linguistically, but not from the angle of communicative efficiency and teamwork optimisation. Consequently, language diversity and strategies of coping with language diversity in team communication are mostly absent in psychological research and communicative efficiency is only a minor subject in organisational psychology.
The main goal is to analyse how communicative efficiency in multilingual company-internal teams is attained. Our research question is whether communicative efficiency depends on the team’s ability to manage its diversity of languages, i.e. to master specific linguistic and communicative challenges in the company appropriately.
Since the project is at the intersection of linguistic communication and team performance in organisations, it calls for an approach that combines linguistic methods with methods of organisational psychology and that is based on action theory and functional-pragmatic communication analysis as a common framework, combining qualitative and quantitative approaches. The data from two partner companies serve as case studies which are compared in a contrastive design.
The findings of the study will help our partners in practice to foster multilingual teams and to establish a best-practice model that may be adapted for the use with other teams. This contrastive design with two partners in practice each having their own specific linguistically diverse work groups, enables an exemplary approach to linguistically diverse work groups, which are most common in this form in a large number of Swiss companies. As contrastive case studies they therefore help to gain new insights into the research area.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2015-07-10T12:01:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-07-10T12:01:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-60</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-60</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/60</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/60</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/60</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-905745-56-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Working Papers in Applied Linguistics</dc:relation>
          <dc:format>30 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24157</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-14T14:44:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Properties of additive-manufactured open porous titanium structures for patient-specific load-bearing implants</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zumofen, Livia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kopanska, Katarzyna S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bono, Epifania</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kirchheim, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>De Haller, Emmanuel B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Graf-Hausner, Ursula</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>3D printing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Additive manufacturing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Porous titanium</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>3D cell culture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Implant</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>PBF-LB/M</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Laser melting</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Biomaterial</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610.28: Biomedizin, Biomedizinische Technik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>670: Industrielle und handwerkliche Fertigung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Additive manufacturing has been well established in many sectors, including the medical industry. For load-bearing bone implants, titanium and its alloys, such as Ti6Al4V, are widely used due to their high strength to weight ratio and osseointegrative properties. However, bone resorption and loosening of implants is related to the significantly higher stiffness of dense Ti6Al4V, leading to stress shielding. With the aging of population, there is an increasing need for orthopedic implants with a high success rate and a long implant life span. Besides that the treatment of non-healing segmental bone defects, where the self repairing properties of bone tissue are not sufficient, is still a challenge. In both fields of application, patient-specific titanium implants combined with functionally graded porosity designed according to locally expected loads unlock new possibilities. Many studies underline the huge potential of the new design freedom to generate open porous structures and more personalized implants with enhanced mechanical properties that also integrate well with surrounding tissues. Integration of functionally graded open porosity into implants allows for the implant to more closely mimic the mechanical properties of human bone and its internal architecture. The results of this work represent the basis for developing complex porous titanium structures with various pore sizes and shapes to tailor structural mechanical properties and biological responses. Therefore, 3D porous structures with various pore sizes and shapes were designed and manufactured in Ti6Al4V using laser powder bed fusion (PBF-LB/M). Based on these structures, the correlation of pore size and shape with cell ingrowth, morphology, metabolic activity, and early markers for bone formation (ALP activity) was investigated in static cell cultures using the osteosarcoma cell line Saos-2. Mechanical properties, such as stiffness and compression strength, were investigated with compression testing. The present study concludes that cell morphology, metabolic activity, and ALP activity are widely independent of pore shape and size within the tested range of 400–700 µm pore size. Furthermore, the mechanical properties of the evaluated structures were in the range of cortical and trabecular bone. This opens the possibility to design mechanical properties with gradient porosity without decisively affecting biological responses.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-02-04T09:32:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-02-04T09:32:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.3389/fmech.2021.830126</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-24157</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.3389/fmech.2021.830126</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-24157</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24157</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24157</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24157</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2297-3079</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Frontiers in Mechanical Engineering</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Frontiers Research Foundation</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19158</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-24T04:00:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Verschwörungstheorien als Trigger jihadistischer Radikalisierung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Eser Davolio, Miryam</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Verschwörungstheorie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Extremismus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>303: Soziale Prozesse</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-01-23T14:36:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-01-23T14:36:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-19158</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-19158</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19158</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19158</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19158</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-290-18259-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-290-18260-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Phänomen Verschwörungstheorien : psychologische, soziologische und theologische Perspektiven</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Tagung der Kommission Neue Religiöse Bewegungen des Schweizerischen Evangelischen Kirchenbunds (NRB/SEK), Zürich, 9. November 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Theologischer Verlag Zürich</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5339</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T11:47:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Breakdown of the born-oppenheimer approximation in ZEKE states of Ag2</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Yeretzian, Chahan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hermann, Robert H.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ungar, Horst</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Selzle, Heinrich L.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schlag, Edward W.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lin, Sheng H.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Zeke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Silver cluster</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Born-oppenheimer approximation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>540: Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Recently we reported on vibrationally resolved spectra of the ionic ground state of Ag2+ via ZEKE spectroscopy. The vibronic intensity distributions could not be interpreted within the Franck-Condon scheme. Here, we show that it is possible to overcome this discrepancy by invoking the breakdown of the Born-Oppenheimer approximation in the ZEKE states of silver dimer. A comparison of the spectral structure of the direct ion signal with simultaneously recorded ZEKE band profiles further illustrates this non-Franck-Condon behavior.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-18T14:09:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-18T14:09:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1995-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/0009-2614(95)00441-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/0009-2614(95)00441-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5339</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5339</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5339</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0009-2614</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1873-4448</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Chemical Physics Letters</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3101</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-02-26T10:18:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Stopp &amp; Go</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lippmann, Eric</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Coach</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Coaching</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Organisationsentwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Führungskräfte</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>158: Angewandte Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T10:18:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T10:18:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3101</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3101</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3101</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-941965-80-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Train the Coach: Methoden : Übungen und Interventionen für die professionelle Weiterbildung von Coachs, Teamcoachs, Change-Agents, Organisationsentwicklern und Führungskräften</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Praxishandbuch Coaching. Edition Training aktuell</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>managerSeminare</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5227</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T11:32:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Strumenti per la traduzione</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Riediger, Hellmut</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Tecnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Traduzione automatica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>CAT-tool</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Strumenti</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T09:28:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T09:28:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5227</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5227</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5227</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>it</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Dizionario treccani di informatica, ICT e nuovi media</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Treccani</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5976</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T10:32:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Fit für innovatives Wirtschaften : was leistet die berufliche Grundbildung?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Trachsel, Sonja</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Spörri, Martina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Baur, Priska</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Berufsbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Koch</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Restaurationsfachleute</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lehrmittelanalyse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schweiz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ernährung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bildungsplan</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Umwelt</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Tiere</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vegetarisch</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vegan</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gastronomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nahrungsmittel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lebensmittel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Flexitarier</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>613.2: Diätetik</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-18T09:17:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-18T09:17:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3600</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3600</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5976</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5976</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5976</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Innovation in der Land- und Ernährungswirtschaft</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Jahrestagung der Schweizerischen Gesellschaft für Agrarwirtschaft und Agrarsoziologie (SGA), Gränichen, 12.-13. April 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9849</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-12-18T09:22:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>BGE 131 III 115: Tierhalterhaftung - Anforderungen an die Umzäunung einer Pferdeweide</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zuberbühler, Ivo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Böhme, Anna</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-08-28T14:46:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-28T14:46:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9849</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9849</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9849</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1660-3427</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>ius.full</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schulthess</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23414</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-08T15:29:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Voiko liikunta ehkäistä kipua?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Luomajoki, Hannu</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616.7: Krankheiten des Bewegungsapparates und Orthopädie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Kivusta kärsivälle ei tule välttämättä mieleen, että liikkuminen ja harjoittelu voisivat aut-taa kivun lievityksessä. Tutkimustulokset osoittavat kuitenkin, että kivun hoidon yksi tärkeä kulmakivi on juuri liikunta ja harjoittelu. Näin on varsinkin tuki- ja liikuntaelimistön kipujen (TULE) suhteen. Tässä artikkelissa käydään läpi harjoitteluterapian evidenssiä klii-nisistä tutkimuksista sekä pohditaan liikunnan kipua lievittävää vaikutusta molekyylitasolla. Lopuksi kerrotaan konkreettisesti, kuinka paljon ja mitä harjoitusta tulisi tehdä.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-11-08T15:29:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-11-08T15:29:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://1596852.166.directo.fi/@Bin/2ae0668df1c337bb9e33365984fd9443/1635933538/application/pdf/615369/Kipuviesti_2_20%20web.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23414</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1796-3141</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>other</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Kipuviesti</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Suomen Kivuntutkimusyhdistys Ry</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22852</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-23T03:01:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Energy master planning on neighbourhood level : learnings on stakeholders and constraints from the Norwegian case of Ydalir</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Baer, Daniela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Haase, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>333.79: Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>While energy planning on the building level is characterized by a limited number of stakeholders and a clear ambition setting, this situation changes when expanding to a neighbourhood level. Depending on the context of the neighbourhood, energy planning is challenged to align several stakeholders and define common ambitions and measures suitable to optimize the outcome of energy planning. In Norway, energy planning on neighbourhood level is a relatively new approach. We apply the Energy Master Planning (EMP) concept developed during the IEA EBC Annex 73 to describe the planning process within the Norwegian case study of Ydalir, which ambition is to become zero-emission. Through a qualitative research approach, we identify stakeholders involved, their role and impact, and indicate constraints on EMP implementation so far. We show how the concept of EMP must be further developed, to reply to evidence-based constraints in implementing and reaching for high ambitions in cutting down energy use and emission. This paper relates to the UN development goal 11 of Smart Cities and Communities.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-07-22T13:27:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-07-22T13:27:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1088/1755-1315/588/2/022001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-22852</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1088/1755-1315/588/2/022001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-22852</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22852</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22852</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22852</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1755-1315</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>IOP Conference Series : Earth and Environmental Science</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>BEYOND 2020 : World Sustainable Built Environment conference, online, 2-4 November 2020</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>IOP Publishing</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1267</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T13:57:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_236</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1055</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Hochschulen als pluralistische Organisationen : Herausforderungen an Leadership im Kontext multirationalen Managements</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Drilling, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Hochschulen gelten in der Organisationstheorie als unvollständige Organisationen, professionelle Bürokratien oder schlicht als organisierte Anarchien. Doch die Forschung über sie ist eher rar und besitzt eine Vielzahl von Leerstellen. Und über die in der Schweiz gerade erst gegründeten Fachhochschulen hat sich die Organisationsforschung noch keine systematischen Gedanken gemacht.

Diesen Umstand hat sich die vorliegende Arbeit zu eigen gemacht und die spezifische Frage nach dem Führungsverständnis auf der mittleren Managementebene in Fachhochschulen gestellt. Diese Ebene interessierte, denn dass Organisationseinheiten wie Instituten oder Kompetenzzentren formelle Leitungen vorstehen, kann als neuartig bezeichnet werden. Deren Aufgabe ist nach innen gerichtet, indem sie die Unternehmensziele für die Mitarbeitenden übersetzen; aber sie ist auch nach aussen gerichtet, denn die Leitungspersonen müssen die pluralen Umweltbedingungen, denen Fachhochschulen heute ausgesetzt sind, erkennen, bewerten und in ihr Führungshandeln einbeziehen.

In der Organisationsforschung wird der plurale Kontext im Konzept „Pluralistische Organisationen“ verhandelt und das Führen in solchen Kontexten als „multirationales Führen“ bezeichnet. Für die neue Linie der Leitenden von Organisationseinheiten bietet sich der Begriff der manager-academics an: Personen, die selbst aus dem Umfeld der Forschung kommen, die Rationalität der Wissenschaft internalisiert haben und nun vor der Aufgabe stehen, Umweltbedingungen mit ihren je spezifischen und zumeist widersprechenden Rationalitäten für die Organisation produktiv miteinander zu verknüpfen und dabei die nach Autonomie strebenden Mitarbeitenden als Expertinnen und Experten nicht zu verlieren.
Die vorliegende Arbeit fragt also einerseits nach der aktuellen Verfassung der Schweizer Fachhochschulen als pluralistische Organisationen. Und andererseits nach den Konzepten und Verständnissen, mit denen die manager-academics führen.
Erstere Frage wurde über die Literatur beantwortet, die zweite Frage mithilfe von Interviews. 11 Leitende von Organisationseinheiten aus 6 Hochschulen der Schweiz und 8 Disziplinen wurden befragt.

Zusammenfassend zeigen sich einflussreiche Kontexte, auf die Leitende von Organisationseinheiten an Schweizer Hochschulen ihre Zielsysteme referenzieren müssen. Die Steuerungsansprüche von Politik und der eigenen Hochschule stellen sich dabei als besonders gewichtig dar. Aber auch die Scientific Community, die Professional Community, die Studierenden, die Mitarbeitenden sowie die Gesellschaft allgemein diffundieren mit ihren Logiken in die einzelnen Organisationseinheiten. Deutlich wird auch, dass die manager-academics diese Logiken vielfach als sich widersprechend wahrnehmen; wenn in der Forschung beispielsweise ein marktwirtschaftliches Verständnis erwartet wird oder die Weiterbildung sowohl den Vorgaben der Berufsverbände als auch den eidgenössischen Stellen genügen soll. In solchen Situationen zeigt sich auch, dass eine ungeklärte Unternehmenspolitik der eigenen Hochschule Führungsentscheide unsicherer macht.

Zu den Führungsinstrumenten, die die manager-academics beim multirationalen Management nutzen, gehören die Gründung von Führungsteams, die partizipative und prozessfokussierte Ausarbeitung von Strategien für die Organisationseinheit aber auch das Bestreben, die Mitarbeitenden mit möglichst verschiedenen Rationalitäten unmittelbar zu konfrontieren (z.B. durch deren Einsatz in Lehre und Forschung). Im Sinne eines Leadership-Verständnisses bezeugen die Aussagen vor allem eine „Bescheidenheit“ des Führungsanspruchs: Die befragten Leitungspersonen realisieren maximale Formen der Mitentscheidung, beteiligen sich als Mitarbeitende im operativen Geschäft (z.B. in der Lehre) und verstehen Leadership als kontinuierlichen Lernprozess.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2017-04-10T11:33:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-04-10T11:33:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Master</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1265</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1265</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1267</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1267</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1267</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2186</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-24T10:53:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1086</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_5</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1087</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Gebäude als System</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wilhelm, Elena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sturm, Ulrike</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Architektursoziologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Interdisziplinarität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gebäude</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>System</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>720: Architektur</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Der vorliegende Sammelband versammelt interdisziplinäre Projekte, welche sich thematisch mit dem «Gebäude als System» auseinandersetzen.18 Beiträge fokussieren das Gebäude in seinem gesellschaftlichen und sozialen Kontext, in seiner Materialität, Wirtschaftlichkeit und kulturellen Ausdrucksgestalt sowie als Ort der Kommunikation und Interaktion. In sechs weiteren Beiträgen werden theoretische Überlegungen zur Programmatik des Interdisziplinären Schwerpunkts «Gebäude als System» erörtert und diskutiert, die Kopplung des Programms mit der Lehre geschildert, Aspekte von kooperativen Netzwerken und Fragen der Interdisziplinarität aufgegriffen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-01-25T10:33:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-25T10:33:45Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2186</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2186</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2186</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7281-3519-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>327 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Interact-Verlag</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/602</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:43:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_52</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Der Einfluss einer adoleszenten idiopathischen Skoliose auf das Gleichgewicht : ein Überblick</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hauser, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:06:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:06:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-602</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-602</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/602</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/602</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/602</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21521</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-08-03T07:37:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Genetic characterization of Erwinia amylovora isolates detected in the wild walnut‑fruit forest of South Kyrgyzstan</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Doolotkeldieva, Tinatin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bobushova, Saikal</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carnal, Simon</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rezzonico, Fabio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Malus sieversii</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Malus niedzwetzkyana</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Crataegus turkestanica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pyrus korshinskyi</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>IUCN red list</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>572: Biochemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>632: Pflanzenkrankheiten, Schädlinge</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erwinia amylovora, the causal agent of fire blight, was first reported in Kyrgyz orchards in 2008 and, within a few years, the disease has spread throughout most of the northern part of the country. As fire blight expanded and penetrated new areas, it also reached the unique ecosystem constituted by the Arslonbob wild walnut–fruit forests in South Kyrgyzstan. Here, we present the results of field surveys in the forests and in the nearby orchards and gardens of the Jalal-Abad region during the 2019 season. Further, we use genetic profiling of the CRISPR regions to compare the genotypes of the obtained isolates to those of previous outbreaks in the north of the country and in nearby Kazakhstan. While fire blight was found in twelve of the twenty-six sites investigated in and around the Arslonbob walnut–fruit forest, it was mostly located on domesticated varieties of quince, apple or pear in gardens, orchards or nurseries. Plants in the forest and especially endangered wild species were not affected by the disease, but their proximity to the current infection herds is cause of major concern and calls for immediate protective action. Genetic analysis suggests that the main introduction route for fire blight to Central Asia was import of contaminated plant material from already affected countries in the Eurasian continent, which probably occurred on multiple independent instances. Nonetheless, indications of natural spread of the disease were identified between the regions of South Kazakhstan and North Kyrgyzstan.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-02-04T09:48:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-02-04T09:48:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-01-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/s42161-021-00752-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/s42161-021-00752-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21521</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21521</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21521</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1125-4653</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2239-7264</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of Plant Pathology</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7497</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-16T13:48:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Gait deviations and compensations in pediatric patients with increased femoral torsion</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bruderer-Hofstetter, Marina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fenner, Verena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Payne, Erika</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zdenek, Katja</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Klima, Harry</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wegener, Regina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>616.7: Krankheiten des Bewegungsapparates und Orthopädie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618.92: Pädiatrie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Coxa antetorta describes an abnormal torsion of the femur. It is commonly considered a cosmetic problem and is treated surgically only in severe cases and the presence of physical complaints. The purpose of this study was to identify deviations in gait kinematics and kinetics in pediatric patients caused by coxa antetorta and to categorize these deviations into primary and secondary deviations. We conducted a retrospective, cross-sectional three-dimensional (3D) gait analysis study to detect gait deviations in adolescents (n = 18; age range 10.5-17.5 years) with coxa antetorta compared to age-matched healthy control subjects (n = 17). Principal component (PC) analysis was used for data reduction. Linear mixed models applied to PC-scores were used to estimate the main effects within retained PCs followed by a post-hoc subgroup analysis. Patients walked with smaller external foot progression angle, greater knee adduction, more internally rotated and flexed hips and greater anterior pelvic tilt. Subgroup analysis revealed that-depending on knee alignment-patients had higher knee and hip adduction moments. These deviations in joint kinematics and kinetics may be associated with physical complaints and accelerated development of osteoarthritis. Assessment of gait deviations related to coxa antetorta using 3D gait analysis may be an additional tool in individual clinical decision-making.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-28T14:52:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-28T14:52:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1002/jor.22746</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1002/jor.22746</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7497</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7497</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7497</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1554-527X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of Orthopaedic Research</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Wiley</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5725</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T10:52:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Antidepressant use prospectively relates to a poorer long-term outcome of depression : results from a prospective community cohort study over 30 years</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hengartner, Michael Pascal</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Angst, Jules</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rössler, Wulf</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>616.8: Neurologie und Krankheiten des Nervensystems</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-02T12:26:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-02T12:26:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1159/000488802</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1159/000488802</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5725</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5725</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5725</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0033-3190</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1423-0348</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>29680831</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Psychotherapy and Psychosomatics</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Karger</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24664</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-28T13:31:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>IoT and AI in Swiss asset management</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schnauss, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.1: Organisation und Finanzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2022-03-28T13:31:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-03-28T13:31:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24664</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24664</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24664</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>2021 WIOTC Summit Forum, online, 30 November 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11072</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T14:09:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_236</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_8947</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Berufliche Zweitausbildung im Erwachsenenalter : Beweggründe, Erfahrungen und Ressourcen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mühlemann, Irene</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>331: Arbeitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die vorliegende Arbeit befasst sich mit dem Thema berufliche Zweitausbildung im Erwachsenenalter. Dabei stehen drei Fragestellungen im Fokus: Was sind die Beweggründe für eine berufliche Zweitausbildung im Erwachsenenalter? Welche Erfahrungen machen Erwachsene und welche Herausforderungen erleben sie im Rahmen ihrer beruflichen Zweitausbildung? Und welche Personen- und Umweltfaktoren tragen dazu bei, dass Erwachsene ihre berufliche Zweitausbildung erfolgreich meistern? Um diesen Fragen auf den Grund zu gehen, wurden problemzentrierte Interviews geführt, die wörtlich transkribiert und nach der qualitativen Inhaltsanalyse ausgewertet wurden. Befragt wurden fünf Personen, die im Alter von 25 oder mehr Jahren eine reguläre oder verkürzte Berufslehre als Zweitausbildung begonnen und zum Zeitpunkt der Befragung bereits abgeschlossen hatten. Die Ergebnisse zeigen, dass die Beweggründe für eine berufliche Zweitausbildung im Erwachsenenalter individuell, vielfältig und multikausal sind und dass intrinsisch motivierte Beweggründe eine wichtige Rolle spielen. Die Befragten erlebten im Rahmen ihrer beruflichen Zweitausbildung diverse Herausforderungen und Erfahrungen, wobei ähnliche Erfahrungen zum Teil unterschiedlich wahrgenommen und bewertet wurden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-26T13:59:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-26T13:59:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Master</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2227</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2227</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11072</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11072</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11072</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>76 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15341</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T15:30:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Veränderte Spielregeln : Finanzberatung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hofmann, Roland</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zemp, Manuela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Weber, Gabriela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Haftung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Anlageberatung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Financial planning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Finanzplanung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332: Finanzwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Der Artikel beleuchtet am Beispiel der Privaten Finanzplanung - deren Kennzeichen es ja ist, finanzielle Planungsrechnungen in die Zukunft zu erstellen -, wie ein Berater auf sich verändernde oder sich abzeichnende gesetzliche Rahmenbedingungen reagieren sollte und welche Aufklärungspflichten er gegenüber seinen Kunden hat.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-13T15:30:38Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-13T15:30:38Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2001</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15341</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15341</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15341</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1010-5808</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Schweizer Bank</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Ringier Axel Springer Schweiz</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20261</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-04-25T13:17:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Caring Communities : das Hören verlieren - die Würde behalten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Händler-Schuster, Daniela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Werren, M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-07-13T08:55:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-07-13T08:55:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.hogrefe.com/ch/index.php?eID=dumpFile&amp;t=f&amp;f=5505&amp;token=72eea4da13449df0a6b4d37ca4c608c1bf84f53c</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20261</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1662-9027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2235-4271</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>NOVAcura</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Hogrefe</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5349</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T10:33:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Realtime signal processing on NVIDIA TX2 using CUDA</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Weiss, Armin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rosenthal, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mazloumian, Amin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>GTC</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>GPU</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Real-time</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Tegra X2</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>CUDA</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Persistent Kernel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In our presentation, we will focus on low latency real-time signal processing on NVIDIA Jetson TX2. Originally designed for image processing, the Jetson TX2 incorporates a vast amount of embedded GPU processing power. However, it has not been widely used for signal processing so far. There are two main challenges that have to be addressed: Constantly high input and output data rate of arbitrary digital signals, as well as a very short and deterministic latency requirement (processing time and data transfer time). Using the example of multichannel digital audio processing, we will look at details of CUDA kernel programming, which is a precondition for uninterrupted signal processing. Moreover, we explain efficient data I/O transfer to Jetson TX2 GPU memory, synchronization between CPU and GPU as well as update mechanisms for control data.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-18T14:36:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-18T14:36:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-26</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5349</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5349</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5349</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Nvidia GPU Technology Conference (GTC), San José, USA, 26-29 March 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10937</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T10:17:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ein neuer Bildungsbegriff oder verdeckte Bildungspolitik? : Ganztagesbildung in der Schweiz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Chiapparini, Emanuela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Bildungsbegriff</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bildungspolitik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ganztagesbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Soziale Arbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kinder- und Jugendhilfe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kinder</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lehrer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>qualitative Befunde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Vortrag</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-21T07:16:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-21T07:16:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-05-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10937</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10937</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10937</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Forschungskolloquiums - Erziehungswissenschaft mit dem Schwerpunkt Soziale Arbeit und außerschulische Bildung, Kassel, Deutschland, 2. Mai 2017</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18273</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-14T12:24:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Innovation and certainty in law : the European court of justice landmark case system in antitrust</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Günster, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>349: Rechtsvergleichung und ausländisches Recht</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-09-26T12:26:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-09-26T12:26:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18273</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18273</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18273</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Third Workshop for Junior Researchers on the Law &amp; Economics of Intellectual Property and Competition Law, Kreuth, Germany, 18-20 June 2012</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18915</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T14:14:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Der politische Einfluss der Städte</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ebnöther, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lennart, Simon</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>320: Politik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Das föderalistische System der Schweiz sieht für die stetig wachsenden Städte keine eigenen föderativen Institutionen vor. Ihre Stellung sollte verbessert werden, zum Beispiel durch eine halbe Standesstimme in Volksabstimmungen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-12-13T14:14:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-12-13T14:14:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-10-23</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18915</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18915</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18915</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0376-6829</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Neue Zürcher Zeitung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Neue Zürcher Zeitung</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/956</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-19T13:39:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_236</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_238</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Aufwachsen zwischen Familiensystemen : eine qualitative Studie zum Erleben von Pflegekindern und ihren Pflegeeltern</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Moser, Evelyn</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:14:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:14:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Master</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-956</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-956</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/956</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/956</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/956</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2086</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T10:12:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Olefin metathesis of a ruthenium carbene complex by electrospray ionization in the gas phase</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hinderling, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Adlhart, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chen, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Gas-phase chemistry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mass spectrometry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Metathesis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Carbene complexes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>660: Technische Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Surprisingly similar reactions in the gas phase and in solution [Eq. (a)]: The ion 1 obtained by electrospray ionization behaves in the gas phase analogously to the corresponding complex [RuCl2(=CHPh)(PCy3)2] in solution. Measured relative rates for ring-opening metathesis are interpreted under the assumption of an intramolecular π complex, which leads to an estimation of the equilibrium constant for π complexation.&#13;
	 </dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-01-17T10:54:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-17T10:54:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1998-10-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1521-3773(19981016)37:19&lt;2685::AID-ANIE2685&gt;3.0.CO;2-M</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1002/(SICI)1521-3773(19981016)37:19&lt;2685::AID-ANIE2685&gt;3.0.CO;2-M</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2086</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2086</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2086</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1433-7851</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0570-0833</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Angewandte Chemie: International Edition</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Wiley</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2993</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T10:12:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Investigating demands on language professionals</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ehrensberger-Dow, Maureen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Massey, Gary</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Revision</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Translator</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Camtasia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Search strategie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>331: Arbeitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The demands on language professionals have increased in recent years, extending from traditional translation from source into target language, adaptation of texts for different readerships, self-revision of own translations and texts, revisions of others' translations, post-editing of machine translations, revision of non-native users' writing, and proofreading. Developments in software applications and business processes in many translation service companies reflect these changes in the workplace, but little research as yet has been done into what demands these various translation and writing processes place on cognitive resources. In fact, many translators prefer translating to editing and other specialized tasks, since they say that they chose to become translators and not technical writers. They may be unprepared for the shifts taking place in the workplace and feel professionally disoriented. We will present an approach to triangulating empirical research on actual working processes that could lay important foundations for optimizing training, workflow efficiency and output quality at all levels of translation competence, from novice to seasoned professional.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-23T15:03:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-23T15:03:49Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008-02-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2993</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2993</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2993</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>VALS-ASLA Conference, Lugano, 7-9 February 2008</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5945</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-25T07:44:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>An open implementation of a two-phase PEMFC model in MATLAB</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Vetter, Roman</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schumacher, Jürgen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Proton exchange</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Membrane</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fuel cell</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.04: Energietechnik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In almost three decades of PEM fuel cell modelling, a large number of numerical models has been developed both in science and industry, but almost none have been made publically available. There is a large need for standardization and establishing a common ground in the development of PEMFC simulation codes, to prevent each research group from having to start from scratch. To this day, there are only two known open-source codes capable of simulating the state of the art in PEMFC modeling at the cell scale: OpenFCST [1], a highly capable but heavy FEM package consisting of more than 120.000 lines of C++ code published under the MIT license, and FAST-FC [2], a finite volume tool built on top of OpenFOAM, consisting of about 12.000 lines of code (not counting the required OpenFOAM) published under the GNU GPL v3, which can pose an insurmountable legal barrier for commercial use. 

Here, we present the first open standalone implementation of a full-blown, steady-state, non-isothermal two-phase, macro-homogeneous MEA model for low-temperature PEMFCs [3]. It implements the most dominant through-plane transport processes in a 5-layer MEA (Fig. 1): the transport of charge, energy, gas species and water. This results in eight coupled nonlinear second-order partial differential equations, which are numerically solved together. The focus is on code simplicity, compactness, portability, transparency, accessibility and free availability. The model is implemented as a standalone MATLAB function, based on MATLAB's boundary value problem solver, and released to the public under a BSD-like license, permitting unrestricted use for commercial and non-commercial purposes.

In order to establish a new reference for model comparison, validation and benchmarking, we subject our model to a series of stress tests with operating conditions recommended for automotive applications by the Joint Research Centre of the European Commission [4] and report here on the test results.

Acknowledgements: Financial support from the Swiss National Science Foundation under the National Research Programme "Energy Turnaround (NRP 70)", project no. 153790, grant no. 407040_153790, from the Swiss Commission for Technology and Innovation under contract no. KTI.2014.0115, through the Swiss Competence Center for Energy Research (SCCER Mobility), and from the Swiss Federal Office of Energy (SFOE), is gratefully acknowledged.

References:
1. M. Secanell et al.. ECS Transactions 64, 2014, 655–680
2. D. B. Harvey, J. G. Pharoah, and K. Karan. https://www.fastsimulations.com/
3. R. Vetter, J. O. Schumacher, manuscript submitted to Computer Physics Communications
4. G. Tsotridis, A. Pilenga, G. De Marco, T. Malkow, JRC Science for Policy report, EUR 27632 EN, 2015</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-05-17T14:04:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-17T14:04:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5945</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5945</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5945</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>15th Symposium on Modeling and Experimental Validation of Electrochemical Energy Devices (ModVal 2018), Aarau, Switzerland, 12-13 April 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Electrochemistry Laboratory, Paul Scherrer Institut PSI</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12989</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T11:10:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Collaborative ad-hoc information sharing in cross-media information environments</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Signer, Beat</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>de Spindler, Alexandre</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Norrie, Moira C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Collaborative</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Cross-media</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Information sharing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658: Allgemeines Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Due to the ever increasing number of different digital media types that we use in our daily work, it is no longer sufficient to manage them in an isolated way but desirable to define associations across the media boundaries. While cross-media information systems allow different forms of media objects to be linked, there is often a lack of support for the flexible authoring and sharing of these links. We present a solution for exchanging cross-media link information in an ad-hoc way among communities of users based on a notion of a cooperative cross-media link server. We describe how the system has been implemented based on an existing cross-media link server (iServer) and peer-to-peer technologies.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-19T09:29:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-19T09:29:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-05148-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-642-05148-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12989</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12989</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12989</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-642-05147-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1610-2886</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of CoopIS 2009 : on the move to meaningful internet systems</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>17th International Conference on Cooperative Information Systems, Vilamoura, Portugal, 2-5 November 2009</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Lecture Notes in Computer Science</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10718</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-04T12:57:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Flexibilisierte Fixlöhne : ökonomisch sinnvoll und leistungsgerecht</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Willi, Hans</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Leistung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lohn</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ökonomisch</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>HR</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.3: Personalmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Im Wettbewerb der Unternehmen drängt es sich auf, Erfolg und Misserfolg sinnvollerweise und fairerweise auf die ganze Organisation zu beziehen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-18T11:55:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-18T11:55:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10718</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10718</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10718</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2235-8471</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>HR Today</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Jobindex</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3232</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T13:39:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Algorithms for highly symmetric linear and integer programs</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bödi, Richard</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Herr, Katrin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Joswig, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Linear programming</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Symmetry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Integer programming</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Permutation group</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>510: Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenzen.ch)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>This paper deals with exploiting symmetry for solving linear and integer programming problems. Basic properties of linear representations of finite groups can be used to reduce symmetric linear programming to solving linear programs of lower dimension. Combining this approach with knowledge of the geometry of feasible integer solutions yields an algorithm for solving highly symmetric integer linear programs which only takes time which is linear in the number of constraints and quadratic in the dimension.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-27T14:21:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-27T14:21:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1736</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10107-011-0487-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1736</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/s10107-011-0487-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3232</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3232</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3232</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0025-5610</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Mathematical Programming</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15083</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T09:26:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Loyalitätsbeziehungen der Übersetzungsrevisorin</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Künzli, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Kulturtransfer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>ÜbersetzerInnen-Ausbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Übersetzung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Übersetzungsgeschichte</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Übersetzungssoziologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Übersetzungswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-02-06T09:18:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-06T09:18:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15083</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15083</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15083</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-8258-9552-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3-7000-0553-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Übersetzen, Translating, Traduire : towards a social turn?</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Repräsentation - Transformation : Representation - Transformation : Représentation - Transformation</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>LIT</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15063</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-02-05T18:30:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wissenschaftliche Überprüfung der Indikatoren des Globalbudgets 2310 Kantonspolizei für das Jahr 2002 : Schlussbericht</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bergmann, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gamper, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Globalbudget</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Indikator</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>350: Öffentliche Verwaltung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>363: Umwelt- und Sicherheitsprobleme</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die im Globalbudget 2002 der Zürcher Kantonspolizei aufgeführten Wirkungs-, Leistungs- und Wirtschaftlichkeits-Indikatoren wurde auf ihre Validität und Reliabilität geprüft. Das Ergebnis der Prüfung ist grundsätzlich positiv. Bei einzelnen Indikatoren werden Hinweise auf mögliche Verbesserungen gegeben.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-05T18:30:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-05T18:30:20Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15063</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15063</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15063</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/834</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T10:44:12Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_236</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_237</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Psychoonkologische Psychotherapie : welche Schwerpunkte bezüglich Wirkfaktoren zeigen sich im Verlauf der psychoonkologischen Psychotherapie?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gysling-Tappeiner, Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Psychoonkologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Psychotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wirkung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:11:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:11:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-834</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-834</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/834</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/834</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/834</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>76 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21378</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-21T13:54:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Zen-Meditation und Leadership : Führen aus der Mitte</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Klink, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>158: Angewandte Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-01-21T13:54:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-01-21T13:54:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-662-55810-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-662-55810-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21378</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21378</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21378</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-662-55809-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-662-55810-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Handbuch Angewandte Psychologie für Führungskräfte : Führungskompetenz und Führungswissen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21186</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-07T13:21:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Hebamme als Profession : Berufsethik</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hauser, Regula</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Berufsethik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>170: Ethik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Ethik und Moral&#13;
Ethisches Dilemma&#13;
Ethische Entscheidungsfindung&#13;
Ethische Theorien&#13;
Ethisches Handeln in der Hebammenarbeit&#13;
Internationaler Ethik Kodex für Hebammen&#13;
Dimensionen der Ethik in der Hebammenarbeit</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-01-07T13:21:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-01-07T13:21:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21186</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21186</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21186</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-13-240450-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Hebammenkunde</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Thieme</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1897</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-04-16T08:39:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>JAMESfocus. Handyverhalten und Nachhaltigkeit</dc:title>
          <dc:title>JAMESfocus. Utilisation du portable et durabilité</dc:title>
          <dc:title>JAMESfocus. Cellulare, comportamenti e sostenibilità</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Suter, Lilian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Waller, Gregor</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Willemse, Isabel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Genner, Sarah</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Süss, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>158: Angewandte Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>338.927: Umweltökonomie und nachhaltige Entwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Bericht auch in französisch und italienisch vorhanden, vgl. www.zhaw.ch/psychologie/jamesfocus</dc:description>
          <dc:description>In diesem Bericht wird zunächst auf den Lebenszyklus eines Handys von der Herstellung bis zur Entsorgung eingegangen und Aspekte der Nachhaltigkeit werden erläutert. Anschliessend wird im Ergebnisteil der Frage nachgegangen, wie ein typisches Handy-Leben in den Händen eines Jugendlichen aus der (Deutsch-) Schweiz abläuft – vom Erwerb bis zur Entsorgung. Weitere Analysen beschäftigen sich mit der Anzahl ungenutzter Handys in den Schubladen Schweizer Jugendlicher und deren Wissenstand über spezifische Fakten im Zusammenhang mit Handy und Nachhaltigkeit. Die Grundlage hierfür bilden einerseits die Daten aus der JAMES-Befragung 2016. Andererseits stammen Daten aus einer Erhebung im Rahmen des Projekts „Digitale Suffizienz“. Das Projekt ist eine Kooperation mit dem IUNR Institut für Umwelt und Natürliche Ressourcen der ZHAW und wird von der Stiftung Mercator Schweiz unterstützt. Abschliessend werden Tipps für Handynutzerinnen und -nutzer für einen nachhaltigen Umgang mit dem Handy gegeben.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2017-12-19T15:23:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-12-19T15:23:23Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3469</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3469</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1897</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1897</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1897</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>20 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16322</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-24T09:44:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Aktuelle Herausforderungen auf dem Wohnungsmarkt : Studie im Auftrag der SP-Fraktion der Bundesversammlung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jans, Armin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Graf, Silvio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leu, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Wohnungsknappheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wohnungsmarktprojektion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wohnungsbauprojektion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333: Bodenwirtschaft und Ressourcen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Im April 2011 erteilte die SPS-Fraktion der Bundesversammlung der Fachstelle für Wirtschaftspolitik an der ZHAW den Auftrag zu untersuchen, wie sich der Wohnungsmarkt in den kommenden 20 Jahren entwickeln wird. Insbesondere interessiert, wie sich der durch den freien Personenverkehr mit der EU geöffnete Arbeitsmarkt auswirken dürfte. Die vom Auftraggeber formulierten wohnpolitischen Ziele lauten: 1. Genügende Abdeckung des nationalen Wohnungsbedarfs (keine Preisexzesse). 2. Keine neuen Verdrängungseffekte aus den fünf Problemregionen (Pendlerströme!), als solche gelten der Kanton Zürich (insbesondere die Stadt Zürich), der Kanton Zug, das Bassin lémanique, die Region Basel und die Stadt Bern. 3. Soziale Durchmischung in allen Problemregionen (keine Gettoisierung). Falls diese Ziele nicht erreicht werden sollten, sind Massnahmen vorzuschlagen, die geeignet sind, sich den Zielen ganz oder zumindest teilweise anzunähern.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-03-26T12:41:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-26T12:41:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.zhaw.ch/storage/sml/institute-zentren/fwp/Studien/Studie_Wohnungsknappheit.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16322</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>84 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20630</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-10-15T12:30:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Der Fall Keetenheuve: zur Einordnung der Demokratiekritik im Treibhaus</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dreesen, Philipp</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Parlamentarismus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Demokratietheorie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Repräsentativität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>320: Politik</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-10-15T12:30:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-10-15T12:30:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20630</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20630</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20630</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1614-7170</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Flandziu : Halbjahresblätter für Literatur der Moderne</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Shoebox House</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5194</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T07:22:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Verbindungslose bidirektionale Kommunikation auf Basis von BLE Advertising für Beacons mit Lifetime Battery</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gruber, Juan-Mario</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fabbroni, Tiziano</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Truninger, Dominique</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Beacon</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wireless</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>BLE</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wireless Sensor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Es wird das Konzept und die Machbarkeitsstudie einer bidirektionalen Kommunikation auf Basis von Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE) im Advertising Mode vorgestellt. Dazu wurden verschiedene Verfahren entwickelt, die auf Beacons und Standard-Smartphones implementierbar sind. Die unterschiedlichen Lösungsansätze wurden mit Prototypischen Aufbauten realisiert. Im Labor und in realitätsnahen praktischen Versuchen konnte die Machbarkeit nachgewiesen werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T08:47:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-12T08:47:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5194</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5194</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5194</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>IoT Konferenz 2015, Internet of Things - vom Sensor bis zur Cloud, München, 22. Oktober 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>WEKA Fachmedien</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22516</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-06-04T07:58:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Development and validation study of a 1D analytical model for the response of reheat flames to entropy waves</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gant, Francesco</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gruber, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bothien, Mirko</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Flame transfer function</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Non-linear flame response</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Entropy waves</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Reheat combustion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Autoignition flames</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.04: Energietechnik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Numerical simulations of laminar premixed flames burning hydrogen and methane in spontaneous ignition mode are performed by harmonically exciting the reactants’ temperature at the domain inlet. The results are compared to an analytical model representing the same reactive flow configuration. The model provides a simplified but nevertheless accurate representation of reheat combustion taking place in sequential gas turbine combustors. An analytic expression for autoignition flames transfer functions to entropy waves is derived and used to extend transfer function models from the literature. For validation purposes, results from fully compressible Direct Numerical Simulations (DNS), including a complete representation of the fluctuating acoustic and entropic fields of the reactive flow, are analyzed and compared to incompressible Unsteady Reynolds-Averaged Navier–Stokes (URANS) simulations that only take into account the fluctuating entropic field. Methane flames are found to be more sensitive to entropic forcing than hydrogen flames, featuring nonlinear phenomena even for low excitation amplitudes. In the linear regime, all flames behave as predicted by the analytical model and the URANS simulations are found to correctly predict the fluctuating entropic field. The transition from linear to nonlinear flame response is described in detail and its physical mechanisms are explained. Comparisons with results available in the literature show good prediction capabilities, both in terms of flame describing function and integrated heat release rate. Limitations of the proposed analytical model with respect to real combustion systems are discussed and a simple correction is proposed.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-05-20T14:07:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-05-20T14:07:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.combustflame.2020.09.005</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.combustflame.2020.09.005</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22516</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22516</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22516</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0010-2180</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Combustion and Flame</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8584</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-27T13:35:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>ZitierGuide : Leitfaden zum fachgerechten Zitieren in rechtswissenschaftlichen Arbeiten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Roger</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-07-26T12:55:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-26T12:55:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8584</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8584</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8584</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7255-6007-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>28 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Schulthess</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6249</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T10:52:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>A critical review of the proposed definitions of fundamental chemical quantities and their impact on chemical communities (IUPAC Technical Report)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Marquardt, Roberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meija, Juris</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mester, Zoltan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Towns, Marcy</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Weir, Ron</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Davis, Richard</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stohner, Jürgen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>540: Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-30T11:32:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-30T11:32:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3702</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1515/pac-2016-0808</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3702</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1515/pac-2016-0808</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6249</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6249</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6249</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1365-3075</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0033-4545</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Pure and Applied Chemistry</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>De Gruyter</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24418</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-02T10:43:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Word of the Year in Switzerland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Whitehouse, Marlies</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Word of the year</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418: Gebrauch der Standardsprache</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2022-03-02T10:43:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-03-02T10:43:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-08-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24418</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24418</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24418</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>AILA World Congress, online, 15-20 August 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8998</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-07T15:31:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Psychoanalytische Ansätze</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kruse, Otto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Emotionspsycholoogie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Psychoanalyse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Emotionale Entwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-08-15T09:00:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-15T09:00:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2000</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8998</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8998</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8998</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3-621-27453-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Emotionspsychologie : ein Handbuch</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Beltz Juventa</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15221</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-02-07T16:51:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Sind Schweizer KMU interessant für Privatinvestoren? : qualitative Analyse eines potentiellen (Finanzierungs-)Marktes zwischen KMU und Privatinvestoren</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Portmann, Jutta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sigg, Anita</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ziegler, Suzanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>KMU</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Privatinvestor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>ZBB</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>IBF</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332: Finanzwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-02-07T16:51:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-07T16:51:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Weiteres (textuelles Material)</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15221</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15221</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15221</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>18 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15360</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T14:10:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1315</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1463</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Das Blackcurrant Reversion Virus bei Cassis (Ribes nigrum) in der Beerensammlung von ProSpecieRara (Riehen BS) : Virusfreimachung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Genucchi, Katharina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Ribes nigrum</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schwarze Johannisbeere</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Cassis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Blackcurrant Reversion Virus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Cecidophyopsis ribis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Johannisbeergallmilbe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>ProSpecieRara</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Virusfreimachung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Thermotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>In-vitro-Kultivierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Blackcurrant</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Blackcurrant gall mite</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Big bud mite</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Virus elimination</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Thermotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>In vitro cultivation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>630: Landwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>634: Obstanlagen, Früchte und Forstwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In this bachelor thesis, black currants (Ribes nigrum L.) from the introductory collection of ProSpecieRara (PSR) were examined for the Blackcurrant Reversion Virus (BRV) and a method for virus elimination in the infected plants was searched. &#13;
PSR collects various types of berries in the introductory collection and in the national berry collection (both in Riehen BS). The aim is to preserve old varieties and to gain knowledge about them. BRV is the worst disease in R. nigrum. It causes large yield losses and changes the morphological characteristics of the variety - this impairs the work of PSR. Plant viruses can hardly be eliminated in the field, and plants usually have to be removed if they are infested. However, removing is not a possibility for PSR because then, the varieties are not preserved. Therefore, a different solution to this problem was sought.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>In dieser Bachelorarbeit wurden schwarze Johannisbeeren (Ribes nigrum L.) in der Einführungssammlung von ProSpecieRara (PSR) auf das Blackcurrant Reversion Virus (BRV) untersucht und es wurde nach einer Methode zur Virusfreimachung der infizierten Pflanzen gesucht.&#13;
PSR sammelt in der Einführungssammlung und in der nationalen Beerensammlung (beide in Riehen BS) diverse Beerenarten. Das Ziel ist, alte Sorten zu erhalten und Wissen darüber zu gewinnen. BRV ist die schlimmste Krankheit bei R. nigrum. Es verursacht grosse Ertragseinbussen und verändert die morphologischen Sorteneigenschaften - dies beeinträchtig die Arbeit von PSR. Pflanzenviren können im Feld kaum bekämpft werden, bei einem Befall müssen die Pflanzen in der Regel entfernt  werden. Dies ist für PSR aber nicht möglich, da dann die Sorten nicht erhalten werden können. Deshalb wurde nach einer anderen Lösung für dieses Problem gesucht.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-14T10:57:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-14T10:57:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2374</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2374</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15360</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15360</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15360</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>68 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16756</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T08:08:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Gezinsondersteuning in de residentiële justitiële setting: standaard?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Knot-Dickscheit, Jana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Drost, Jelle Y.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kalverboer, Margrite E.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Harder, Annemiek T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Knorth, Erik J.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tausendfreund, Tim</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-04-18T08:18:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-18T08:18:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16756</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16756</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16756</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-90-441-2394-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>other</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>De ontwikkeling van kinderen met problemen: gewoon anders</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Garant</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19918</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T12:47:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The role of organizational culture for information technology management in digitalization</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sieber, Marcel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Information technology management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Information technology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Organizational culture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Platform economy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.403: Entscheidungsfindung, Informationsmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The following paper discusses the challenges and benefits of the Fourth Industrial Revolution for information technology management and the corresponding impact on organizations. Exploring the relationship between organizational culture and information technology management in the era of digitalization, it aims to find a model and hypotheses for further study.&#13;
&#13;
Design/methodology/approach: The paper presents a literature review in the research field of information technology management with a focus on the Fourth Industrial Revolution, digitalization, and organizational culture. It structures the findings and develops a conceptional model about the effect of corporate culture on information technology management.&#13;
&#13;
Findings: Although the cited literature hardly examines organizational culture, the review shows several notes of culture-related topics. The paper structures these perceptions along the dimensions“ behaviors,” “artifacts,” “norms,” and “values.” It proposes the dimensions’ direct relationships with success in digitalization as well as mediated effects between them.&#13;
&#13;
Research/practical implications: The study closes a gap in the research of the industry and the field of information technology management. It contributes to the discussion and awareness of the impact of organizational culture in information technology. Further research needs more exploration of the topic, the models, and theory as well as empirical tests of hypotheses.&#13;
&#13;
Originality/value: The paper reflects the role of organizational culture in the information technology research where a shortcoming is observable. It reshapes a layered architecture of corporate culture and proposes an adapted model for the effects of organizational culture on information technology management in the era of digitalization.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-04-16T08:14:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-04-16T08:14:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.18267/pr.2019.dvo.2316.0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.18267/pr.2019.dvo.2316.0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19918</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19918</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19918</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-80-245-2316-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Innovation management, entrepreneurship and sustainability : proceedings of the 7th international conference</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>7th International Conference Innovation Management, Entrepreneurship and Sustainability (IMES 2019 ), Prague, Czech Republic, 30-31 May 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>University of Economics, Oeconomica Publishing House</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15438</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T10:11:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1075</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1074</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1076</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Baukultur und Identität</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Staufer, Astrid</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Baukultur</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Denkmalpflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>720: Architektur</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-02-18T16:14:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-18T16:14:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15438</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15438</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15438</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Tagung Patrimoine 2018 der KSD - CSCM - CSSM, Regensdorf, 16. November 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2251</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T09:47:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Innovative, non-stirred bioreactors in scales form milliliters up to 1000 L for suspension cultures of cells using disposable bags and containers - a Swiss contribution</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Werner, Sören</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eibl-Schindler, Regine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lettenbauer, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Röll, Marcel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eibl, Dieter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>De Jesus, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zhang, Xiaowei</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stettler, Matthieu</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tissot, Stephanie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bürkie, Cedric</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Broccard, Gilles</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kühner, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tanner, Rolf</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Baldi, Lucia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hacker, David</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wurm, Florian M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Disposable bioreactors</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Engineering characteristics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>High density cho cultures</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Orbitally shaken</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wave mixed</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>660: Technische Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Innovative mixing principles in bioreactors, for example using the rocking of a platform to induce a backwards and forwards 'wave', or using orbital shaking to generate a 'wave' that runs round in a cylindrical container, have proved to be successful for the suspension cultures of cells, especially when combined with disposable materials. This article presents an overview of the engineering characteristics when these new principles are applied in bioreactors, and case studies covering scales of operation from milliliters to 1000 Liters.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-01-29T15:05:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-29T15:05:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.2533/chimia.2010.819</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.2533/chimia.2010.819</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2251</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2251</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2251</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0009-4293</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Chimia</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schweizerische Chemische Gesellschaft</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4339</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:00:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wohlbefinden von Kindern in Tagesschulen : differenzierte Ansichten aus ihrer Perspektive</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Chiapparini, Emanuela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kadrie, Selmani</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schuler, Patricia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kappler, Christa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Soziale Arbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wohlbefinden</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kinder- und Jugendforschung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Tagesschule</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>371: Schulen und schulische Tätigkeiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Das Wohlbefinden von Schülerinnen und Schülern in Schweizer Schulen ist gemäss der letzten PISA-Studie (OECD 2017) und im Vergleich zu anderen OECD-Ländern hoch eingestuft. Gleichzeitig gilt Wohlbefinden als Qualitätsmerkmal von Tagesschulen (Brückel et al. 2014). Jedoch wurde dieses Thema bislang kaum empirisch erforscht. Die Stadt Zürich ist die erste Schweizer Gemeinde, die flächendeckend gebundene Tagesschulen eingeführt hat. Hier knüpft der Beitrag an, der im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationalfond Studie „AusTEr“ der Frage nachgeht, wie Heranwachsende dieser Schulen ihr Wohlbefinden kollektiv deuten. Begriffstheoretische Ausgangspunkte bilden die drei Dimensionen ‘self‘, ‘agency‘ und ‘security‘ des Wohlbefindens von Heranwachsenden (Fattore et al. 2012), die mit den Befunden aus einer Tiefenanalyse nach der Grounded Theory (Strauss &amp; Corbin 1997) von geführten Gruppendiskussionen (Bohnsack 1999) mit den Heranwachsenden diskutiert werden. Erste Befunde aus der Analyse weisen darauf hin, dass die grundsätzlich positive Einstellung der Heranwachsenden im Zuge der Einführung vom Tagesschulbetrieb differenzierter zu betrachten ist.&#13;
Im Vortrag werden die theoretischen und praxisbezogenen Bedingungen hinter dem gewandelten Ansatz des Wohlbefindens von Kindern in der Bewegung der Ganztagsbildung reflektiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T08:01:51Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T08:01:51Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4339</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4339</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4339</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>DGfE Kongress «Bewegungen», Essen, Deutschland, 18.-21. März 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11231</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-30T08:35:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Schweizer Forscher definieren Handlungsfelder für Stadtgrün : Nachhaltigkeit im Grünraummanagement</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brack, Florian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hagenbuch, Reto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Grünstadt Schweiz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Freiraum</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Forschung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>711: Raumplanung (Städtebau)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-09-28T14:32:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-28T14:32:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://stadtundgruen.de/artikel/schweizer-forscher-definieren-handlungsfelder-fuer-stadtgruen-1818.html</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11231</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0948-9770</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Stadt + Grün</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Patzer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18635</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-12T10:29:12Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Downright : a framework and toolchain for privilege handling</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Neuhaus, Stephan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schweizer, Remo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Security</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Privileges</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Linux</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Unix</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>© 2019 IEEE.  Personal use of this material is permitted.  Permission from IEEE must be obtained for all other uses, in any current or future media, including reprinting/republishing this material for advertising or promotional purposes, creating new collective works, for resale or redistribution to servers or lists, or reuse of any copyrighted component of this work in other works.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>We propose Downright, a novel framework based on Seccomp, Berkeley Packet Filter, and PTrace, that makes it possible to equip new and existing C applications with a request broker architecture.  An extensive configuration language allows AppArmor-like configuration that supports programmers in building rules for system call parameter validation and result sanitization. Access to these privileged function calls can be restricted both within Linux kernel and user spaces.&#13;
&#13;
Downright's main strength compared to related approaches is that it implements a complete mediation request broker architecture, in which all system calls are vetted before execution, either by the kernel or by a request broker, which runs as another process.  This isolates the main program from many failures due to programming bugs and attacks, which would have to pass not only the attacked program, but the request broker also. We argue that this makes acquiring and releasing elevated privileges easier and safer. Downright eliminates the need to write Seccomp programs, instead allowing policies to be expressed declaratively through a rich policy language.&#13;
  &#13;
We demonstrate the viability of this approach by instrumenting nginx, an industrial-strength web server and reverse proxy. While this instrumentation takes only a single line of code, we argue that even this effort can be avoided by suitable C runtime code. We show that Downright's overhead is substantial, halving nginx's perfomance, but propose measures for optimisation.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-11-07T14:30:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-11-07T14:30:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1109/SecDev.2019.00019</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-18635</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1109/SecDev.2019.00019</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-18635</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18635</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18635</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18635</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-5386-7289-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0018-9219</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the 2019 IEEE Secure Development (SecDev) Conference</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>IEEE SecDev 2019, McLean, USA, 25 - 27 September 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the IEEE</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>IEEE</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1102</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T13:56:51Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_52</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Auswirkung von Sport auf die Harninkontinenz bei jungen Athletinnen : Teilprojekt des Forschungsprojekts „pelvisuisse-Toilette“</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Arnold, Jennifer</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Schweizerische Gesellschaft für Blasenschwäche schätzt, dass weltweit über 200 Millionen Menschen an ungewolltem Urinverlust leiden. Da sich viele Patienten ihrer Krankheit wegen schämen, wird von einer massiv höheren Dunkelziffer ausgegangen. Aus der Angst die Toilette nicht rechtzeitig erreichen zu können, erfolgen sozial isolierte Lebensformen.

Die Bachelorarbeit nähert sich dem Thema Harninkontinenz sowohl aus einer theoretischen wie auch praktischen Perspektive. In theoretischen Teil untersuchten Petra Egli und Jennifer Arnold eine je spezifische Gruppe von Betroffenen. Vorliegend wird dargestellt, wie sich Sport auf die Harninkontinenz junger Athletinnen auswirken kann. Die Aufarbeitung wissenschaftlicher Studien dazu legt nahe, dass Sport mit hoher intraabdominaler Druckerzeugung die Harnkontinenz negativ beeinflussen kann. Spezifisches Beckenbodentraining stellt jedoch eine mögliche Form der Kompensation von Harninkontinenz bei Athletinnen dar, obwohl signifikante Erhebungen für eine Qualifizierung bislang noch ausstehen. Über die effizientesten Trainingsmethoden für eine Stärkung des Beckenbodenmuskels wird durch ein Interview mit einer Fachperson Aufschluss gegeben.

Der Verein pelvisuisse möchte in Zusammenarbeit mit der Schweizerischen Gesellschaft für Blasenschwäche Betroffene ins soziale Leben reintegrieren. Dazu erarbeiteten Egli und Arnold ein Netzwerk von öffentlichen Toiletten in Zürich für Personen mit Harninkontinenz, das in eine Stadtkarte übertragen wurde. Das Ziel von diesem Forschungsprojekt war doppelt angelegt: Die Anbieter für die Thematik der Harninkontinenz zu sensibilisieren als auch konkret Abhilfe für die Betroffenen zu schaffen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2016-07-28T15:01:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-07-28T15:01:08Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1103</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1103</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1102</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1102</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1102</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14809</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-01-31T09:42:51Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Modelling the transformation of heat supply and demand : a case study for the residential building stock of the city of St. Gall</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kytzia, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mosimann, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Burgy, Raffael Severin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Heizenergie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Gebäudepark</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wohngebäude</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Modellierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>690: Hausbau und Bauhandwerk</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In Northern European countries, the transformation of prevailing systems to supply and use energy for heating residential buildings is considered a major challenge in urban development. Ongoing renewal and growth in the residential building stock allows increasing energy efficiency by introducing new buildings standards. By additionally encouraging alternative sources for heat supply such as geothermal and solar energy, a significant reduction of greenhouse gas emissions seems feasible. To evaluate options and conditions favourable for such a development, we developed a spatial explicit, dynamic model for the transformation of the residential building stock. This model was used to assess energy demand and greenhouse gas emissions for heating the residential buildings in the City of St. Gall and analyse alternative scenarios for future development. The model incorporates the communal energy plan as well as empirical data of 50 refurbishment projects (estimates for construction costs and gains in energy efficiency). Modelbased scenario calculations show that the City of St. Gall can reach its ambitious goals in energy policy within the next 50 years. However, the municipality and private property owners have to provide substantial funding and make a great effort in refurbishing their old building stock.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-01-31T09:42:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-31T09:42:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14809</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14809</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14809</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>SB13 Graz : sustainable buildings construction products &amp; technologies</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Verlag der Technischen Universität Graz</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4812</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-24T13:26:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Das Formulieren von Zielen durch Schweizer ErgotherapeutInnen : ein Forschungsprojekt in vielen Sprachen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Roos, Kim Caroline</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Page, Julie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Demburger, Magali</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rossini Drecq, Emmanuelle</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Galli Hudec, Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kuster, Erica</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Margot, Isabel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meyer, Sylvie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>000: Allgemeines und Wissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615.8515: Ergotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Das Forschungsprojekt "Goal Phrasing in Swiss Occupational Therapy" untersucht den aktuellen Stand der Schweizerischen ErgotherapeutInnen im Bereich Zielformulierung in drei Sprachregionen der Schweiz (Italienisch, Französisch und Deutsch). Durchgeführt wird das Projekt von den Ergotherapieforschungsgruppen an den Fachhochschulen in Lausanne, Manno und Winterthur (Projektleitung). EVS / ASE und SRK sind Praxispartner in diesem KTI-finanzierten Projekt. Durch die Forschungsarbeit sollen aktuell in der Schweiz praktizierende ErgotherapeutInnen in diesem wichtigen Teil des therapeutischen Prozesses unterstützt werden, indem verschiedene evidenz-basierte Produkte entwickelt werden, wie z.B. eine Fortbildung oder Leitlinien. 
Laufzeit des Projekts ist: 1. Juli 2010 bis 31. Juni 2012.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-04T14:35:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-04T14:35:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4812</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4812</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4812</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0258-672X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Ergotherapie</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ErgotherapeutInnen-Verband Schweiz</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16133</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-25T16:52:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Das Recht und die Regulierung von Erdwärme</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Abegg, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dörig, Leonie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Energierecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Umweltrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Baurecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Planungsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>343: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Sachen-, Finanz-, Steuer- und Wirtschaftsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>344: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Arbeits-, Sozial-, Bildungs- und Kulturrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Mit der zunehmenden Nutzung der Erdwärme sind Konflikte mit Nachbarn und mit Infrastrukturprojekten vorprogrammiert. Die Suche nach dem anwendbaren Recht und die Frage nach der richtigen Regulierung bieten vorderhand mehr Fragen als Antworten. Der Beitrag fasst den Stand der Debatte zusammen und weist auf zentrale Aspekte bei der Suche nach dem richtigen Recht hin.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-03-18T14:59:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-18T14:59:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-09-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://jusletter.weblaw.ch/juslissues/2017/907/das-recht-und-die-re_e3fb75dbd5.html</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16133</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1424-7410</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Jusletter</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Weblaw</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6569</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T10:11:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Resistance risk evaluation of fludioxonil : a new phenylpyrrole fungicide</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schüepp, H.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schwinn, F.J.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hilber, Urs</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>630: Landwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-06T08:57:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-06T08:57:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1994</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6569</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6569</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6569</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-0948404771</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Fungicide resistance : Proceedings of a Symposium Held in Reading in March 1994 with the BSPP</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Symposium «Plant Pathology», Reading, United Kingdom, 28-30 March 1994</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>British Crop Protection Council (BCPC)</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1788</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T12:31:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>JAMES : mit einem Fokus auf die Handynutzung kurz vor der Matura</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Waller, Gregor</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2017-12-13T15:08:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-12-13T15:08:32Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-09-15</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1788</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1788</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1788</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>SDBB Tagung «IT kreativ genutzt», Zürich, 15. September 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2159</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:00:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ernährungsbiografie : Essen im Lebensverlauf</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brombach, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>300: Sozialwissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>613.2: Diätetik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>forum. ernährung heute (f.eh), Verein zur Förderung von Ernährungsinformation</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22T15:32:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22T15:32:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2159</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2159</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2159</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>5. f.eh-Symposium «Demografische Revo­lution: Reifeprüfung auf dem Teller», Wien, Österreich, 26. Juni 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21224</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-16T07:22:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>§ 52 Delegation der Geschäftsführung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Keller, Nicolas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meier, Romuald</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-01-11T09:11:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-01-11T09:11:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21224</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21224</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21224</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7190-4018-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Handbuch Schweizer GmbH-Recht : Musterdokumente, Checklisten und Übersichten für die Praxis</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Helbing &amp; Lichtenhahn</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12026</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T10:17:47Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The energy principle in a model of electric braking of a flywheel</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Corni, Federico</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dumont, Elisabeth</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fuchs, Hans Ulrich</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schütz, Edy</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>530: Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-10-22T13:46:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-22T13:46:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4834</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4834</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12026</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12026</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12026</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>GIREP Seminar on the Occasion of GIREP 50th Anniversary, Krakow, Poland, 30 August - 3 September 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/762</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-19T13:39:04Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_236</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_237</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ich nehme die Pille – na und? : Bewusstsein von Psychologiestudierenden der Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften über die Nebenwirkungen der hormonellen Schwangerschaftsverhütung auf somatischer und psychischer Ebene</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Eltayeb-Keller, Miriam</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Koller, Joanna</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:10:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:10:05Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-762</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-762</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/762</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/762</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/762</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15560</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-02-20T15:29:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Aufbruch zu neuen Kompetenzen : Schlussbericht zum Programm EFFI-BAU</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kunz, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Impulsprogramm</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bauwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>338: Produktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>1998 bis 2000 lief in der Schweiz ein Impulsprogramm des Bundes mit dem Titel "Effizienzpotentiale der Schweizer Bauwirtschaft". Es umfasste verschiedene Projekte und Initiativen, um der Schweizer Bauwirtschaft aus der Rezession der 90er Jahre herauszuhelfen. Der vorliegende Bericht stellt den Schlussbericht des Programms dar.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-20T15:29:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-20T15:29:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1999</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15560</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15560</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15560</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Bundesamt für Berufsbildung und Technologie</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4728</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T12:56:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Design of a prospective payment system for inpatient psychiatric care in Switzerland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wieser, Simon</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dettling, Marcel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riguzzi, Marco</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pletscher, Mark</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Psychiatry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Prospective payments system</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Health economics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hospital</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.1041: Gesundheitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.11: Krankenhäuser und verwandte Einrichtungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-04T12:05:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-04T12:05:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4728</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4728</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4728</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>International Health Economics Association Congress 2014, Dublin, Ireland, July 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8114</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-26T07:17:14Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Einfluss von Routine auf das Blickverhalten im Strassenverkehr</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Amstad, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hackenfort, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Diener, Sarah</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tsimitselis, Lambros</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Routine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Blickverhalten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Unfall</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Verkehrssicherheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>363: Umwelt- und Sicherheitsprobleme</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In einer Pilotstudie wurde an der Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften (ZHAW) das Blickverhalten von Fussgängern mittels mobiler Eye-Tracking-Brille untersucht. Im Fokus stand dabei die Fragestellung, ob Routine und Ablenkung dazu führen, dass sicherheitsrelevante Hinweise weniger beachtet werden. Tatsächlich führten weder die mehrmalige Exposition (Routine), noch eine kognitive Beanspruchung (Ablenkung) zu einer Veränderung der Fixationsdauer bei sicherheitsrelevanten Stimuli. Es zeigte sich stattdessen der inhaltlich positive Effekt, dass unter Ablenkung den nicht-sicherheitsrelevanten Stimuli deutlich weniger Aufmerksamkeit beigemessen wurde. Das Blickverhalten der Probanden deutet somit stark auf ein Kompensationsverhalten hin, demzufolge wegen der kognitiven Belastung versucht wird, die Sicherheit anhand einer Kompensationsstrategie möglichst aufrecht zu erhalten. Dass dies allerdings im Endeffekt tatsächlich erfolglos sein könnte, zeigte die inhaltliche Auswertung der sicherheitsrelevanten Merkmale, die Probanden verarbeiteten – bzw. nicht tiefer verarbeiteten. Diese "trügerische Sicherheit" kann sich stark unfallerhöhend auswirken. Implikationen für die Unfallforschung, beispielsweise im Kontext von so genannten "looked but failed to see"- Unfallursachen werden diskutiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-16T08:10:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-16T08:10:53Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8114</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8114</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8114</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1663-4888</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Strassenverkehr</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Dike</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6773</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-19T14:50:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wege zur Integration : eine Einführung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Steinebach, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Integration</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sonderkindergarten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Integrativer Kindergarten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Integration</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Inklusion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-13T07:12:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-13T07:12:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1997</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6773</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6773</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6773</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7841-0946-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Integration auf dem Weg : die Öffnung einer Sondereinrichtung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Lambertus</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5903</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-11T07:31:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Teil-Plattformen : was am Teilen fasziniert</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Baur, Nicole Anja</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Sharing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Economy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Community</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Armut</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Plattform</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Online</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>330: Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-16T14:13:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-16T14:13:03Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3656</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3656</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5903</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5903</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5903</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1422-8432</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>SozialAktuell</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>AvenirSocial</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23814</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-12-22T13:51:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>A semi-automated Multiphysics simulation software for process design in the powder coating industry</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Siyahhan, Bercan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Boiger, Gernot Kurt</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Coatsim</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Multiphysics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Simulation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>CFD</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Cloud</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Cloud computing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>530: Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Powder coating is a widely used industrial process to obtain functional or aesthetic surface properties on manufactured parts. In a previous contribution we have introduced a Multiphysics methodology to simulate real life coating applications with a Eulerian-Lagrangian solver within the OpenFOAM framework, incorporating multiple periodically moving coating pistols.&#13;
In the scope of the current study, the aforementioned methodology has been semi-automated to develop the software coatSim. The aim of the software is to provide a sequential work-flow for setting up and simulating practical coating applications for all users, regardless of their expertise in the field of computational science. A database of pre-generated coating chambers and pistol geometries is at the disposal of the user. The database can be complemented by any substrate geometry uploaded. Then the user can interactively perform geometric operations via a combination of Paraview and Python libraries to manipulate STL files. An elaborate meshing scheme allows the user to automatically mesh each of the pistol regions and the coating chamber with the possibility of coarsening or refining the mesh through a single scaling parameter. As the material and process parameters are prescribed, the software performs the necessary operations to set up the case in the correct sequence. The finalized cases are uploaded to the cloud platform KaleidoSim through its extensive API (Application Programming Interface) capabilities in order to perform large series of simulations (e.g.: parametric studies, optimization runs) online.&#13;
The coatSim software bridges the gap between the practical application and the theoretical expertise required to accurately simulate a coating process in OpenFOAM. Hence, CFD becomes a viable predictive tool for process design in the powder coating industry, as coatSim allows an intuitive workflow without in depth expertise in the field of CFD.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-12-22T13:51:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-12-22T13:51:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5c9f89c101232c1d41297d67/t/61a4a918db92b17c6a8ce63e/1638181147118/MULTIPHYSICS+2021+Abstract+Booklet.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23814</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2409-1669</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2409-7527</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>International Conference of Multiphysics, Online, 9-10 December 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>International Society of Multiphysics</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22926</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-27T13:16:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Synergistic interaction between the type III secretion system of the endophytic bacterium Pantoea agglomerans DAPP‐PG 734 and the virulence of the causal agent of olive knot Pseudomonas savastanoi pv. savastanoi DAPP‐PG 722</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Moretti, Chiaraluce</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rezzonico, Fabio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Orfei, Benedetta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cortese, Chiara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moreno‐Pérez, Alba</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>van den Burg, Harrold A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Onofri, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Firrao, Giuseppe</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ramos, Cayo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Smits, Theo H.M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Buonaurio, Roberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Pantoea agglomerans</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pseudomonas savastanoi pv. savastanoi</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pseudomonas syringae complex</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>T3SS</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Endophyte</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hypersensitive reaction</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mutant</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Olive knot community</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>579: Mikrobiologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The endophytic bacterium Pantoea agglomerans DAPP-PG 734 was previously isolated from olive knots caused by infection with Pseudomonas savastanoi pv. savastanoi DAPP-PG 722. Whole-genome analysis of this P. agglomerans strain revealed the presence of a Hypersensitive response and pathogenicity (Hrp) type III secretion system (T3SS). To assess the role of the P. agglomerans T3SS in the interaction with P. savastanoi pv. savastanoi, we generated independent knockout mutants in three Hrp genes of the P. agglomerans DAPP-PG 734 T3SS (hrpJ, hrpN, and hrpY). In contrast to the wildtype control, all three mutants failed to cause a hypersensitive response when infiltrated in tobacco leaves, suggesting that P. agglomerans T3SS is functional and injects effector proteins in plant cells. In contrast to P. savastanoi pv. savastanoi DAPP-PG 722, the wildtype strain P. agglomerans DAPP-PG 734 and its Hrp T3SS mutants did not cause olive knot disease in 1-year-old olive plants. Coinoculation of P. savastanoi pv. savastanoi with P. agglomerans wildtype strains did not significantly change the knot size, while the DAPP-PG 734 hrpY mutant induced a significant decrease in knot size, which could be complemented by providing hrpY on a plasmid. By epifluorescence microscopy and confocal laser scanning microscopy, we found that the localization patterns in knots were nonoverlapping for P. savastanoi pv. savastanoi and P. agglomerans when coinoculated. Our results suggest that suppression of olive plant defences mediated by the Hrp T3SS of P. agglomerans DAPP-PG 734 positively impacts the virulence of P. savastanoi pv. savastanoi DAPP-PG 722.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-07-30T13:41:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-07-30T13:41:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-07-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1111/mpp.13105</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-22926</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1111/mpp.13105</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-22926</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22926</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22926</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22926</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1364-3703</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1464-6722</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>34268839</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Molecular Plant Pathology</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Wiley</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7187</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-02T07:59:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Fundraising Management</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Labaronne, Leticia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Seger, Bruno</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.1: Organisation und Finanzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Non-Profit-Organisation, Spenden, Stiftung, Sponsoring, Ressourcenbeschaffung  Dieses Buch richtet sich in erster Linie an Personen, die sich für Fundraising interessieren und einen ersten, umfassenden Überblick gewinnen möchten. Ebenso eignet es sich als Lehrmittel oder ergänzende Lektüre für den Unterricht. Im Unterschied zu einigen Fundraising-Fachbüchern haben wir besonderen Wert auf eine zeitgemässe didaktische Aufarbeitung gelegt. Neben der Darstellung der wichtigsten Methoden und Instrumente spielen die Vermittlung von strategischen Analysemethoden und die Erstellung integrierter Fundraising-Konzepte eine zentrale Rolle. Somit erhalten auch erfahrene Fundraiserinnen und Fundraiser Anregungen für die Bewältigung ihrer strategischen Aufgaben. Die Inhalte dieses Buches beziehen sich vorwiegend auf die Praxis in der Schweiz. Wo es sinnvoll erschien, wurden Fakten und Erfahrungen aus anderen Ländern einbezogen. Viele grundlegende Inhalte sind deshalb auch für Interessenten aus Deutschland oder Österreich nützlich.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-22T09:14:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-22T09:14:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7187</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7187</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7187</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7281-3731-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>SML essentials</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>76 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>vdf Hochschulverlag</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/252</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:42:45Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_50</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Nahtoderfahrung – der Einblick in ein aussergewöhnliches Erlebnis : welches Wissen benötigen Pflegefachpersonen um Menschen ab 18 Jahren, welche eine Nahtoderfahrung erlebt haben, adäquat unterstützen zu können?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Egli, Alexandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gfeller, Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:02:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:02:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-252</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-252</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/252</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/252</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/252</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken completeListSize="24863" cursor="48">oai_dc////4900</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
