<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="static/style.xsl"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-06-08T16:55:14Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" resumptionToken="oai_dc////12100">https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/oai/request/</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2033</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T09:26:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ausbildungs- und Berufswahl als Entscheidung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schreiber, Marc</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>158: Angewandte Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>331: Arbeitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-01-16T14:23:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-01-16T14:23:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2033</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2033</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2033</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-8258-0536-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Berufliche Übergänge : psychologische Grundlagen für die Berufs-, Studien- und Laufbahnberatung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>LIT</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18108</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T10:13:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Guidelines for the pharmacological acute treatment of major depression : conflicts with current evidence as demonstrated with the German S3-guidelines</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Plöderl, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hengartner, Michael Pascal</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>616.8: Neurologie und Krankheiten des Nervensystems</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Several international guidelines for the acute treatment of moderate to severe unipolar depression recommend a first-line treatment with antidepressants (AD). This is based on the assumption that AD obviously outperform placebo, at least in the case of severe depression. The efficacy of AD for severe depression can only be definitely clarified with individual patient data, but corresponding studies have only been available recently. In this paper, we point out discrepancies between the content of guidelines and the scientific evidence by taking a closer look at the German S3-guidelines for the treatment of depression. Based on recent studies and a systematic review of studies using individual patient data, it turns out that AD are marginally superior to placebo in both moderate and severe depression. The clinical significance of this small drug-placebo-difference is questionable, even in the most severe forms of depression. In addition, the modest efficacy is likely an overestimation of the true efficacy due to systematic method biases. There is no related discussion in the S3-guidelines, despite substantial empirical evidence confirming these biases. In light of recent data and with their underlying biases, the recommendations in the S3-guidelines are in contradiction with the current evidence. The risk-benefit ratio of AD for severe depression may be similar to the one estimated for mild depression and thus could be unfavorable. Downgrading of the related grade of recommendation would be a logical consequence.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-09-05T13:37:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-09-05T13:37:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-019-2230-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-18108</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1186/s12888-019-2230-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-18108</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18108</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18108</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18108</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1471-244X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>BMC Psychiatry</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>BioMed Central</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13411</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T13:39:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Simulated resumption of the North Atlantic meridional overturning circulation : slow basin-wide advection and abrupt local convection</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Renold, Manuel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Raible, C.C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Yoshimori, M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stocker, T.F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>551: Geologie und Hydrologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The resumption process of the North Atlantic meridional overturning circulation (MOC) is investigated in a series of freshwater hosing experiments using a comprehensive coupled climate model. Four different freshwater perturbations are applied to the North Atlantic between 50°N and 70°N leading to a substantial weakening of MOC and an expansion of winter sea ice cover over the Greenland-Iceland-Norwegian (GIN) Seas. Deactivating the freshwater forcing leads to a two-phase recovery of the MOC. The first phase is a slow basin-wide advection process whereas the second phase is an abrupt, decadal-scale transition, located in the North Atlantic. The slow basin-wide advection process to an intermediate state of the MOC is characterized by a restart of the deep water production in the area of the subpolar gyre and the Irminger Basin. However, the ice cover over the GIN Seas remains, whereas the surface density gradually increases in the GIN Seas on a century time scale. The length of this intermediate state depends on the strength of freshwater perturbation, which determines the magnitude of the meridional density gradient in the North Atlantic. The second transition phase is triggered by a model-specific density threshold reached in the GIN Seas. When passed, the MOC abruptly intensifies by ∼60% within 60-80 years. The analysis shows that this abrupt intensification only depends on surface salinity in the GIN Seas. The model results reveal that the simulated sea ice retreat in the GIN Seas and a rapid increase of the Greenland air temperature of the second phase of the resumption of the MOC are similar in amplitude to temperature proxies observed during Dansgaard-Oeschger events of the last ice age.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-30T10:12:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-30T10:12:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2009.11.005</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.quascirev.2009.11.005</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13411</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13411</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13411</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0277-3791</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Quaternary Science Reviews</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10895</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T14:09:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1315</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1463</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Förderung einer gesunden, ressourcenschonenden Esskultur : Bildungskonzept, Bildungsangebot und Wirkungsanalyse bei Jugendlichen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dettwiler, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stacher, Robin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Esskultur</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Essverhalten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ernährung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bildungskonzept</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bildungsangebot</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Projektwoche</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>300: Sozialwissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>613.2: Diätetik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Good food, a sound environment, good health, the solution of world hunger and a world without animal suffering are desired by most humans. Still Swiss consumers invest less and less money and time into quality products and the preparation of meals, as statistics show. Studies proved: The average Swiss eating habits are the main cause for environmental stress, a major risk factor for the country’s most widespread diseases, the reason for a very intense use of farm animals and partially responsible for world hunger – which is not commonly known. Consumers need the competences that allow them to scrutinize their own habits and to implement solution based approaches. They must know what they eat and understand the consequences of it. They should develop their behavior consciously. This paper examines how an institutional education of juveniles can reach a positive contribution to the aforementioned development.</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Gutes Essen, eine intakte Umwelt, eine gute Gesundheit, die Lösung des Welthungerproblems und eine Welt ohne Tierleid wünschen sich grundsätzlich alle Menschen. Trotzdem sind den Schweizer Konsumierenden hochwertige Lebensmittel und die Mahlzeitenzubereitung immer weniger Geld und Zeit wert, wie Statistiken belegen. Studien zeigen: Das Essverhalten der Durchschnittsschweizer ist der Hauptverursacher ihrer Umweltbelastungen, ein Hauptrisikofaktor für ihre Volkskrankheiten, der Grund für die äusserst intensive Nutztierhaltung und ein Auslöser von Welthunger – vielen ist das nicht bewusst. Die Konsumierenden benötigen Kompetenzen, die das Hinterfragen des eigenen Essverhaltens und das Umsetzen von Lösungsansätzen ermöglichen. Sie müssen wissen, was sie essen, und die Auswirkungen davon verstehen. Ihr Verhalten sollen sie bewusst gestalten können. Die vorliegende Arbeit untersuchte, wie die institutionelle Bildung von Jugendlichen einen positiven Beitrag dazu leisten kann.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-20T13:26:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-20T13:26:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-2152</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-2152</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10895</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10895</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10895</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>188 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23830</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-04T08:09:44Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Tutorial on OpenFOAM &amp; kaleidosim : compile and run custom OpenFOAM solvers in the cloud using kaleidosim</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Boiger, Gernot Kurt</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sharman, Darren</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Michel Rivero, Jhimy</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Siyahhan, Bercan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Boldrini, Marlon</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lienhard, Viktor</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>OpenFOAM</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kaleidosim</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Compile</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Custom solvers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Cloud</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Simulation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Multiphysics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>CFD</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>530: Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>YouTube</dc:description>
          <dc:description>In this video Prof. G. Boiger of ICP Institute of Computational Physics ZHAW Zurich University of Applied Sciences shows how to compile and run custom OpenFOAM solvers in the cloud using Kaleidosim. This feature was inspired by colleagues from our aR&amp;D team here at ICP/ZHAW like Bercan Siyahhan, Marlon Boldrini and Viktor Lienhard as well as by customers, contributors and friends of Kaleidosim Technologies AG like: Dr. Christian Witz of TU-Graz (see: christian.witz@tu-graz.at) or Dr. József Nagy to whom special thanks go out. &#13;
&#13;
How it works: 1.) Copy &amp; Paste any folder of any self-composed OpenFoam application into the OpenFoam case folder you wish to upload and run in Kaleidosim #cloud platform. 2.) Zip case folder containing case set-up &amp; source code of self-composed OpenFoam application(s). 3.) Set up an OpenFoam project within Kaleidosim cloud platform &amp; start case creation wizard (if unsure how: press 'Show Tutorial' button top-right at Kaleidosim - Dashboard). 4.) In Kaleidosim case-creation-wizard 'Step-2 Choose OpenFoam Solver': choose any standard OpenFoam solver from the list; Even if you do not intend to use it since you are after compiling &amp; running your own application(s). 5.) In Kaleidosim case-creation-wizard 'Step-4 Additional Parameters': enter a bash-script which will step-by-step do the following: 5.1.) Change from case-directory into directory of Library1 (if present), clean links/environment variables using wclean and compile by using wmake libso. Like so: cd ./Library1 wclean wmake libso 5.2) Change back to case-directory, change into directory of SolverA (or any application, if present), clean links/environment variables using wclean and compile by using wmake. Like so: cd .. cd ./SolverA wclean wmake 5.3) Change back to case-directory, and run case using your freshly compiled application SolverA on any number of cores Num_Cores in accordance with the hardware you chose previously in 'Step-3 Computing resources'. Like so: cd .. decomposePar mpirun --allow-run-as-root -np Num_Cores SolverA -parallel reconstructPar rm -r processor* Keep in mind: ... that Ubuntu and OpenFoam installation on Kaleidosim basically work 1:1 equivalently to any local installation. So the wmake compilation procedure does exactly what it would do locally. ... that the code you compile just exists on the very virtual machine(s) you spin-up in order to run your case(s). This means: i) As soon as running of the case(s) is completed and results are moved into storage, the virtual machine(s) are closed and the compiled version of your source code is gone. ii) You will have to repeat the exact same procedure whenever you would like to run self-compiled OpenFoam applications. iii) This is completely safe. No one else will be able to access and/or use your temporarily compiled software, because access to your Kaleidosim account as well as to the virtual machines you spin-up is always encrypted.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-01-04T08:09:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-01-04T08:09:43Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Lehrmaterial</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Bewegte Bilder</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://youtu.be/3QoQAlaCQxk</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23830</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW School of Engineering, ICP Institute of Computational Physics</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9235</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-18T07:15:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Working Poor in der Schweiz : eine Untersuchung zu Ausmass, Ursachen und Problemlagen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Streuli, Elisa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bauer, Tobias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Working poor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Armut</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schweiz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Existenzminimum</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Schweizerische Arbeitskräfteerhebung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>SAKE</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mindestlohn</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Massnahmen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>BFS-Nummer 	299-9905</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Erwerbsarbeit schützt auch in der Schweiz nicht vor Armut. Die Erkenntnis der nationalen Armutsstudie, dass für eine grosse Zahl von Menschen das Einkommen trotz einer vollen Erwerbstätigkeit nicht für die Sicherung der Existenz ausreicht, hat in den letzten Jahren einige Diskussionen ausgelöst. Eine vertiefte empirische Analyse der Gruppe der «Working Poor» fehlte bisher. Die vorliegende Untersuchung, die im Rahmen der Armutsberichterstattung des Bundesamtes für Statistik vom Büro BASS durchgeführt wurde, holt dies nach und stellt gleichzeitig die Grundlagen für eine systematische Berichterstattung zur Risikogruppe der Working Poor bereit.

Die Untersuchung stützt sich auf die Daten der Schweizerischen Arbeitskräfteerhebung SAKE. Sie analysiert die Situation im Jahr 1999 und zeichnet gleichzeitig die Entwicklung von 1991 bis 1999 nach. Im Jahr 1999 gehörten 7,5% der 20- bis 59-jährigen Erwerbstätigen zur Gruppe der Working Poor. Dies sind 250’000 Personen, deren Haushalte 535’000 Haushaltmitglieder (53’000 nicht erwerbstätige Erwachsene und 232’000 Kinder) umfassen. 
Die Quote der «Vollzeit-Working Poor» ist mit 6% deutlich tiefer als jene der «Teilzeit-Working Poor» die 29% beträgt. Zu den «Vollzeit-Working Poor» zählen Erwerbstätige in armen Haushalten, in denen der gesamte Erwerbsumfang aller Haushaltsmitglieder mindestens 36 Wochenstunden entspricht – unabhängig vom individuellen Erwerbsumfang.

Das Risiko, Working Poor zu werden, hängt einerseits von der Stellung auf dem Arbeitsmarkt ab und andererseits von den Kosten im Zusammenhang mit der Betreuung und Unterstützung von Kindern. 
Armut ist in den verschiedenen Gruppen von Erwerbstätigen unterschiedlich verbreitet. Besonders gefährdet sind Frauen, ausländische Staatsangehörige, Alleinerziehende und Paarhaushalte mit drei oder mehr Kindern sowie wenig ausgebildete Personen. Ebenfalls überdurchschnittlich häufig betroffen sind Selbständige (oft ohne Angestellte) und Erwerbstätige in Tieflohn-Bereichen (Landwirtschaft, Gastgewerbe, Verkauf, Privathaushalte). Die Working Poor arbeiten häufig in Teilzeitstellen, in ungesicherten Arbeitsverhältnissen und in Stellen mit atypischen Arbeitszeiten. Besonders markant erhöht ist ihr Anteil an den Erwerbstätigen in der Landwirtschaft sowie an Frauen, die in Detailhandel und Gastgewerbe arbeiten. In den 1990er Jahren hat sich die Working Poor-Quote deutlich erhöht. Auffällig ist der Sprung zwischen 1995 und 1996. Bis 1995 lag die Quote bei rund 5%, 1996 nahm sie auf rund 7% zu. Die Erklärung für diesen Anstieg liegt in der allgemeinen Lohnentwicklung Mitte der 90er Jahre, in der markanten Zunahme der «neuen Selbständigen» sowie der Arbeitsverhältnisse mit nicht dauerhaften Arbeitsverträgen. Der armutsvermindernde Effekt der individuellen Prämienverbilligung kann dabei aus Datengründen nur unzureichend einbezogen werden. Hätten die Paarhaushalte mit Kindern in der Beobachtungsperiode nicht generell den Erwerbsumfang erhöht, wäre die Zahl der Working Poor noch stärker gestiegen. Bei Alleinerziehenden und kinderreichen Familien, denen die zeitlichen Möglichkeiten für mehr Erwerbsarbeit fehlen, stieg die Working Poor-Quote denn auch stark überproportional.
Im biografischen Verlauf zeigt sich ein häufiger Wechsel von Perioden von Armut und Nicht-Armut. Zwar bleiben Personen, die im Vorjahr «Vollzeit-Working Poor» waren, dies fast zur Hälfte auch im Folgejahr. Immerhin schafft die Hälfte innert Jahresfrist den Sprung über die Armutsgrenze. Temporäre Armut ist somit ein verbreitetes Phänomen: Von allen 20- bis 59-Jährigen Erwerbstätigen war fast ein Fünftel innerhalb von fünf Jahre mindestens einmal arm.

Das Phänomen der Working Poor erklärt sich nur teilweise aus einem Tieflohn: Liegt die Tieflohn-Grenze bei 35’000 Franken netto pro Jahr, beträgt der Anteil der Personen mit Tieflohn an allen Working Poor 67%. Werden nur die «vollzeit Erwerbstätigen» betrachtet, sinkt er auf 45%. Die Einführung eines verbindlichen Vollzeit-Mindestlohns in gleicher Höhe würde die Zahl der Working Poor reduzieren, das Phänomen aber nicht zum Verschwinden bringen. Wesentlichen Einfluss auf die Einkommensverhältnisse eines Haushalts haben neben dem Lohnsatz auch die Kinderzahl, der überhaupt mögliche Erwerbsumfang sowie weitere Einkommensquellen.

Die Studie zeigt deutlich, dass das Phänomen der Working Poor nicht auf einen einzelnen Faktor zurückgeführt werden kann. Vielmehr bestimmt ein komplexes Zusammenspiel verschiedenster Faktoren, ob jemand trotz Arbeit arm ist oder nicht. Massnahmen zur Bekämpfung der Armut Erwerbstätiger müssen deshalb in mehreren Politikbereichen gleichzeitig ansetzen: Mit Massnahmen auf dem Arbeitsmarkt und in der Bildungspolitik kann Tieflöhnen und prekarisierten Arbeitsbedingungen begegnet werden.
Insbesondere für Alleinerziehende und kinderreiche Familien sind familienpolitische Massnahmen wie ein höherer Familienlastenausgleich und Verbesserungen der Vereinbarkeit von Familie und Beruf von vorrangiger Bedeutung.

Datengrundlagen: Die Untersuchung stützt sich auf Daten der Schweizerischen Arbeitskräfteerhebung SAKE. Die letzte verfügbare Erhebung von 1999 umfasst eine Stichprobe von 17’720 befragten Personen aus der ständigen Wohnbevölkerung. Nicht einbezogen sind Asylsuchende, Saisonniers und Saisonnières, Grenzgängerinnen und Grenzgänger. Da für diese Untersuchung nur erwerbstätige Personen zwischen 20 und 59 Jahren mit gültiger Antwort zu Haushalts- und Erwerbseinkommen auswertbar sind, reduziert sich die Zahl der Datensätze auf 7395. Die befragten Personen werden mit der in der SAKE verfügbaren individuellen Gewichtung auf die gesamte Bevölkerung hochgerechnet. Daraus resultieren repräsentative Angaben über die Zahl der Working Poor. Vergleichbare Stichproben stehen auch für die Vorjahre ab 1991 zur Verfügung.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-20T13:36:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-20T13:36:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2001</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/de/home/statistiken/kataloge-datenbanken/publikationen.assetdetail.337466.html</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9235</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-303-13035-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Statistik der Schweiz : Fachbereich : 13 Soziale Sicherheit</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>48 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Bundesamt für Statistik</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6793</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T14:48:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Raumnutzung des Libellen-Schmetterlingshafts nördlich der Alpen : Folgerungen für den Artenschutz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Krüsi, Bertil</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schlegel, Jürg</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>333: Bodenwirtschaft und Ressourcen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>590: Tiere (Zoologie)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Spatial Use of the Owly Sulphur north of the Alps – Consequences for species protection Isolation of habitats remains one of the most severe threats to biodiversity, and it is vital to enable exchange among habitat islands by creating suitable stepping stones or connecting habitat corridors. The Owly Sulfur Libelloides coccajus has been heavily affected by isolation north of the Alps since it depends on dry and warm open forests and on grasslands which should not be cut before early August. The study investigated flying habits of this protected species in order to elucidate both its core habitat and adjacent areas used for hunting and mating, with special regard to obstacles. The results revealed that wind protection seems to be one of the prime requirements for L. coccajus, whereas land use and thus vegetation type play a minor role, at least as far as hunting is concerned. For instance, L. coccajus was frequently observed to fly and hunt above corn fields and other crops. Apparently, neither hedge rows nor crop fields seem to seriously hamper the dispersal of L. coccajus. This finding is very important for designing and creating effective stepping stones and connecting corridors between the remaining L. coccajus populations.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-13T08:12:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-13T08:12:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.nul-online.de/artikel.dll?AID=3628079&amp;MID=82030</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6793</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0940-6808</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1869-5191</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Naturschutz und Landschaftsplanung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Ulmer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24450</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-21T12:50:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Resolving taxonomic confusion : establishing the genus Phytobacter on the list of clinically relevant Enterobacteriaceae</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Smits, Theo H. M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Arend, Lavinia N. V. S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cardew, Sofia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tång-Hallbäck, Erika</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mira, Marcelo T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moore, Edward R. B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sampaio, Jorge L. M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rezzonico, Fabio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pillonetto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Phytobacter diazotrophicus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Phytobacter ursingii</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Phytobacter palmae</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Genomics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Identification</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Taxonomy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>579: Mikrobiologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Although many clinically significant strains belonging to the family Enterobacteriaceae fall into a restricted number of genera and species, there is still a substantial number of isolates that elude this classification and for which proper identification remains challenging. With the current improvements in the field of genomics, it is not only possible to generate high-quality data to accurately identify individual nosocomial isolates at the species level and understand their pathogenic potential but also to analyse retrospectively the genome sequence databases to identify past recurrences of a specific organism, particularly those originally published under an incorrect or outdated taxonomy. We propose a general use of this approach to classify further clinically relevant taxa, i.e., Phytobacter spp., that have so far gone unrecognised due to unsatisfactory identification procedures in clinical diagnostics. Here, we present a genomics and literature-based approach to establish the importance of the genus Phytobacter as a clinically relevant member of the Enterobacteriaceae family.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-03-02T14:57:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-03-02T14:57:19Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-02-15</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10096-022-04413-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-24450</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/s10096-022-04413-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-24450</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/24450</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24450</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/24450</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0934-9723</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1435-4373</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>European Journal of Clinical Microbiology &amp; Infectious Diseases</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3000</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-24T14:04:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Polyphenol, anthocyanin and antioxidant content in different parts of maqui fruits (Aristotelia chilensis) during ripening and conservation treatments after harvest</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>González, Benita</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vogel, Hermine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Razmilic, Iván</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wolfram, Evelyn</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Frozen fruit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pulp</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>HPTLC</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Dried fruit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>630: Landwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Maqui, Aristotelia chilensis (Mol.) Stuntz, Elaeocarpaceae, is a berry with one of the highest antioxidantactivities known, and which is exploited from the wild as raw material for nutraceutical products. Thepresent work studies factors that might affect fruit quality in further industrial processing and proposesHPTLC fingerprint methods for routine quality control of metabolites and radical scavengers. Polyphenoland anthocyanin concentrations in fruit were determined in cultivated maqui. Polyphenol concentrationdid not vary significantly during the ripening process, but differed from one growing season to another(2.1 and 2.8 g GAE/100 g dry weight). Anthocyanin concentration increased during maturation from 0.07to 1.13 g Cy-3-glu/100 g dry weight, whereas antioxidant ORAC value remained stable (194-241 molTE/g DW). Anthocyanins were concentrated only in the fleshy parts of ripe fruits (4.2 g Cy-3-glu/100 gDW), while other polyphenols were found in the seeds (2.1 g GAE/100 g DW). Polyphenol and anthocyanincontents did not decrease during desiccation, cooling or freezing processes. Desiccation approximatelydoubled sugar contents, from 24.5◦Brix in fresh to 50◦Brix in dry fruit. Frozen fruit retained their solublesolids content and anthocyanins, while polyphenols increased.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-23T15:17:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-23T15:17:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.indcrop.2015.06.038</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1016/j.indcrop.2015.06.038</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3000</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3000</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3000</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0926-6690</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Industrial Crops and Products</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20009</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-21T12:30:39Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Dual oxygen and temperature sensing with single indicator using multi-task-learning neural networks</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Venturini, Francesca</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Michelucci, Umberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Baumgartner, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Optical sensor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Luminescence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Multi-task learning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Oxygen sensing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Dual sensing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The optical determination of oxygen partial pressure is of great interest in numerous areas, like medicine, biotechnology, and chemistry. A well-known optical measuring approach is based on the quenching of luminescence by the oxygen molecules. The conventional approach consists in measuring the intensity decay time and relate it to the oxygen concentration through a multi-parametric model (Stern–Volmer equation). The parameters of this equation are, however, all temperature-dependent. Therefore the temperature needs to be known to determine the oxygen concentration and is measured separately, either optically or with a completely different sensor. This work proposes a new approach based on a multi-task learning (MTL) neural network. Using the luminescence data of one single indicator, which is sensitive to both oxygen and temperature, the neural network achieves predictions of both parameters which are comparable to the accuracy of commercial senors. The impact of the new proposed approach is however not limited to dual oxygen and temperature sensing, but can be applied to all those cases in which the sensor response is too complex, to be comfortably described by a mathematical model.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-05-14T12:34:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-05-14T12:34:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1117/12.2554941</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1117/12.2554941</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20009</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20009</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20009</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:9781510634800</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:9781510634817</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0277-786X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1996-756X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings Volume 11354 : Optical Sensing and Detection VI</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>SPIE Photonics Europe, Digital Forum, France, 6 - 10 April 2020</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE)</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3018</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T10:12:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Potentiometric Immunoassay with Quantum Dot Labels</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Thürer, Reto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vigassy, Tamás</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hirayama, Martina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wang, Joseph</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bakker, Eric</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pretsch, Ernö</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Immunoassay</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Potentiometric</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Quantum dot</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>540: Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Potentiometric sensors based on polymer membrane electrodes, if properly optimized, are useful for measurements at trace levels. The expected independence of the electrochemical signal of the sample size makes them extremely attractive for measurements in small volumes. Here, we report on electrodes for the potentiometric detection of cadmium ions that reach a detection limit of 6 nM and utilize a Na+-selective electrode as pseudoreference in order to facilitate measurements in 150-µL samples. A potentiometric immunoassay of mouse IgG is performed via CdSe quantum dot labels on a secondary antibody according to a sandwich immunoassay protocol in a microtiter plate format. The CdSe quantum dots are found to be easily dissolved/oxidized in a matter of minutes with hydrogen peroxide, allowing us to maintain the pH at a near-neutral value. The potentiometric protein immunoassay exhibits a log-linear response ranging from 0.15 to 4.0 pmol of IgG, with a detection limit of &lt;10 fmol in 150-µL sample wells.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T07:55:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-26T07:55:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2007-05-26</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1021/ac070932m</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1021/ac070932m</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3018</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3018</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3018</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0003-2700</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1520-6882</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Analytical Chemistry</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>American Chemical Society</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5557</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T10:13:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Network coordination following discharge from psychiatric inpatient treatment : a study protocol</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>von Wyl, Agnes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Heim, Gisela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rüsch, Nicolas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rössler, Wulf</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Andreae, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>362: Gesundheits- und Sozialdienste</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Background: Inadequate discharge planning following inpatient stays is a major issue in the provision of a high standard of care for patients who receive psychiatric treatment. Studies have shown that half of patients who had no pre-discharge contact with outpatient services do not keep their first outpatient appointment. Additionally, discharged patients who are not well linked to their outpatient care networks are at twice the risk of re-hospitalization. The aim of this study is to investigate if the Post-Discharge Network Coordination Program at ipw has a demonstrably significant&#13;
impact on the frequency and duration of patient re-hospitalization. Subjects are randomly assigned to either the treatment group or to the control group. The treatment group participates in the Post-Discharge Network Coordination Program. The control group receives treatment as usual with no additional social support. Further outcome variables include: social support, change in psychiatric symptoms, quality of life, and independence in daily functioning. Methods/design: The study is conducted as a randomized controlled trial. Subjects are randomly assigned to either the control group or to the treatment group. Computer generated block randomization is used to assure both groups have the same number of subjects. Stratified block randomization is used for the psychiatric diagnosis of ICD-10, F1. Approximately 160 patients are recruited in two care units at Psychiatrie-Zentrum Hard Embrach and two care units at Klinik Schlosstal Winterthur. Discussion: The proposed post-discharge network coordination program intervenes during the critical post-discharge period. It focuses primarily on promoting the integration of the patients into their social networks, and additionally to coordinating outpatient care and addressing concerns of daily life.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-24T15:11:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-24T15:11:56Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1962</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-244X-13-220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1962</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1186/1471-244X-13-220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5557</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5557</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5557</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1471-244X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>BMC Psychiatry</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>BioMed Central</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20159</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-20T09:51:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>A new census of protein tandem repeats and their relationship with intrinsic disorder room</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Delucchi, Matteo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Tandem repeat</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Homorepeat</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Domain repeat</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Protein repeat</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Repeat prediction</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Intrinsic disorder</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Protein function</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Swiss-Prot</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>572: Biochemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Protein tandem repeats (TRs) are often associated with immunity-related functions and diseases. Since that last census of protein TRs in 1999, the number of curated proteins increased more than seven-fold and new TR prediction methods were published. TRs appear to be enriched with intrinsic disorder and vice versa. The significance and the biological reasons for this association are unknown. Here, we characterize protein TRs across all kingdoms of life and their overlap with intrinsic disorder in unprecedented detail. Using state-of-the-art prediction methods, we estimate that 50.9% of proteins contain at least one TR, often located at the sequence flanks. Positive linear correlation between the proportion of TRs and the protein length was observed universally, with Eukaryotes in general having more TRs, but when the difference in length is taken into account the difference is quite small. TRs were enriched with disorder promoting amino acids and were inside intrinsically disordered regions. Many such TRs were homorepeats. Our results support that TRs mostly originate by duplication and are involved in essential functions such as transcription processes, structural organization, electron transport and iron-binding. In viruses, TRs are found in proteins essential for virulence.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-06-18T14:03:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-06-18T14:03:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.3390/genes11040407</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-20159</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.3390/genes11040407</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-20159</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20159</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20159</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20159</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>SIB Days 2020, virtual conference, 8-10 June 2020</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Genes</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>image/png</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13934</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-22T12:56:13Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>“Dear Internet, what should I do when…?” : parents’ digital media behaviour when searching for information on children’s health in Switzerland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dratva, Julia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Baumann, Isabel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jaks, Rebecca</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Robin, Dominik</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Juvalta, Sibylle</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610: Medizin und Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Background &#13;
Little is known on parental use of digital media when it comes to children’s health, we investigated how parents utilize digital media in this context, when and how they assess the trustworthiness of information.&#13;
&#13;
Methods&#13;
A random sample of parents with children age 0-2.5 yrs. received an online and paper questionnaire on use of digital media on child health, child and parental socio- demographic and health and the German eHealth Literacy Scale (eHEALS). Qualitative data was collected in a focus group. Descriptive and regression analyses are planned.&#13;
&#13;
Results&#13;
Participation rate was 40% (394 online, 338 on paper). Preliminary results relate to online sample: 337 mothers and 57 fathers; mean age 35.8 sd 3.7 and 38.2 sd 6.4, respectively; mean age of youngest child 14.7 months, sd 7.1; number of children 1.6, sd 0.7. &#13;
34% of parents searching for general child health information used print media. 92% used digital media, reasons being 24/7 availability (76%), up to date information (34%) good experience (34%).  24% of parents searching for information on acute health problems resort to print and 82% to digital media for similar reasons. Parents search digital information on nutrition (24%), child development (20%), regulatory disturbance (18%), general information on acute health problem (47%) and alternative treatment options (40%). 3% report to fully trust the information found online and 8% report to never verify its content. Preliminary data analysis yields heterogeneity of utilization by health questions and socio-demographic characteristics. Qualitative data supports the wish for guidance.&#13;
&#13;
Conclusions&#13;
Parents frequently use digital media on child health related topics. They differentiate when and whom they trust, depending on the context. Parents constitute strengths and limitations of digital information. Guiding and enabling parents to use digital media may impact positively on parental health literacy.&#13;
&#13;
Main Messages &#13;
Parents frequently utilize digital media to access information about their children’s health. Parents are reluctant to fully trust the information and wish for more guidance.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-12-18T14:57:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-18T14:57:26Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1093/eurpub/cky218.233</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1093/eurpub/cky218.233</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13934</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13934</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13934</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1101-1262</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1464-360X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>11th European Public Health Conference, Ljubljana, Slovenia, 28 November - 1 December 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>European Journal of Public Health</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Oxford University Press</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9111</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-13T12:21:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Von der Wehe zur Geburt : Simulationstraining im Rettungsdienst</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Putscher-Ulrich, Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>618.4: Geburt</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-08-17T08:44:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-17T08:44:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9111</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9111</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9111</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>4th Swiss Conference on Standardized Patients and Simulations (SPSIM), Bern, 10.-12. September 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11726</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:00:45Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>A model for planar self-breathing proton exchange membrane fuel cells in FEMLAB</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ziegler, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tranitz, Marco</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schumacher, Jürgen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Self-breathing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fuel cell</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Modelling</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>A mathematical model of planar self-breathing fuel cells is developed and validated. The geometry of the model is a two-dimensional symmetric element of a planar self-breathing fuel cell. The multicomponent transport of the species is considered as well as the couplings between the transport processes of heat, charge, and mass, and the electrochemical reactions. The cell model is validated by comparison of the measured overall performance of a planar self-breathing fuel cell to the predictions of the model. The model is applied to study the behavior of planar self-breathing fuel cells during operation. The results of this study show that the mass transport, the charge transport, the heat transport, and the electrochemical reactions are strongly coupled. The consideration of these couplings is essential for the validity of the simulation results. The gas distribution, the potential distribution, and the temperature distribution are in?uenced by the geometric design of the cathode end-plate. Thus the charge generation rate in the active area of the cathode and anode is affected by the ribs of the cathode end-plate. A strong non-uniformity of the current distribution over the cathode is found. Based on the model, improvements of the fuel cell design and the components are suggested.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-12T08:04:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-12T08:04:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11726</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11726</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11726</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:0976679213</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings and user presentations CD - COMSOL Multiphysics Conference 2005</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>COMSOL Conference, Frankfurt a.M., Germany, 2-4 November 2005</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>COMSOL Group</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3347</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T09:10:37Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Skills for midwives : a practice-oriented written course material for teaching midwifery</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schwager, Monika</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stiefel, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Origlia, P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fankhauser, L.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-02-28T15:56:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-28T15:56:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014-06-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3347</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3347</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3347</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>30th International Confederation of Midwives (ICM) Triennial Congress, Prague, Czech Republic, 1-5 June 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18323</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T13:56:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_16708</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ein gesundheitsförderliches Kursangebot zur Stärkung der psychischen Gesundheit von Menschen ab 60 Jahren : ein theoriebasiertes Pilotprojekt basierend auf Mental Health First Aid Australia</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carisch, Andrina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leuenberger, Lea Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Mental health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>First aid course</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Older people</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610: Medizin und Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Einleitung: Die zunehmende Bevölkerungsalterung bringt Veränderungen auf verschiedenen Ebenen mit sich. Die aktuelle Situation zeigt, dass auch die psychische Gesundheit der Menschen ab dem 60. Lebensjahr davon beeinflusst werden kann. 
 
Ziel: Die vorliegende Bachelorarbeit stellt ein theoriebasiertes Pilotprojekt, basierend auf dem australischen Mental Health First Aid (MHFA) Programm, dar. Der Inhalt des australischen Standardkurses wird an schweizerische Verhältnisse und an die Bedürfnisse von Menschen ab 60 Jahren angepasst. Dieser Ersthelferkurs befähigt Laien psychisch belastende Situationen oder Krisen bei Menschen ab 60 Jahren zu erkennen und bedarfsgerecht zu handeln.   
Methode: Es wurde eine Literaturrecherche sowie eine Fokusgruppe durchgeführt. Für die Erarbeitung des Projektes diente das Projektmanagementtool Quintessenz als Orientierung. 

Ergebnisse: Themen wie Schwangerschaft, Aborigines und gewisse Substanzmittel werden weggelassen. Um zielgruppenspezifisch zu informieren, soll der Kurs MHFA 60+ durch Themen wie Demenz, Delirium, Recht und Medikamentenmissbrauch ergänzt werden. 
Schlussfolgerung: Mittels der Literaturrecherche und der Fokusgruppe wurde klar ersichtlich, dass ein Bedarf besteht, die psychische Gesundheit von Menschen ab 60 Jahren zu stärken. Zudem konnte aufgezeigt werden, dass es notwendig ist, die Öffentlichkeit über die Thematik der psychischen Gesundheit zu informieren. Dies kann durch das theoriebasierte Pilotprojekt MHFA 60+ erfüllt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-09-28T12:11:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-09-28T12:11:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-18323</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-18323</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18323</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18323</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18323</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>232 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13973</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T09:01:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Corporate image formation and corporate communications in virtual communities : a qualitative study</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hallier Willi, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Corporate communication</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Virtual community</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Corporate image</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Corporate identity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Computer-mediated communication</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Impression formation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>659: Werbung und Öffentlichkeitsarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>An interesting phenomenon in virtual communities (VCs) is that our identity often changes when we become members of communities. There are numerous studies in social psychology, which show that if we become part of a group our personal identity decreases while our social identity increases. Thus, we positively over-attribute everything that comes from this group. This is one of the reasons why companies try to target VCs with their communication activities. Unfortunately, they still often use traditional corporate communication activities, which are not appreciated by community members. They feel disturbed by the companies, which can have a negative impact on corporate image.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-12-19T09:58:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-19T09:58:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13973</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13973</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13973</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the Academy of Marketing Conference 2011: Marketing Field Forever, Academy of Marketing</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Doctoral Symposium, London, United Kingdom, 28-29 March 2011</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Brunel University</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20511</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-18T03:00:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Untersuchung der Eigenschaften und Fruchtbarkeit von Gewächshausböden</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hafner, Simon</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jean Petit Matile, Luzius</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Frey, Beat</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Berger, Roman</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hutter, Monika</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kulli Honauer, Beatrice</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Gewächshaus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bodenverdichtung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bodenbiologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hors-sol</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fruchtfolgeflächen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>630: Landwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Im Auftrag des Bundesamtes für Umwelt (BAFU)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Die Fruchtfolgeflächen in der Schweiz sind unter Druck. Beim Bau von Gewächshäusern stellt sich die Frage, ob diese weiterhin als Fruchtfolgeflächen angerechnet werden könnten oder nicht. Über die Qualität von Gewächshausböden in Abhängigkeit vom Anbausystem gibt es nur wenige Daten. Um für diese Diskussion und allfällige Entscheide eine Datengrundlage zu schaffen, sollen im vorliegenden Projekt die Qualität unterschiedlich genutzter Gewächshausböden untersucht werden. Der Fokus liegt auf folgenden Forschungsfragen: Inwieweit beeinflussen der Bau und Betrieb von Gewächshäusern die betroffenen Böden? Welche Rolle spielt die Bewirtschaftungsart? Unter welchen Bedingungen erfüllen Gewächshausböden die Kriterien eines fruchtbaren Bodens?&#13;
Für die Untersuchungen wurden sieben Gewächshäuser (GWH) mit unterschiedlicher Bewirtschaftung ausgewählt: Bodenkultur (BK), Hors-sol (HS) und saisonale Wechsel zwischen Bodenkultur und Hors-sol (W). Auf jeweils drei Plots in den Gewächshäusern und auf ausserhalb der Gewächshäuser liegenden Referenzflächen wurden biologische und physikalische Bodenparameter erhoben und Profilansprachen durchgeführt. Die biologischen Parameter sollen eine Aussage über die biologische Aktivität und die Biodiversität in den Böden ermöglichen, die physikalischen den Einfluss des Baus und der Bewirtschaftung auf die Dichte und den Wasserhaushalt des Bodens untersuchen. Auch das Erfassen chemischer Parameter wurde verzichtet, da in der Diskussion um Fruchtfolgeflächen nicht von zentraler Bedeutung sind.&#13;
Obwohl die Vergleichbarkeit zwischen Gewächshäusern und Referenzflächen und auch die Einheitlichkeit der Eigenschaften der Gewächshausböden nicht in allen Fällen optimal war, ist es möglich, den Einfluss der Bewirtschaftung auf die Gewächshausböden zu erkennen. Sowohl in den GWH mit BK, als auch in denjenigen mit W sind die Gehalte an organischem Material erhöht, vermutlich wegen der mit den Setzlingen eingebrachten Torfpresslingen. Biologische Parameter wie mikrobielle Biomasse, DNA Menge und Bodenatmung korrelieren üblicherweise stark mir Corg. In den GWH mit BK ist dies der Fall. Bei den GWH W ist die Korrelation aber um einiges weniger stark, als man es erwarten würde. Dies und die Tatsache, dass in den letzteren der metabolische Koeffizient deutlich erhöht war, lässt auf nicht ideale Bedingungen für die Bodenorganismen unter W schliessen. Die Gewächshäuser mit HS weisen die geringsten Gehalte an Corg auf und zeigten auch sonst eine tiefere biologische Aktivität als die übrigen Versuchsflächen. Mithilfe der molekularbiologischen Untersuchungen konnten standortspezifische aber auch gewächshausspezifische Lebensgemeinschaften in den Böden nachgewiesen werden. Generell war der Artenreichtum in den Gewächshausböden tiefer als in den dazugehörigen Referenzflächen. Interessanterweise konnten viele erwünschte oder unerwünschte Zielorganismen neben phytopathogenen auch pflanzenstärkende und bodenbelebende Mikroben nachgewiesen werden. &#13;
Durch die Messung von bodenphysikalischen Grössen konnten bei allen untersuchten Standorten mit mineralischen Böden in den Gewächshäusern und/oder auf den Referenzflächen mindestens Richtwertüberschreitungen festgestellt werden. Nicht immer ist aber die Beeinträchtigung im Gewächshaus grösser als ausserhalb und die Unterschiede zwischen Gewächshäusern im gleichen Betrieb waren teilweise gross. Ein Vergleich zwischen dem Verdichtungszustand der Böden und den Aussagen der Bewirtschafter zum Gewächshausbau zeigen einen Zusammenhang zwischen nassen Bedingungen beim Bau und Verdichtungen innerhalb und in der Umgebung des Gewächshauses. Bei den untersuchten Gewächshäusern verlangten die Bewilligungsbehörden in keinem Fall eine Bodenkundliche Baubegleitung (BBB). Bezüglich Verdichtung wären klarere Vorgaben für den Ablauf sicher sinnvoll. &#13;
Die Frage, ob Gewächshauböden grundsätzlich die Kriterien von Fruchtfolgeflächen erfüllen, lässt sich aufgrund unserer kleinen Stichprobe nicht abschliessend beantworten. Weitere Untersuchungen, vor allem bei Gewächshäusern mit Hors-sol oder Wechsel zwischen Hors-sol und Bodenkultur wären interessant. Dazu wäre eine grössere Stichprobe an Gewächshäusern wichtig. Vertiefte Untersuchungen mit molekularbiologischen Methoden könnten zeigen, ob sich die Habitat-Gebundenheit von mikrobiellen Gemeinschaftsstrukturen ausnutzen lässt, um typische Gemeinschaften von "gestörten" oder "geschädigten" zu unterscheiden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-09-17T13:23:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-09-17T13:23:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-20511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-20511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>108 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>WSL Eidgenössische Forschungsanstalt für Wald, Schnee und Landschaft</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23222</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-10-15T06:35:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Can we play together? : inclusive playgrounds as an example to enhance resilience in public spaces</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wenger, Ines</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schulze, Christina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lundström, Ulrica</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Prellwitz, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Play</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Outdoor play</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Inclusive</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Playground</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>302: Soziale Interaktion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610: Medizin und Gesundheit</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-09-27T13:51:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-09-27T13:51:11Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23222</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23222</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23222</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>2nd COTEC-ENOTHE Congress, Prague, Czech Republic (online), 15-18 September 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16614</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T10:32:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Moderne ökonomische Perspektive : mögliche Ansatzpunkte für Good Governance im Bildungsbereich</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kohlstock, B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Müller Werder, Claude</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>370: Bildung und Erziehung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-04-15T10:48:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-04-15T10:48:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16614</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16614</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16614</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Jahreskongress 2011 der SGBF, der SGL und der SGS : Bildungsreform und Reformkritik, Basel, 20.-22. Juni 2011</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9683</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-22T06:47:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Sustainable cleaning : smooth processes for transparency and peace of mind</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pericin Häfliger, Irina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Sustainability</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Cleaning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Assessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>648: Haushaltsführung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-08-27T07:57:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-27T07:57:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9683</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9683</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9683</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Global Cleaning</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Holzmann Medien</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9095</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T07:22:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Training von geburtshilflichen Situationen für medizinisches Fachpersonal ohne Ausbildung : Vertiefung in der Geburtshilfe am Beispiel der Veranstaltung "Von der Wehe zur Geburt" für den Rettungsdienst</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Putscher-Ulrich, Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meili-Hauser, Cynthia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>618: Geburtsmedizin und Hebammenarbeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Interaktiver Workshop</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-17T08:19:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-17T08:19:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9095</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9095</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9095</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>InSIM 2014: Simulationstraining für Patientensicherheit - Interdisziplinäres Symposium zur Simulation in der Medizin, Frankfurt am Main, Deutschland, 25.-27. September 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11414</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T10:17:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Eine lebensweltliche Erkundung zur Spiel- und Unterhaltungskultur eines Schweizer Casinos</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Robin, Dominik</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>306: Kultur</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-10-04T12:29:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-04T12:29:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11414</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11414</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11414</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Forschungswerkstatt der Allgemeinen Soziologie, Berlin, Deutschland, 13. Februar 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18393</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-11T13:52:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Kommentar zu Art. 31 ZGB</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kley, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Seferovic, Goran</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-10-11T13:52:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-10-11T13:52:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18393</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18393</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18393</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-280-07353-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>ZGB : Kommentar : Schweizerisches Zivilgesetzbuch</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Orell Füssli Kommentar</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Orell Füssli</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20020</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-04T12:56:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Towards a better understanding of the value of blockchains in supply chain management</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lustenberger, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Spychiger, Florian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Malešević, Saša</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.5: Produktionssteuerung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Whether or not blockchain technology adds value to supply chains is a highly controversial topic. It has been lauded as the technology that brings transparency and efficiency to supply chains. However, others find this view overly optimistic. In this paper, we aim to add more insight into the issue by applying an action design research approach. We develop and evaluate two artifacts in collaboration with companies and use the results to conclude how blockchain technology can help overcome issues in the current supply chain information flow. It shows that blockchains can provide a shared trust base and a common standard that allows for increased information exchange between supply chain partners. Based on our findings, we propose a research agenda for studying blockchain technology with a stronger focus on governance mechanism and transparency issues.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-05-14T13:40:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-05-14T13:40:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-44322-1_8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-20020</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-030-44322-1_8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-20020</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20020</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20020</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20020</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-030-44321-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-030-44322-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1865-1348</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1865-1356</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Information Systems : 16th European, Mediterranean, and Middle Eastern Conference, Proceedings</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>16th European Mediterranean and Middle Eastern Conference on Information Systems, Dubai, United Arab Emirates, 9-10 December 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Lecture Notes in Business Information Processing</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7160</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-18T09:05:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Studie 450 kW Photovoltaik-Fassadenkraftwerk</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hochreutener, Hanspeter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gnos, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Posnansky, Mario</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Fassadenkraftwerk</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Photovoltaik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Im Rahmen dieser Studie wurde die Machbarkeit eines grösseren Photovoltaik-Fassadenkraftwerks, das in die Südfassaden von fünf Hochhäusern der Überbauung Murifeld-Wittigkofen (bei Bern) integriert ist, abgeklärt. Grundsätzlich haben sich zwei Varianten der Fassadenbelegung (flach, geschuppt) und zwei Varianten der Energieabgabe (230/400V-Wechselstromnetz, Tram-Gleichstrom) herauskristallisisert.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-06-21T09:23:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-21T09:23:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1993</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7160</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7160</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7160</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Bundesamt für Energiewirtschaft</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3728</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T09:47:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1075</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1074</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1076</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Architektur gibt es nicht! für eine politische Architektur</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kurath, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Iseppi, Ivano</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>720: Architektur</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-14T10:05:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-14T10:05:13Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3728</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3728</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3728</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0005-6529</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0257-9332</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Werk, Bauen + Wohnen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Verlag Werk</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21834</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-25T08:31:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Challenges with matrix metalloproteinase inhibition and future drug discovery avenues</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fischer, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riedl, Rainer</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Antibodies</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Drug design</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Drug discovery</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hemopexin-like domain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Matrix metalloproteinase</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Medicinal chemistry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Polypharmacology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Small-molecule inhibitors</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615: Pharmakologie und Therapeutik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Matrix metalloproteinases have been in the scope of pharmaceutical drug discovery for decades as promising targets for drug development. Until present, no modulator of the enzyme class survived clinical trials, all failing for various reasons. Nevertheless, the target family did not lose its attractiveness and there is ever more evidence that MMP modulators are likely to overcome the hurdles and result in successful clinical therapies.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-02-25T08:31:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-02-25T08:31:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-09-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1080/17460441.2020.1819235</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1080/17460441.2020.1819235</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21834</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21834</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21834</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1746-0441</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1746-045X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>32921161</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Expert Opinion on Drug Discovery</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Taylor &amp; Francis</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/940</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-19T13:38:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_236</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_238</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Welche Paare profitieren von Prävention? : Couples Coping Enhancement Training (CCET) und Kommunikationsverhalten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sutter, Sven</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:14:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:14:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Master</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-940</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-940</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/940</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/940</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/940</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14879</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T11:10:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>PROFINET Real-time protection layer : performance analysis of cryptographic and protocol processing overhead</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Doran, Hans</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Real-Time Ethernet</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Automation Systems</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Cryptography</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Message Authentication</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Recent times have seen an increasing demand for access to process-data from the field level through to the Internet. This vertical integration of industrial control systems into the IT infrastructure exhibits major drawbacks in the context of security. Such systems now suffer exposure to cyber security attacks well-known from the IT environment. Successful attacks on industrial control systems can lead to downtimes, malfunction of production machinery, cause financial damage and may present a hazard for human life and health. Current automation communication systems generally lack a comprehensive security concept. PROFINET is a widespread Industrial Ethernet standard, fulfilling general communication requirements on automation systems as well as explicit real-time requirements. We elaborate the challenges of protecting the realtime component of PROFINET. We specify the requirements and a concept for ensuring integrity and authenticity using a keyed-hash message authentication code (HMAC) in combination with the cryptographic hash algorithm SHA-3. With a proof of concept implementation of a PROFINET RT protection layer, the performance overhead for generation and transmission of this HMAC and other required data fields, e.g. to prevent replay attacks, could be analyzed. Based on these data the limitations of security technology on real-time systems were explored as was the optimization potential of hardware acceleration.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-01-31T13:12:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-31T13:12:31Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-25</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-5010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1109/ETFA.2018.8502670</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-5010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1109/ETFA.2018.8502670</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14879</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14879</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14879</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-5386-7108-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-5386-7107-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-5386-7109-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1946-0759</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1946-0740</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the 23rd International Conference on Emerging Technologies and Factory Automation (ETFA)</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>2018 IEEE 23rd International Conference on Emerging Technologies and Factory Automation (ETFA 2018), Torino, Italy, 4-7 September 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>IEEE</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12439</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-11-01T13:17:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Skin problems in palliative care</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Grocott, P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gethin, G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Probst, Sebastian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>5th revised edition</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-01T13:17:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-01T13:17:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1093/med/9780199656097.003.0111</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1093/med/9780199656097.003.0111</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12439</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12439</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12439</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-0-19-965609-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Oxford textbook of palliative medicine</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Oxford University Press</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12284</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T11:47:04Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Schweizer Mischungen, die’s feucht mögen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Föhn, Martina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Mischung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Pflanzenverwendung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Stauden</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>635: Gartenpflanzen (Gartenbau)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-10-29T15:01:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-29T15:01:40Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12284</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12284</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12284</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1615-3502</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1866-6272</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Campos: die Zeitung für Landschaftsgärtner</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Ulmer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11363</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-18T07:15:45Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Diagnose und Therapie von Unternehmenskulturen : Massnahmen zur gezielten und nachhaltigen Veränderung der Unternehmenskultur</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Danko, Fabian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Unternehmenskultur</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Aufsatzsammlung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>BWL</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Unternehmenserfolg</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wettbewerb</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-10-03T14:13:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-03T14:13:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11363</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11363</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11363</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7910-3375-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7992-6917-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Wettbewerbsfaktor Unternehmenskultur : wie Unternehmenskulturen den Erfolg beflügeln oder lähmen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schäffer-Poeschel</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2480</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T10:36:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wastewater-fed aquaculture Otelfingen, Switzerland : influence of system design and operation parameters on the efficiency of nutrient incorporation into plant biomass</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Graber, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Junge, Ranka</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Pilot plant</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wastewater-fed aquaculture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nutrients elimination</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>630: Landwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>A wastewater-fed, partly indoor aquaculture plant consisting of 36 basins with a total area of 360 m2, charged with effluent from a methanization plant processing organic household waste (Kompogas System), started operation in spring 1998 in Otelfingen, Switzerland. Due to high effluent concentrations on one hand (total organic carbon, total nitrogen, and total phosphorus concentrations being 670, 255, and 52 mg l−1, respectively) and stringent wastewater regulations on the other hand, the aquaculture was split into modules and stocked with organisms of different environmental requirements. The modular structure, as opposed to traditional one-pond polyculture, allowed manipulation and better nutrient budgeting of the system. Research focused on nutrient-recycling efficiency of a wide array of modules, producing biomass such as algae, fish, zooplankton, and aquatic macrophytes as ornamental plants (Eichhornia, Pistia, Ipomoea, Lemna, Azolla) which were suitable for sale on the Swiss market. Different arrangements of modules, of water and wastewater flows and of nutrient concentrations were tested in 3 years, 1998-2000. Our research showed that aquaculture can be set up to either produce treated wastewater ready for discharge into surface waters or to maximize nutrient recycling through biomass production. In the first case, the recommended loadings are below 0.47 g N m−2 day−1 and 0.084 g P m−2 day−1, in the latter 4.3 g N m−2 day−1 and 0.31 g P m−2 day−1 still resulted in a 78% removal of nitrogen and 28% removal of phosphorus. Through weekly biomass harvest, up to 0.36 g N m−2 day−1 and 0.06 g P m−2 day−1 were converted into plants. With appropriate planning and plant selection and management, it was possible to increase the fraction of  nutrients eliminated via primary production up to 40%, which is significantly higher than reported in the literature.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-01T09:04:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-01T09:04:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2480</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2480</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2480</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-1-4020-8234-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Wastewater treatment, plant dynamics and management in constructed and natural wetlands</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7067</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-07T11:57:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Aktive latente Steuern auf steuerliche Verlustvorträge : der Fall - die Lösung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Acker, Christine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meyer, Dieter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>332: Finanzwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-18T10:28:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-18T10:28:41Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7067</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7067</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7067</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1862-5533</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Zeitschrift für internationale Rechnungslegung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Beck</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12780</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-25T11:32:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Überleitung von Swiss GAAP FER auf IFRS : am Beispiel einer Regionalbank</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nagel, Gabriela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Knecht, Heinz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Bank Linth</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332.1: Banken</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>657: Rechnungswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Bank Linth wurde per 6. März 2007 in die Gruppe der LiechtensteinischenLandesbank LLB integriert und muss dadurch ihren Abschluss, welcher für die Konzernrechnung der LLB verwendet wird, nach den Rechnungslegungsnormen der IFRS erstellen. Die Umstellung von den Regeln der RRV-EBK (welche im Wesentlichen den Swiss GAAP FER entsprechen) auf IFRS ist seit der Inkraftsetzung von IFRS 3 noch an keiner Schweizer Regionalbank vorgenommen worden und stellt daher ein Novum dar. Nach IFRS 3 kann ein sich zwischen Kaufpreis und Buchwert ergebender Unterschiedsbetrag nicht mehr weitgehend unreflektiert als Goodwill ausgewiesen und in einem einzigen Posten über die geschätzte Nutzungsdauer abgeschrieben werden. Die neuen Regeln fordern eine differenzierte Auseinandersetzung mit der Frage, warum der Erwerber denn mehr als den Buchwert der ausgewiesenen Vermögenswerte und Schulden für ein Unternehmen bezahlt hat. Im Weiteren wird eine planmässige Abschreibung für den Goodwill untersagt. Es wird eine jährliche Überprüfung der Werthaltigkeit gefordert (impairment-only-approach). Der vorliegende Beitrag beschreibt einleitend die strategische Ausrichtung der LLB sowie der Bank Linth. Anschliessend werden die allgemein geltenden Rechnungslegungsvorschriften für Banken in der Schweiz erläutert. Schliesslich werden ausgewählte, relevante IFRS-Normen beschrieben sowie die betragsmässigen Auswirkungen der Überleitung des Abschlusses der Bank Linth dargestellt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-14T09:36:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-14T09:36:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12780</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12780</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12780</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-29701-418-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Finanz- und Rechnungswesen : Jahrbuch 2008</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>WEKA</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21360</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-22T04:01:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Perspectives of people accompanying a person during voluntary stopping eating and drinking : a convergent mixed methods study</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stängle, Sabrina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fringer, André</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Data integration</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Convergent mixed methods</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Focus group interviews</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Survey</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Voluntary stopping eating and drinking (VSED)</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Background: Voluntary stopping eating and drinking (VSED) is an option for people wishing to bring about premature death. In Switzerland, VSED is considered a controversial action at the end of life in the guidelines for “Management of dying and death,” which states that the decision to support or oppose VSED must be made individually by health care professionals; so far there are no instructions for action. The aim of this research was to explore the experiences of people who play an important role in VSED accompaniment, and to explain how the people involved in the process deal with VSED.&#13;
&#13;
Methods: This convergent mixed methods study included a national survey (n=1,681) and five focus group interviews (n=47). Data integration was conducted using the four-stage pillar integration process.&#13;
&#13;
Results: Given Swiss society interest, VSED has already established itself in the health system without the institutions having addressed the issue, whereupon health professionals make individual decisions when a person willing to die comes to them with a VSED wish. Health professionals are open to VSED, but are also ambivalent and would like to know more about it before being confronted with a VSED case.&#13;
&#13;
Conclusions: In Switzerland, VSED has become a rare but desired option for ending life prematurely. While health professionals are already being confronted with the phenomenon, there is a lack of discussion at the level of health institutions about how to deal with it.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-01-21T11:16:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-01-21T11:16:33Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21037/apm-20-1339</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-21360</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21037/apm-20-1339</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-21360</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21360</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21360</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21360</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2224-5820</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2224-5839</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>33440976</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Annals of Palliative Medicine</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>AME Publishing</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19394</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-30T08:35:47Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Tagung Grünflächenmanagement - Arbeitwelt im Wandel : Tagungsdokumentation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brack, Florian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.2: Facility Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.3: Personalmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>712: Landschaftsgestaltung (Landschaftsdesign)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Arbeitswelt befindet sich im Umbruch: Die Wertvorstellungen der Generationen Y und Z, fortschreitende Digitalisierung, flexible Arbeitszeiten und -orte sowie neue Anforderungen an Fachkräfte beschäftigen auch die Akteure der Grünen Branche. Daraus ergeben sich neue Chancen und Möglichkeiten.&#13;
Wie positioniere ich mein Gartenbauamt oder Unternehmen in der Zukunft, um bei Arbeitnehmenden als attraktiver Arbeitgeber wahrgenommen zu werden? Wie finde ich die richtigen Fachkräfte und was biete ich diesen? Welche Kompetenzen brauchen Arbeitnehmende heute, sei es in der Planung, in der Kommunikation im Umgang mit Kunden oder als Führungsperson? Was zeichnet ein erfülltes Arbeitsleben aus?&#13;
Die Referate geben einen Überblick über aktuelle und zukünftige Trends im Schweizer Arbeitsmarkt und wie sich dadurch Aufgaben und Verantwortungsbereiche verändern. Besonderheiten und spezifische Fragestellungen zu Gartenbau, Landschaftsarchitektur, Facility Management und Naturschutz werden vertieft beleuchtet.&#13;
An der diesjährigen Tagung mischen wir Bewährtes mit Neuem: Nach einem Vormittag mit inspirierenden Vorträgen steht der Nachmittag ganz im Zeichen der Interaktion und des Netzwerkens: Inputreferate, Diskussionen, Marktplatz und Möglichkeiten zum Austausch – sich aktiv einbringen und diskutieren oder einfach nur zuhören.&#13;
Dazu sind Sie alle herzlich eingeladen – für ein erfülltes Arbeitsleben in Grün!</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-02-06T10:23:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-02-06T10:23:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-11-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Proceedings</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-19394</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-19394</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19394</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19394</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19394</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Tagung Grünflächenmagamenent, Wädenswil, 7. November 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>23 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19627</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-06T04:01:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_22</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_6874</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Kennzeichnungspflicht von Influencer-Beiträgen auf Instagram : die Folgen der Werbeerkennung auf das Markenvertrauen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>El Benna, Leila</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>658.8: Marketingmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Der Einsatz von Influencer auf Instagram ist bei vielen Unternehmen ein Bestandteil des Marketing-Mix geworden, was für die Marke aber auch negative Folgen haben kann. Influencer sind gesetzlich verpflichtet, Werbung in ihren Posts durch Kennzeichnung offenzulegen, wenn sie im Auftrag eines Unternehmens agieren. Diese Pflicht wurde jedoch lange ignoriert. Gerichte und Aufsichtsbehörden wurden deshalb vermehrt aktiv und verurteilten widerrechtliche Handlungen, um Follower zu schützen. Ohne Werbekennzeichnung ist es für diese schwierig zu erkennen, ob eine kommerzielle Absicht hinter dem Post besteht. Es existieren Empfehlungen, wie Influencer-Beiträge zu kennzeichnen sind. Auch Instagram stellt mittlerweile ein Tool zur Offenlegung von Beziehungen zu Marken zur Verfügung.  &#13;
 &#13;
Der Einsatz einer Werbeoffenlegung kann aber negative Folgen für das Vertrauen in die Marke als wichtigster Faktor der Kunden-Marken-Beziehung haben, wenn Follower erkennen, dass sie einem Überzeugungsversuch ausgesetzt sind. Unternehmen und ihre Influencer sollten wissen, welche Kennzeichnung geeignet ist, den Werbecharakter zu vermitteln, um damit gesetzeskonform handeln zu können. Gleichzeitig benötigen Unternehmen die Gewissheit, ob sie dadurch ihrer Marke schaden.  &#13;
 &#13;
In der Masterarbeit wurde deshalb untersucht, ob die bestehenden Möglichkeiten der Werbeoffenlegung zur Werbeerkennung geeignet sind und dadurch das Markenvertrauen beeinflusst wird. Dazu wurde die Theorie des Überzeugungswissensmodells hinzugezogen. Die Zusammenhänge wurden mittels Experiments analysiert. Bei einer Experimentalgruppe wurde beim Instagram-Post #Werbung im Text platziert. Bei der zweiten das Instagram-Tool verwendet, bei dem die Kennzeichnung Bezahlte Partnerschaft mit unterhalb des Benutzernamens erfolgt. In der Kontrollgruppe wurde zum Vergleich keine Kennzeichnung gesetzt. Mit dem Kruskal-Wallis-Test wurde der Einfluss der Kennzeichnung auf die Werbeerkennung untersucht. Für deren Einfluss auf das Markenvertrauen wiederum wurde die lineare Regression verwendet. Der indirekte Einfluss der Werbeoffenlegung auf das Markenvertrauen wurde durch eine Mediatoranalyse festgehalten.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-03-05T11:43:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-03-05T11:43:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Master</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-19627</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-19627</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19627</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19627</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19627</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>180 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23946</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-20T10:23:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Satirical Literacy als Voraussetzung für die Decodierung von journalistischer Satire</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Keel, Guido</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Media Literacy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>302.23: Medien</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Diskussion um Media Literacy geht heute weit über das klassische Verständnis von Medienkompetenz hinaus. Gleichzeitig werden dem Begriff ganz unterschiedliche Bedeutungen zugeschrieben. Der Sammelband vereint 14 Beiträge zu verschiedenen Dimensionen von Media Literacy: Neben Begriffsdefinitionen thematisiert er Media and Information Literacy im Umgang mit journalistischen Inhalten; er erörtert Media Literacy im Kontext von Social Media, Organisationen und in spezifischen Rollen und beleuchtet technologische, gesellschaftliche und ästhetische Aspekte von Media Literacy. Die Beiträge schlagen eine Brücke zwischen den Erkenntnissen aus der Medien- und Kommunikationsforschung, der Erziehungswissenschaft und dem Konzept von Media Literacy.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-01-20T10:23:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-01-20T10:23:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5771/9783748920656</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.5771/9783748920656</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23946</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23946</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23946</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-8487-8265-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7489-2065-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Media Literacy</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Nomos</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22555</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-05-28T03:01:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die EU-Türkei-Beziehungen und die Flüchtlingsvereinbarung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Celik, Hüseyin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Flüchtlingspolitik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>327: Internationale Beziehungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-05-27T14:03:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-05-27T14:03:57Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-09-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.17176/20180522-181219</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-22555</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.17176/20180522-181219</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-22555</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://voelkerrechtsblog.org/die-eu-turkei-beziehungen-und-die-fluchtlingsvereinbarung/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22555</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2510-2567</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Völkerrechtsblog</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Völkerrechtsblog</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4612</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T13:39:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Chaotische Strukturen in Raum und Zeit</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Weigert, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Breymann, Wolfgang</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Elmer, Franz-Josef</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Thomas, Harry</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>500: Naturwissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-03T13:21:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-03T13:21:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>1995</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4612</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4612</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4612</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>UNI NOVA - Das Wissenschaftsmagazin der Universität Basel</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Universität Basel</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14675</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T09:11:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1075</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1074</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1076</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Tragende Elemente aus Faserverbundkunststoff für den konstruktiven Hochbau</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sydow, Antje</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ringli, Alexis</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>620.11: Werkstoffe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>624: Ingenieurbau</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-01-28T17:42:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-01-28T17:42:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14675</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14675</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14675</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>4th ICC International Composite Congress, Stuttgart, Deutschland, 5. November 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22724</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-06-23T12:30:42Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wer sind die Teilnehmenden bei unseren Weiterbildungen in Managed Health Care?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Waech, Cassandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>362.1041: Gesundheitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>378: Hochschulbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-06-23T12:30:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-06-23T12:30:42Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-05-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://blog.zhaw.ch/gesundheitsoekonomie/2021/05/06/wer-sind-die-teilnehmende-bei-unseren-weiterbildungen-in-managed-health-care/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22724</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Gesundheitsökonomie @ ZHAW</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12601</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-17T14:34:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Unschuldsvermutung in der Berichterstattung über die Verhaftung im Fall Rupperswil</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dutler, Alex</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Keel, Guido</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Medienrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>070: Nachrichtenmedien, Journalismus und Verlagswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>345: Strafrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Journalisten müssen in ihrer Berichterstattung zwischen dem Schutz der Privatsphäre der Beteiligten und dem öffentlichen Interesse an Information abwägen. Dies gilt in besonderem Ausmass bei der Berichterstattung über extreme Gewaltverbrechen.
Anhand des stark beachteten Tötungsdelikts in Rupperswil untersucht dieser Beitrag, wie Schweizer Medien(schaffende) unmittelbar nach der Verhaftung des Beschuldigten mit dem rechtstaatlichen Grundprinzip der Unschuldsvermutung umgegangen sind. Die Analyse von 413 Beiträgen in Print- und Onlinemedien sowie auf Social-Media-Kanälen von Medienunternehmen zeigt, dass unabhängig vom Medientyp oft vorverurteilend und identifizierend berichtet wurde, was auf ein mangelhaftes Bewusstsein der Medienschaffenden hindeutet, wenn es um den Schutz der Beschuldigten bei Gewaltverbrechen geht.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-11-07T10:04:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-07T10:04:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12601</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12601</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12601</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1420-3723</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Medialex</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Stämpfli</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header status="deleted">
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23907</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-20T07:24:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11786</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-08-27T08:10:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die neuen Rechnungslegungsvorschriften für Banken</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Meyer, Dieter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nagel, Gabriela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Bank</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Rechnungslegung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>nRLR</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>FINMA</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>332.1: Banken</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>657: Rechnungswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Nach der Verabschiedung des neuen Rechnungslegungsrechts (nRLR) im OR hat die Finanzmarktaufsicht (FINMA) die entsprechenden Vorschriften für Banken überarbeitet und im Juni 2014 veröffentlicht. Einerseits ging es um eine Harmonisierung mit dem nRLR und um strukturelle Verbesserungen, andererseits um Anpassungen an Entwicklungen in der internationalen Rechnungslegung und um die Behandlung von Themen, welche in den bisherigen Vorschriften nicht oder nur oberflächlich adressiert wurden. Die Autoren fassen die wichtigsten Neuerungen zusammen und kommentieren bedeutende Themen, bei denen die Vorschriften ihrer Meinung nach weiterhin grosse Lücken aufweisen, und weisen auf Unzulänglichkeiten in der Formulierung gewisser Vorschriften hin.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-15T10:00:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-15T10:00:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11786</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11786</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11786</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-297-14115-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Finanz- und Rechnungswesen : Jahrbuch 2015</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Jahrbuch zum Finanz- und Rechnungswesen</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>WEKA</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/15232</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T10:12:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Filling the Gap of Overfishing in LCIA: Eco-factors for Global Fish Resources</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stucki, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Keller, Regula</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Itten, René</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eymann, Lea</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Environmental impact</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>LCA</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Overfishing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>630: Landwirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Introduction: Life cycle assessment has been widely used to measure the environmental impact of food production and value chains. However, there is a lack of LCIA methods to assess the contribution of fish consumption to the global problem of overfishing, despite that fact that more than two thirds of commercially used fish resources are overexploited. Due to this methodological gap, fish is often determined to have a lower environmental footprint than other sources of animal protein in LCA studies. The aim of this publication is to present the development of eco-factors for fish resources and by-catch as an addition to the Swiss Ecological Scarcity Method 2013 and to compare the eco-factors of different fish resources and the impacts of fishing as well as the impacts of dietary alternatives like chicken, pork, lamb, beef and veal.

Materials and Methods: The sustainable use of fish resources ensures that the fish stock for each fish species exceeds the minimum stock needed for a maximum sustainable yield. Therefore, the method developed uses a distance to target approach based on the fish stock for maximum sustainable yield (FSMSY) and the current fish stock (FS) for the characterisation of the use of fish resources. Langlois et al. and Emanuelsson et al. also suggest approaches for the characterisation of overexploitation of fish resources based on the FSMSY. The eco-factors were calculated for each fish species and fishing area. Thereafter, they were aggregated for each fish species using the weighted average of the total catch per fishing area. The target value for FSMSY depends on the fish species and the fishing area. The amount of by-catch was approximated with the dead discard of the walleye pollock (gadus chalcogrammus), which has the highest by-catch rate worldwide. In order to be able to compare the eco-factors for fish resources with the eco-factors of meat production, the factors were corrected from live weight to product weight assuming that the product weight corresponds to 45 % of live weight and that 98 % of the economic value is associated with the final product weight.

Results and Discussion: The inclusion of eco-factors for the overexploitation of fish resources and by-catch shows a relevant contribution to the total environmental impact of fish compared to other impacts resulting from fishing and fish processing.
Depending on the fish species, fish can have significantly higher overall impacts compared with different types of meat. The contribution of the eco-factors for by-catch is minor compared to fish resources but still relevant for the comparison with dietary alternatives. The total contribution of the eco-factors for fish resources exceeds the impacts of the fishery and fish processing.

Conclusions: Distance to target based eco-factors using regionalised data for FS and FSMSY not only follow a comparable underlying approach as suggested in literature but also enable aggregation into a single-score with other environmental impacts. The overexploitation of fish resources is highly variable for different fish species and fishing areas as well as for by-catch, which also requires the consideration of by-catch species and fishing method. When comparing fish to equivalent dietary alternatives like chicken, pork, lamb, beef or veal, consideration of the overexploitation of fish resources results in some fish species exceeding the environmental impact of dietary alternatives. Therefore, overexploitation of fish resources is relevant in the Life Cycle Assessment of fish products in different diets. The suggested approach can be integrated in a full single-score LCIA of meals and is able to reflect the regionalised impacts caused by the overexploitation of fish resources for different species and fishing areas as well as the impacts associated with by-catch and fishing method.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-11T11:13:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-11T11:13:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-5017</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-5017</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/15232</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/15232</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/15232</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>SETAC Europe 28th annual meeting, Rome, Italy, 13-17 May 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9787</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-08-28T13:30:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Zufriedene Schweizer Journalisten trotz Medienkrise</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wyss, Vinzenz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dingerkus, Filip</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Keel, Guido</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>070: Nachrichtenmedien, Journalismus und Verlagswesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-08-28T13:30:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-28T13:30:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Weiteres (textuelles Material)</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/9787</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9787</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/9787</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11249</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-30T08:35:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Forschungsprojekt Grünstadt Schweiz : ein Projekt für nachhaltiges Stadtgrün</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hagenbuch, Reto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Weiss, Martina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Biodiversität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Unterhalt</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nachhaltigkeit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>712: Landschaftsgestaltung (Landschaftsdesign)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-10-01T13:43:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-01T13:43:12Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11249</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11249</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11249</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Tagung Grünflächenmanagement, Wädenswil, 6. November 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7595</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-13T10:13:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Is the work ability index useful to evaluate absence days in ankylosing spondylitis patients? : a cross-sectional study</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Meyer, Katharina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Niedermann Schneider, Karin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tschopp, Alois</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Klipstein, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>616.7: Krankheiten des Bewegungsapparates und Orthopädie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Background: The work incapacity of ankylosing spondylitis (AS) ranges between 3% and 50% in Europe. In many countries, work incapacity is difficult to quantify. The work ability index (WAI) is applied to measure the work ability in workers, but it is not well investigated in patients.&#13;
&#13;
Aims: To investigate the work incapacity in terms of absence days in patients with AS and to evaluate whether the WAI reflects the absence from work.&#13;
&#13;
Hypothesis: Absence days can be estimated based on the WAI and other variables.&#13;
&#13;
Design: Cross-sectional design.&#13;
&#13;
Setting: In a secondary care centre in Switzerland, the WAI and a questionnaire about work absence were administered in AS patients prior to cardiovascular training. The number of absence days was collected retrospectively. The absence days were estimated using a two-part regression model.&#13;
&#13;
Participants: 92 AS patients (58 men (63%)). Inclusion criteria: AS diagnosis, ability to cycle, age between 18 and 65 years. Exclusion criteria: severe heart disease.&#13;
&#13;
Primary and secondary outcome measures: Absence days.&#13;
&#13;
Results: Of the 92 patients, 14 received a disability pension and 78 were in the working process. The median absence days per year of the 78 patients due to AS alone and including other reasons was 0 days (IQR 0–12.3) and 2.5 days (IQR 0–19), respectively. The WAI score (regression coefficient=−4.66 (p&lt;0.001, CI −6.1 to −3.2), ‘getting a disability pension’ (regression coefficient=−106.8 (p&lt;0.001, 95% CI −141.6 to −72.0) and other not significant variables explained 70% of the variance in absence days (p&lt;0.001), and therefore may estimate the number of absence days.&#13;
&#13;
Conclusions: Absences in our sample of AS patients were equal to pan-European countries. In groups of AS patients, the WAI and other variables are valid to estimate absence days with the help of a two-part regression model.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-05T13:48:38Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-05T13:48:38Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3831</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002231</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3831</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002231</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7595</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7595</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7595</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2044-6055</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>BMJ Open</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>BMJ Publishing Group</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24965</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-05-12T11:34:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Volle Kraft voraus mit dem Innosuisse-Flagship SHIFT : wie Schweizer Forschende das smarte Spital der Zukunft entwickeln</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stahl, Johanna</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Angerer, Alfred</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Spital der Zukunft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Digitalisierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Flagship SHIFT</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Innosuisse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.11: Krankenhäuser und verwandte Einrichtungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>3.5 Jahre Laufzeit, 5.7 Millionen Franken Projektbudget, 20 Spitäler, fünf Forschungs- sowie 24 Praxispartner/innen… UND ein grosses Ziel: das smarte Krankenhaus der Zukunft entwickeln! Im Innosuisse-Flagship-Projekt «SHIFT» (Smart Hospital: Integrated Framework, Tools &amp; Solutions) – gestartet am 01.01.2022 – übernimmt die ZHAW nun das Steuer und macht sich gemeinsam mit einer Crew aus weiteren Schweizer Hochschulen (Universitätsspital Basel, Universität Basel, Universität Zürich, Fachhochschule Nordwestschweiz) und Praxispartner/innen auf die Reise, um zu erforschen, wie die Spitäler hierzulande die digitale Transformation umsetzen können.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-05-12T11:34:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-05-12T11:34:54Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-01-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://blog.zhaw.ch/gesundheitsoekonomie/2022/01/20/volle-kraft-voraus-mit-dem-innosuisse-flagship-shift/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24965</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Gesundheitsökonomie @ ZHAW</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/474</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:42:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_52</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Manuelle Therapie bei Gonarthrose – effektiv oder Zeitverschwendung? : welchen Effekt zeigt manuelle Therapie zur Schmerzlinderung bei Patienten mit Gonarthrose?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Forster, Nicole Marianne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:05:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:05:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-474</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-474</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/474</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/474</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/474</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4125</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T09:11:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Adipositas bei Jugendlichen korreliert mit einem Netzwerk aus sozialen Faktoren, Medien- und Alkoholkonsum sowie spezifischen Lebensmittelpräferenzen</dc:title>
          <dc:title>Poster</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stolberg, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Krömker, Dörthe</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bode, Christiane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Parlesak, Alexandr</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>305: Soziale Gruppen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>613.2: Diätetik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616: Innere Medizin und Krankheiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-21T12:10:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-21T12:10:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4125</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4125</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4125</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>47. Wissenschaftlicher Kongress der Deutschen Gesellschaft für Ernährung, Jena, Deutschland, 11.-12. März 2010</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Deutsche Gesellschaft für Ernährung</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18413</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-20T10:26:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Exoscore: a design tool to evaluate factors associated with technology acceptance of soft lower limb exosuits by older adults</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Shore, Linda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Power, Valerie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hartigan, Bernard</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schülein, Samuel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Graf, Eveline</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>de Eyto, Adam</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>O’Sullivan, Leonard</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Designing for the elderly</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Home health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Product design</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Usability/acceptance measurement and research</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wearable device</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>620: Ingenieurwesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Objective: This pilot study proposed and performs initial testing with Exoscore, a design evaluation tool to assess factors related to acceptance of exoskeleton by older adults, during the technology development and testing phases.&#13;
&#13;
Background: As longevity increases and our aging population continues to grow, assistive technologies such as exosuits and exoskeletons can provide enhanced quality of life and independence. Exoscore is a design and prototype stage evaluation method to assess factors related to perceptions of the technology, the aim being to optimize technology acceptance.&#13;
&#13;
Method: In this pilot study, we applied the three-phase Exoscore tool during testing with 11 older adults. The aims were to explore the feasibility and face validity of applying the design evaluation tool during user testing of a prototype soft lower limb exoskeleton.&#13;
&#13;
Results: The Exoscore method is presented as part of an iterative design evaluation process. The method was applied during an exoskeleton research and development project. The data revealed the aspects of the concept design that rated favorably with the users and the aspects of the design that required more attention to improve their potential acceptance when deployed as finished products.&#13;
&#13;
Conclusion: Exoscore was effectively applied to three phases of evaluation during a testing session of a soft exoskeleton. Future exoskeleton development can benefit from the application of this design evaluation tool.&#13;
&#13;
Application: This study reveals how the introduction of Exoscore to exoskeleton development will be advantageous when assessing technology acceptance of exoskeletons by older adults.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-10-16T13:54:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-10-16T13:54:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1177/0018720819868122</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1177/0018720819868122</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18413</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18413</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18413</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0018-7208</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1547-8181</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Human Factors</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Sage</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10647</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T13:39:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Reconstruction of total solar irradiance 1974–2009</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ball, W. T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Unruh, Y.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Krivova, N. A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Solanki, S. K.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wenzler, T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mortlock, D. J.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jaffe, A. H.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Sunspots</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sun: activity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sun: faculae, plages</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sun: photosphere</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>500: Naturwissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Context: The study of variations in total solar irradiance (TSI) is important for understanding how the Sun affects the Earth’s climate.

Aims:  Full-disk continuum images and magnetograms are now available for three full solar cycles. We investigate how modelled TSI compares with direct observations by building a consistent modelled TSI dataset. The model, based only on changes in the photospheric magnetic flux can then be tested on rotational, cyclical and secular timescales.

Methods: We use Kitt Peak and SoHO/MDI continuum images and magnetograms in the SATIRE-S model to reconstruct TSI over cycles 21-23. To maximise independence from TSI composites, SORCE/TIM TSI data are used to fix the one free parameter of the model. We compare and combine the separate data sources for the model to estimate an uncertainty on the reconstruction and prevent any additional free parameters entering the model.

Results: The reconstruction supports the PMOD composite as being the best historical record of TSI observations, although on timescales of the solar rotation the IRMB composite provides somewhat better agreement. Further to this, the model is able to account for 92% of TSI variations from 1978 to 2009 in the PMOD composite and over 96% during cycle 23. The reconstruction also displays an inter-cycle, secular decline of 0.20 (+0.12, −0.09) Wm−2 between cycle 23 minima, in agreement with the PMOD composite.

Conclusions: SATIRE-S is able to recreate TSI observations on all timescales of a day and longer over 31 years from 1978. This is strong evidence that changes in photospheric magnetic flux alone are responsible for almost all solar irradiance variations over the last three solar cycles.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-17T12:35:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-17T12:35:27Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-4708</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201118702</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-4708</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1051/0004-6361/201118702</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10647</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10647</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10647</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1432-0746</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0004-6361</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>EDP Sciences</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10293</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-14T15:29:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Energiesparen durch Energiebenchmark</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Buchli, Jürg</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Benchmark</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lebensmittel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>664: Lebensmitteltechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Ist die Herstellung industrieller Lebensmittel eine Energieverschwendung? Die Antwort der Energiespezialisten am Institut für Lebensmittel- und Getränkeinnovation ILGI ist: Der spezifische Energieverbrauch für die Herstellung von Lebensmitteln sollte möglichst nahe beim thermodynamischen Minimum liegen. Diese physikalische Betrachtungsweise liefert einen objektiven Benchmark für den Vergleich mit dem effektiven Verbrauch bei der Lebensmittelherstellung.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-06T09:06:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-06T09:06:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-10293</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-10293</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10293</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10293</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10293</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Transfer</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3472</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-04T09:11:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1071</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_2</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1073</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>The importance of the parent-therapist alliance in child psychotherapy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>von Wyl, Agnes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jaeger, Manuela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>616.89: Psychische Störungen, klinische Psychologie und Psychiatrie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-07T14:03:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-07T14:03:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012-06-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3472</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3472</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3472</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>43rd Annual International Meeting, Society for Psychotherapy Research (SPR), Virginia Beach VA, USA, 20-23 June 2012</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10539</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T11:44:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1096</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_8</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1097</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>"Unbesungene Heldinnen"? Hilfe für Verfolgte zur Zeit des Nationalsozialismus in der Schweiz und geschlechtsspezifische Erinnerungsdebatten nach 1945</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Businger, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>306: Kultur</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>900: Geschichte</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-09-13T08:24:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-13T08:24:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10539</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10539</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10539</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Die Schweiz und die Shoa: Von Kontroversen zu neuen Fragen, Aarau, 22. Januar 2011</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/382</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:42:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_51</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Arbeiten mit ADHS : mögliche Barrieren im Arbeitsalltag</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Binggeli, Selina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bossart, Yvonne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.8515: Ergotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:04:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-08-11T16:04:07Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-382</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-382</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/382</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/382</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/382</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22603</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-06-08T03:01:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Amyotrophe Lateralsklerose : Bedürfnisse von erkrankten Menschen und deren Familien</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Derungs, Seraina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bürgi, Tabea</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Waldboth, Veronika</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616.8: Neurologie und Krankheiten des Nervensystems</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2021-06-07T11:42:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-06-07T11:42:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-22603</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-22603</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22603</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22603</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22603</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>SBK Kongress Online, 12. Mai 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22099</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-16T04:01:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Aquaponics as an educational tool</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Junge, Ranka</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Griessler Bulc, Tjasa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Anseeuw, Dieter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Yavuczan Yildiz, Hijran</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Milliken, Sarah</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Aquaponics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Aquaponics course</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vocational training</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Higher education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Survey</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>378: Hochschulbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>639.8: Aquakultur</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>This chapter provides an overview of possible strategies for implementing aquaponics in curricula at different levels of education, illustrated by case studies from different countries. Aquaponics can promote scientific literacy and provide a useful tool for teaching the natural sciences at all levels, from primary through to tertiary education. An aquaponics classroom model system can provide multiple ways of enriching classes in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM), and the day-to-day maintenance of an aquaponics can also enable experiential learning. Aquaponics can thus become an enjoyable and effective way for learners to study STEM content, and can also be used for teaching subjects such as business and economics, and for addressing issues like sustainable development, environmental science, agriculture, food systems, and health. Using learner and teacher evaluations of the use of aquaponics at different educational levels, we attempt to answer the question of whether aquaponics fulfils its promise as an educational tool.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-03-15T14:24:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-03-15T14:24:25Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-15943-6_22</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-22099</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-030-15943-6_22</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-22099</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22099</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22099</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22099</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-030-15942-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-030-15943-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Aquaponics Food Production Systems</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/14919</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-12-15T13:12:42Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Roadblocks to inclusive education and career development for people with hearing impairments in french and italian speaking Switzerland</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rodríguez Vázquez, Silvia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bouillon, Pierrette</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Strasly, Irene</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hohenstein, Christiane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zavgorodnia, Larysa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Näf, Manuela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Inclusive access</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Swiss-wide survey</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Deaf and hearing-impaired individuals</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>French- and Italian-speaking Switzerland</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Tertiary education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>378: Hochschulbildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>At present, the penetration rate of deaf and hearing impaired students in tertiary education continues to be low in the French and Italian regions of Switzerland. This paper summarises some of the findings of a nation-wide survey, conducted to provide a better understanding of why that is the case. Data gathered seems to point at communication barriers during primary and secondary education as the main reasons for this lack of integration.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-02-04T12:50:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-02-04T12:50:22Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/14919</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/14919</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/14919</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the Second Barrier-Free Communication Conference 2018, Geneva, 9-10 November 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Second Barrier-Free Communication Conference 2018, Geneva, 9-10 November 2018</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Université de Genève</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/193</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-06T12:49:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_52</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Continuous Passive Motion nach Knietotalendoprothese : Effektivität bei spezifischen Subgruppen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Forte, Gina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tang, Katherine</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Einführung: Nach Implantierung einer Knietotalendoprothese wird die Behandlung mittels einer motorisierten Bewegungsmaschine als Zusatz zur physiotherapeutischen Behandlung im stationären Setting vielerorts routinegemäss durchgeführt. Der effektive Nutzen der Durchführung wird jedoch von vielen Autoren in Frage gestellt. &#13;
Ziel: Es soll eine evidenzbasierte Empfehlung für die Anwendung der motorisierten Bewegungsmaschine an die Praxis abgegeben werden können. Dabei soll aufgezeigt werden, welche Subgruppe von Patienten mit einer Knietotalendoprothese von der Anwendung der motorisierten Bewegungsmaschine postoperativ profitiert, bezogen auf die ROM und die Schmerzangaben.&#13;
Methode: Es wurde eine Literaturrecherche im NEBIS-Katalog sowie in den Datenbanken PubMed, Medline via OvidSP, Cinahl Database, Google Scholar und Pedro durchgeführt. Des Weiteren wurde Fachliteratur aus den Hochschulbibliotheken sowie aus dem NEBIS-Katalog, den bereits erwähnten Datenbanken und aus dem Internet gesucht. &#13;
Ergebnisse: Mit Ausnahme von einer Studie konnten keine statistisch signifikante Unterschiede der Schmerzangaben beziehungsweise der ROM im Vergleich zwischen der Kontroll- und der Experimentalgruppen aufgezeigt werden. &#13;
Schlussfolgerung: Zur Garantierung der evidenzbasierten Physiotherapie ist es von grosser Wichtigkeit, dass Praxis und Forschung eng miteinander arbeiten und dasselbe Ziel verfolgen. Die Autorinnen raten von der postoperativen Anwendung der motorisierten Bewegungsmaschine zugunsten von einem vergrösserten Bewegungsausmass oder der Schmerzreduktion ab.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2015-07-23T15:56:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-07-23T15:56:34Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-193</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-193</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/193</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/193</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/193</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19039</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-11-09T14:46:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Improve implementation of a novel paediatric therapy programme : taking theories of human behaviour into account</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Akhbari Ziegler, Schirin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hadders-Algra, Mijna</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Implementation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Theory of human behaviour</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Behaviour change</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Paediatric physical therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Early intervention</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>615.82: Physiotherapie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>618.92: Pädiatrie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Background: ‘COPing with and CAring for Infants with special Needs’ (COPCA) is a novel family-centred early intervention programme in paediatric physiotherapy. COPCA differs from well-known approaches, e.g. the therapist takes on the role of a coach and uses hands-off approaches. This implies, that to become a COPCA-coach, the therapist needs to change behaviour. Thus, it may be assumed that for successful implementation of new approaches, theories of human behaviour have to be taken into account. &#13;
Purpose: The study aims to measure behaviour changes in therapists following a COPCA course in order to identify the challenges that interfere with the implementation of the COPCA program in daily practice.  &#13;
Methods: Data were collected during a three-part COPCA course over 6 months (with two months intervals between parts) in which 15 therapists learned to become a COPCA-coach. To document behaviour changes four treatment sessions (one prior to part I T0), one in each interval (T1, T2), and one after part III (T3) of each participant (n=60) were video-recorded and analysed quantitatively with the Groningen Observation Protocol version 2 (GOP 2.0). The videos were randomized and masked to the chronology of recording moment. GOP 2.0 is a quantitative tool to assess therapeutic behaviour in different categories, e.g. “educational actions toward caregivers” or “neuromotor actions”. It allows for a quantification of the relative duration of therapeutic actions (percentage of total treatment time) during a session. Interrater reliability of the GOP 2.0 was evaluated. The first author analysed changes in therapeutic behaviour over time with the Wilcox-sign rank test. Median changes and corresponding non-parametric confidence intervals were computed using the Hodges-Lehmann estimator (HL). &#13;
Results: Interrater reliability of the GOP 2.0 (ICC2) was 0.48-1.00 (median 0.92).  Course participation was associated especially with changes in “educational actions toward caregivers” and “ neuromotor actions”. Time spent on ‘caregiver coaching’ increased: between T0 and T1 by 77.9% (99% confidence interval (CI) 48.7-99.1) and between T0 and T3 by 96.1% (99%CI 51.7-100). Also time spent on hands-off techniques increased, 37.9% (99%CI 18.8-59.5) between T0 and T1 and 40.3% (99%CI 17.8-57.7) between T0 and T3. The implementation of hands-off approaches developed at a slower rate and somewhat less sustainable than that of coaching. &#13;
Conclusions: Behaviours with a slower and less sustainable rate of change represented strong habits. The neural substrate of strong habits is located subcortically, making them relatively resistant to cognitive input. To overcome this challenge, future COPCA courses need to be adapted, by including (1) more modelling of desired behaviour and (2) more repetition and practice for the behaviours in the neuromotor domain.  &#13;
Implication: Quantitative analysis of therapeutic behaviour is a useful method to monitor changes in behaviour of therapists and – by doing so – may assist the implementation of new approaches. To implement new approaches successfully, theories of human behaviour have to be taken into account. The Behaviour Change Wheel of Michie et al., a method to characterise and design behaviour change in interventions, is a helpful framework to understand the nature of behaviour and to overcome behaviour change barriers.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-01-08T15:38:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-01-08T15:38:39Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-05-13</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Poster</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-19039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-19039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.abstractstosubmit.com/wcpt2019/archive/#/viewer/1027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.abstractstosubmit.com/wcpt2019/archive/#/viewer/abstract/1027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>World Confederation of Physical Therapy Congress, Geneva, 10-13 May 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Not specified</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/9753</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-27T13:28:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Lernen im Zeitalter von Internet und Smartphone</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Alder, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>371: Schulen und schulische Tätigkeiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Während das verfügbare Wissen im Internet explodiert ist, hinken Lehr- und Lernmethoden den Gegebenheiten  hinterher. Gefragt ist heute nicht mehr die pure Wissensvermittlung oder -aufnahme, sondern die Fähigkeit, Information  zu interpretieren, zu ordnen und zu gewichten – kurz: Lernen 2.0. Ein Plädoyer für neue Lehr- und Lernformen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-27T13:41:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-27T13:41:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015-03-27</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.hrtoday.ch/de/article/lernen-im-zeitalter-%E2%80%A8von-internet-und-smartphone</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/9753</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2235-8471</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>HR Today</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Jobindex</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6123</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T10:12:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Applied linguistics in a globalizing world : the case of professional writing and the digital literacy shift</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Perrin, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-05-25T13:12:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-25T13:12:04Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-09-10</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6123</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6123</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6123</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>The 3rd AILA East Asia and 2016 ALAK-GETA Joint International Conference, Gwangju, Korea, 9-11 September 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4680</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-18T07:15:37Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Staudenmischpflanzungen : Praxis – Beispiele – Tendenzen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Heinrich, Axel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Messer, Uwe Jörg</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>712: Landschaftsgestaltung (Landschaftsdesign)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-04-04T08:03:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-04T08:03:44Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://content-select.com/de/portal/media/view/519cc6a4-5998-429d-be00-29115dbbeaba</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4680</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-8001-7586-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-8001-9184-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>225 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Ulmer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/21065</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-12-18T04:01:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_49</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_50</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Pflegende als Zielscheibe von Aggressionen : Effekt von Schulungen im Aggressionsmanagement auf den Umgang mit Aggressionen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hölzli, Belinda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Keller, Nina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Nurse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nursing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Aggression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Training</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Program</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Prevention</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Aggression management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Hospital</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Acute ward</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Acute care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>610.73: Pflege</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Einleitung: Erlebte Aggressionen durch Patientinnen und Patienten stellen weltweit ein zunehmendes Problem für Gesundheitsfachpersonen, insbesondere für Pflegende, dar. Erlebte Aggressionen gehen mit verschiedenen psychischen und physischen Folgen einher. Eine Möglichkeit, um der Problematik und deren Folgen entgegenzuwirken, sind Schulungen im Aggressionsmanagement.&#13;
&#13;
Fragestellung: Welchen Effekt haben Schulungen im Aggressionsmanagement für Pflegende im Akutspital auf deren Umgang mit Aggressionen ausgehend von Patientinnen und Patienten?&#13;
&#13;
Methode: Um die Fragestellung zu beantworten, wurden in den Fachdatenbanken Cinahl Complete, Pubmed, Psycinfo, Pubpsych und Cochrane Library eine systematisierte Literaturrecherche durchgeführt. Die inkludierten Studien wurden zusammengefasst, gewürdigt und deren Ergebnisse diskutiert. Anhand der gewonnenen Erkenntnisse wurden Implikationen für die Pflegepraxis und die Pflegeforschung abgeleitet.&#13;
&#13;
Ergebnisse: Die Ergebnisse zeigten, dass die Schulungen mehrheitlich positive Effekte auf die Aspekte Sicherheitsgefühl, Kompetenzerwartung, Einstellung gegenüber Aggressionen und Gewalt, Selbstvertrauen und Veränderungen in den praktischen Fähigkeiten haben.&#13;
&#13;
Schlussfolgerung: Pflegende können durch Schulungen im Aggressionsmanagement gestärkt werden im Umgang mit erlebten Aggressionen durch Patientinnen und. Die regelmässige Durchführung der Schulungen werden für die Praxisinstitutionen und die Bildungsinstitutionen empfohlen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-12-17T14:42:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-12-17T14:42:50Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Thesis: Bachelor</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-21065</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-21065</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/21065</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/21065</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/21065</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>99 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/1804</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-05T11:53:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>PromoS : Prozessmodell für nicht-medizinische Supportleistungen in Spitälern</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gerber, Nicole</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tschümperlin, Carina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hofer, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Prozesse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>HM</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>FM in HC</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.2: Facility Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Spätestens seit der Einführung der Fallpauschale/SwissDRG ist in Schweizer Spitälern das Interesse an Prozessbetrachtungen gestiegen. Einerseits, um mehr Effektivität und Effizienz zu erreichen und andererseits, um genauere Kostenzuordnungen zwecks Generierung von einheitlichen, benchmarkingfähigen Kennzahlen zu ermöglichen. Ziel war daher, ein Prozess-Metamodell zu entwickeln, welches für alle Fachbereiche der nicht-medizinischen Supportleistungen [FM in HC] einsetzbar ist, aber trotzdem genügend Freiraum lässt, um individuelle Adaptionen für die unterschiedlichen Gesundheits-Institutionen und -Organisationsformen vornehmen zu können. Zudem musste gewährleistet sein, dass die (Teil)Prozessdefinitionen die genaue Umsetzung der im Kennzahlenkatalog definierten Kennzahlen [KPIs] ermöglicht und dass umgekehrt die KPIs den (Teil)Prozessen zugeordnet werden können. Auf Basis von bestehender Prozess-Literatur und –Dokumentationen aus den vier Projekt-Spitalpartnern wurde im Konsortialforschungsansatz in mehreren iterativen Experten-Runden zusammen mit den Projekt-Businesspartnern die Prozessmodellierung aller FM in HC-Supportprozesse vorgenommen. Das Resultat ist ein Prozess-Metamodell und konkrete Prozessmodelle für alle FM in HC-Supportprozesse. Das Prinzip basiert auf dem Plan-Do-Study-Act-Prinzip des Deming Cycles und zeigt die drei Ebenen Supportprozesse, Teilprozesse und Prozessschritte. Zudem wird auf die Leistungen aus dem Leistungskatalog für nicht-medizinische Supportleistungen [LekaS] verwiesen. Das Prozessmodell PromoS ist, zusammen mit dem Kennzahlenkatalog KenkaS und dem Applikationenkatalog ApplikaS, Teil des Referenzmodells für nicht-medizinische Supportleistungen in Spitälern RemoS und Basis für den Leitfaden zum Einsatz von SAP für das Facility Management im Gesundheitswesen LesapS und das Assessment-, Simulations- und Benchmarking-Tool für das Facility Management im Gesundheitswesen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2017-12-13T15:21:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-12-13T15:21:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-12</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1504</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1504</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/1804</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/1804</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/1804</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>97 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/23263</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-06-02T06:44:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Key performance indices of photovoltaic carports</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Loup, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Allenspach, Cyril Armand</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hofmann, Hendrik</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vogt, Roman</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carigiet, Fabian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Baumgartner, Franz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>PV carport</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Distribution of costs and material</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>CO2 footprint</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>e-mobility</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Durability</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333.79: Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>380: Verkehr</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>PV carports are an ideal solution to produce electricity locally and sustainably, while taking advantage of the dual use of the space. On average, large carports have a power output of 0.17 kWp/m2. The average costs amount to 2'100 CHF/kWp. The price per kWp decreases slightly when the power clearly increases. The costs of the PV modules are lower than the costs for the carport's foundation and supporting structure, which represent generally between 30 % and 60 % of the total costs. The amount of steel is estimated to 155 kg/kWp and the quantity of concrete required is approximately 650 kg/kWp. The specificities of the terrain naturally have an impact on these values. A carport parking space emits 690 kg-CO2-eq during the construction phase and an electric vehicle (EV) 11.2 kg-Co2-eq/100 km on average. Innovative projects include retractable roofs to offers the potential to reduce the amount of material used in the mounting structure, due to storing the PV modules in a safety box during heavy wind or snow load. The use of wood instead of metal, and screws anchor instead of concrete, as well as the addition of greenery, greatly reduces total CO2 emissions.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-10-07T08:40:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-10-07T08:40:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.4229/EUPVSEC20212021-6CV.4.31</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-23263</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.4229/EUPVSEC20212021-6CV.4.31</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-23263</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/23263</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/23263</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/23263</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3-936338-78-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:2196-100X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the 38th EUPVSEC</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>38th European Photovoltaic Solar Energy Conference and Exhibition (EUPVSEC), online, 6-10 September 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>WIP</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7461</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:39:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Massgeschneiderte Versorgungssicherheit : Stromproduktion</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dümmler, Patrick</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Winzer, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>333.79: Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-06-28T13:30:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-06-28T13:30:37Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017-12-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.nzz.ch/meinung/massgeschneiderte-versorgungssicherheit-ld.1336882</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7461</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0376-6829</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Neue Zürcher Zeitung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Neue Zürcher Zeitung</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22921</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-05-19T03:07:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ground speed measuring system for autonomous vehicles</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Antille, Yasmine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gubler, Etienne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gruber, Juan-Mario</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Sensor fusion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ground speed</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Autonomous driving</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Inertial measurement unit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Global positioning system</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kalman filter</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektro-, Kommunikations-, Steuerungs- und Regelungstechnik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>629: Luftfahrt- und Fahrzeugtechnik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In this paper a Ground Speed Measuring System which can measure the ground speed over the ground in three dimensions is proposed. The system uses two Kalman filters to compute the final ground speed based on the readings from its various sensors. The proposed solution combines state of the art techniques from different fields of sensor technology and will be incorporated into the high-performance driverless vehicle after completion of this project. The findings and learnings of developing this system are discussed and an evaluation of the module is presented. In the end, the system can accurately estimate a test vehicle’s ground speed during system field tests.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-07-30T13:28:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-07-30T13:28:48Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5220/0010543106610668</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-22921</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.5220/0010543106610668</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-22921</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22921</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22921</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22921</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-989-758-522-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Proceedings of the 18th International Conference on Informatics in Control, Automation and Robotics</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>18th International Conference on Informatics in Control, Automation and Robotics (ICINCO), online, 6-8 July 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>SciTePress</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/11751</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:39:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ökobilanz von PVT-Kollektoren</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Koller, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stucki, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mathez, Stefan A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Ökobilanz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333.79: Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>PVT-Hybridkollektoren kombinieren ein Photovoltaikmodul und ein Solarthermie-Kollektor zu einem System. Dadurch kann thermische und elektrische Energie gleichzeitig genutzt werden.&#13;
Aus Sicht des energetischen Ertrages weist ein PVT-Kollektor ein ähnliches Verhalten wie ein PV-Modul auf. Ein solarthermisches Modul verfügt in aller Regel über eine Rückwanddämmung, welche in einer deutlichen Ertragssteigerung bei einem grösseren Temperaturunterschied im Gegensatz zu einem PVT-Modul resultiert. Aufgrund dieser fehlenden Dämmung ist ein PVT-Modul nicht geeignet Temperaturen mit einer grösseren Differenz der Temperatur zur Umgebungsluft zu etablieren.&#13;
Um die Umweltauswirkungen eines PVT-Hybridkollektorsystems abschätzen zu können, ist es daher notwendig, die Arbeitstemperatur der Wärmesenke festzulegen und in die Berechnungen miteinzubeziehen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-10-12T08:33:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-12T08:33:15Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/11751</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/11751</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/11751</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>8. Forum Bauwerkintegrierte Photovoltaik, Bad Staffelstein, Deutschland, 8. März 2016</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16198</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T11:44:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1080</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_3</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1081</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Unsichtbares sichtbar machen : Basler Vegetative State Assessment BAVESTA</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Huber, Marion</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Assessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>TBI</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Diagnostik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wachkoma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>616.8: Neurologie und Krankheiten des Nervensystems</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-03-20T14:56:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-20T14:56:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16198</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16198</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16198</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>REHAB Basel Jubiläums-Kongress: „Lernen bewegt: 20 Jahre Rehabilitation von hirnverletzten Menschen“, Basel, 20.-21. Januar 2011</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/6196</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-21T10:31:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>PHYs and symmetrical propagation delay : study on propagation delay variation of 100Base-TX ethernet PHY chips</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Thomas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Weibel, Hans</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Blattner, Jörg</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ockert, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Ethernet</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Synchronisation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Physical layer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>NISTIR 7192</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The Institute of Embedded Systems develops devices for different hard real time Ethernet applications. In such use cases, precise knowledge of data propagation delay of Ethernet PHY chips is crucial (e.g. for precise time stamping in protocol analyzers of for IEEE 1588 enabled network interface cards). This document describes the analysis of a typical PHY chip in detail. Other PHY chips showed similar behaviour. It is expected that the observed timing characteristic is common to many 100Base-TX transceivers.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-05-29T13:00:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-05-29T13:00:06Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/6196</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/6196</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/6196</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>2004 Conference on IEEE 1588, Standard for a Precision Clock Synchronization Protocol for Networked Measurement and Control Systems</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>2004 Conference on IEEE 1588, Standard for a Precision Clock Synchronization Protocol for Networked Measurement and Control Systems, Gaithersburg, USA, 27-29 September 2004</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>NIST</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16110</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-09T12:52:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Das Projekt "Literacy for Entrepreneurship" : eine korpusbasierte Studie zur Ermittlung des Sprachförderbedarfs im Kontext von Kleinstunternehmensgründungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hoefele, Joachim</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Konstantinidou, Triantafyllia Liana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Liste Lamas, Elsa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>418: Gebrauch der Standardsprache</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-03-14T14:54:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-14T14:54:47Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16110</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16110</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16110</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Hochschultage Berufliche Bildung 2019, Fachtagung Sprachen, Siegen, Deutschland, 11.-12. März 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/7566</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-25T07:45:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Atmospheric dimethylsulphide production from corals in the Great Barrier Reef and links to solar radiation, climate and coral bleaching</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fischer, Esther</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jones, Graham</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Aerosol</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Coral bleaching</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Dimethylsulphide</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>577: Ökologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Erworben im Rahmen der Schweizer Nationallizenzen (http://www.nationallizenzen.ch)</dc:description>
          <dc:description>Coral zooxanthellae contain high concentrations of dimethylsulphoniopropionate (DMSP), the precursor of dimethylsulphide (DMS), an aerosol substance that could affect cloud cover, solar radiation and ocean temperatures. Acropora intermedia a dominant staghorn coral in the Indo-Pacific region, contain some of the highest concentrations of DMSP reported in the literature but no studies have shown that corals produce atmospheric DMS in situ and thus could potentially participate in sea surface temperature (SST) regulation over reefs; or how production varies during coral bleaching.
We show that A. intermedia from the Great Barrier Reef (GBR) produces significant amounts of atmospheric DMS, in chamber experiments, indicating that coral reefs in this region could contribute to an ‘‘ocean thermostat’’ similar to that described for the western Pacific warm pool, where significantly fewer coral reefs have bleached during the last 25 years because of a cloud-SST feedback. However, when Acropora intermedia was stressed with higher light levels and seawater temperatures DMSP production, an indicator of zooxanthellae expulsion, increased markedly in the chamber, whilst atmospheric DMS emissions almost completely shut down. These results suggest that during increased light levels and seawater temperatures in the GBR coral shut-down atmospheric DMS aerosol production, potentially increasing solar radiation levels over reefs and exacerbating coral bleaching.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-07-04T14:00:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-07-04T14:00:17Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-3826</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10533-012-9719-y</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-3826</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/s10533-012-9719-y</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/7566</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/7566</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/7566</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1573-515X</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0168-2563</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Special Issue of the 5th International Symposium on Biological and Environmental Chemistry of DMS(P) and Related Compounds, Goa, India, 19-22 October 2010</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>5th International Symposium on Biological and Environmental Chemistry of DMS(P) and Related Compounds, Goa, India, 19-22 October 2010</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Biogeochemistry</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10207</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-07-01T14:29:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Knowledge Management : strategisch oder operativ?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Minonne, Clemente</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Wissensmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Strategisches Wissensmanagement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Knowledge management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>ZWI</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.4: Leitendes Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-09-05T14:33:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-05T14:33:02Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009-03-21</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10207</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10207</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10207</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1422-9994</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Tages-Anzeiger</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Tamedia</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/5654</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-18T07:15:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Intuition und professionelles Schreiben : das Thema dieses Buches</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kruse, Otto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Perrin, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Writing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Writing research</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Progression analysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Writing strategies</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Schreiben lernt man in der Schule, dann kann mans – diese traditionelle Haltung erweist sich immer mehr als unzureichend angesichts der hohen Erwartungen einer auf Schrift ausgerichteten Gesellschaft. Auf die Erwartungen an die Schreibkompetenz wirken etwa ökonomische, technologische und psychologische Faktoren: Der Wettbewerbsdruck erfordert in Kultur, Wissenschaft und Wirtschaft wie im Sozial-und Bildungsbereich eine ausgefeilte und adressatensichere Textkommunikation. Durch die neuen Medien sind neue Formen der Textkommunikation mit eigenen Darstellungs-und Ausdrucksmitteln entstanden. Der Individualisierungsdruck der Postmoderne verlangt dem Individuum heute zudem hohe Sprachkompetenz in verschiedenen Textgenres ab. Kurz: Im deutschen Sprachraum ist eine Professionalisierung des Schreibens zu beobachten. Seit den neunziger Jahren beschleunigt sich dieser Prozess – mit entsprechenden Folgen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-04-27T12:28:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-04-27T12:28:18Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-663-12358-3_1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-663-12358-3_1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/5654</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/5654</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/5654</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:3-531-13559-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Schreiben : von intuitiven zu professionellen Schreibstrategien</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/22989</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-29T13:53:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Measuring software delivery performance using the four key metrics of DevOps</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sallin, Marc</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kropp, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Anslow, Craig</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Quilty, James W.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meier, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>DevOps</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Agile metrics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Four key metrics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>IT-performance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>The Four Key Metrics of DevOps have become very popular for measuring IT-performance and DevOps adoption. However, the measurement of the four metrics deployment frequency, lead time for change, time to restore service and change failure rate is often done manually and through surveys - with only few data points. In this work we evaluated how the Four Key Metrics can be measured automatically and developed a prototype for the automatic measurement of the Four Key Metrics. We then evaluated if the measurement is valuable for practitioners in a company. The analysis shows that the chosen measurement approach is both suitable and the results valuable for the team with respect to measuring and improving the software delivery performance.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2021-08-19T13:08:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021-08-19T13:08:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-78098-2_7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-22989</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1007/978-3-030-78098-2_7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-22989</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/22989</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/22989</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/22989</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-030-78097-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-030-78098-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1865-1348</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1865-1356</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Agile Processes in Software Engineering and Extreme Programming</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>22nd International Conference on Agile Software Development (XP 2021), Virtual Event, 14-18 June 2021</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Lecture Notes in Business Information Processing</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18096</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:39:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Monitoraggi floristici alle Bolle di Magadino (Cantone Ticino, Svizzera) : modifiche vegetazionali delle associazioni palustri aperte su substrato sabbioso (località Piattone) : confronto tra il 1992 e il 2015</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Haritz, Candida</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gaggini, Luca</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Babbi, Manuel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Catalano, Chiara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Donati, Franca</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meier, Sybille</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Krüsi, Bertil O.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Patocchi, Nicola</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Floristic monitoring</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vegetationsaufnahme</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vegetationsveränderung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Vegetation change</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Marshland</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Feuchtgebiet</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Lago Maggiore</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wetland</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333.7: Landflächen, Naturerholungsgebiete</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In this contribution the surveys of swamp/marsh vegetation in 83 squares of 5 m x 5 m placed on a grid measuring 30 m x 30 m per grid cell are presented, which were performed in 1992 and repeated in 2015 in the southern area of the Bolle di Magadino nature reserve (extended over 12 hectares). For both years of survey, the precise altitude of each square is known and all the floristic species present were recorded following the classic phytosociological method. The comparison between the two years shows a great change in the floristic spectra, even though the overall floristic diversity has increased and no species disappearance could be noted. In particular, the vegetation formations associated to the superior band of the moisture gradient that is influenced by the lake and considered to be the original and typical units of the bioregion, underwent a great change related to a lower intensity of mowing/grazing (from intensive exploitation to landscape management) and to a great expansion of invasive species. The comparison between the cartographies performed in 1963, 1976, 1992 and 2015 shows a wide growth of the reed formations towards the inland, at the expense of the magnocaricetum community and in particular of the upper swamp association. For each vegetation formation and for the different species it was possible to determine the altitude range in which their growth is optimal nowadays.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-09-05T13:06:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-09-05T13:06:28Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>http://tectel.services/dbook/Museo_Scienze_Naturali/Bollettino_STSN/Bollettino_STSN_2017-Vol._105/Index_Pc.html#p=41</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18096</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0379-1254</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>it</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Bollettino della Società Ticinese di Scienze Naturali</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Società Ticinese di Scienze Naturali</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/24316</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-01T11:59:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Wirkung von Tabaksteuern : die Schweiz im europäischen Ländervergleich</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kohler, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mattli, Renato</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vinci, Linda</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>343: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Sachen-, Finanz-, Steuer- und Wirtschaftsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>362.1041: Gesundheitsökonomie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Aufgrund der Krankheitslast des Tabakkonsums versuchen Regierungen weltweit im Rahmen der öffentlichen Gesundheit den Tabakkonsum durch bestimmte Massnahmen zu beeinflussen. Diese Massnahmen reichen von Tabakkontrollmassnahmen wie Passivrauchschutz im öffentlichen Raum über neutrale Zigarettenpackungen bis hin zu Steuern auf Tabakprodukten. In der vorliegenden Studie untersuchen wir in einem europäischen Ländervergleich die Wirkung von Tabaksteuern auf das Rauchverhalten, mit einem Fokus auf die Schweiz.&#13;
In dieser Studie verwenden wir einen umfassenden Datensatz mit Daten zu 27 europäischen Ländern über den Zeitraum von 2010 bis 2020. Dazu haben wir Daten vom Euromonitor, der Tobacco Control Scale (TCS), der Weltbank und der Weltgesundheitsorganisation (WHO) zusammengetragen. Berücksichtigt werden die Prävalenz des Zigarettenrauchens, die Anzahl verkaufter Zigaretten, die Tabaksteuer, die Zigarettenpreise, das Bruttoinlandprodukt, die Bevölkerungsgrösse und der Score der TCS, welcher ausgewählte Tabakkontrollmassnahmen eines Landes zusammenfasst. Ein tiefer TCS Score bedeutet schwache Tabakkontrollmassnahmen.&#13;
Zuerst zeigen wir, dass die Schweiz im europäischen Vergleich ein tabakkonsumfreundliches Umfeld hat mit einer tiefen Gesamtsteuerbelastung von Zigaretten, einem tiefen kaufkraftbereinigten Zigarettenpreisniveau und einem tiefen TCS Score. Bezüglich Prävalenz des Zigarettenrauchens und des Zigarettenkonsums liegt die Schweiz im europäischen Mittelfeld. Alternative Tabakprodukte werden in Europa meist viel tiefer besteuert als Zigaretten, so auch in der Schweiz.&#13;
In einer qualitativen Analyse isolieren wir den Effekt einer höheren Tabaksteuer auf die Prävalenz des Zigarettenrauchens und den Zigarettenkonsum, indem wir nur Länder mit konstanten Tabakkontrollmassnahmen im Zeitraum von 2010 bis 2020 betrachten. Wir zeigen, dass in einem relativ tabakkonsumfreundlichen Umfeld und bei tiefem Zigarettenpreisniveau viele Raucherinnen und Raucher auf Tabaksteuererhöhungen reagieren, indem sie ihren Zigarettenkonsum verringern, aber nicht mit dem Zigarettenrauchen aufhören. In einem relativ tabakkonsumunfreundlichen Umfeld und bei hohem Zigarettenpreisniveau hingegen reagieren viele Raucherinnen und Raucher auf Tabaksteuererhöhungen, indem sie mit dem Zigarettenrauchen aufhören. Die verbleibenden Raucherinnen und Raucher scheinen so stark abhängig zu sein, dass sie auch bei noch höheren Zigarettenpreisen in etwa gleich viele Zigaretten rauchen.&#13;
In einer quantitativen Analyse schätzen wir zudem auf Basis eines ökonometrischen Modells die Preiselastizität des Zigarettenkonsums. Unsere Resultate zeigen, dass der Zigarettenkonsum im europäischen Durchschnitt um circa 0.9 % sinkt, wenn der Zigarettenpreis um 1 % ansteigt. Das bedeutet, dass im Durchschnitt die Anzahl verkaufter Zigarettenpackungen pro Raucherin und Raucher um circa 25 Packungen pro Jahr sinkt, wenn der Zigarettenpreis um 10 % steigt.&#13;
Unsere Resultate deuten darauf hin, dass es für eine deutliche Reduktion des Anteils an Zigarettenraucherinnen und -rauchern in der Bevölkerung ein Bündel von Tabakkontrollmassnahmen braucht. Hohe Tabaksteuern sind dabei eine notwendige, aber als Einzelmassnahme&#13;
keine hinreichende Voraussetzung. Wenn die Gesellschaft und Politik in der Schweiz die Prävalenz des Zigarettenrauchens nachhaltig reduzieren wollen, müssen gemäss unseren Erkenntnissen gleichzeitig weitere strenge Tabakkontrollmassnahmen eingeführt werden.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2022-03-01T11:59:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2022-03-01T11:59:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2021</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.lungenliga.ch/fileadmin/user_upload/LLS/01_MetaNavigation/02_Medien/Tabak/Wirkung_von_Tabaksteuern_Schlussbericht.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/24316</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>61 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/2828</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T14:53:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Ergonomic issues at the professional translation workplace : reducing cognitive dissonance</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ehrensberger-Dow, Maureen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>O'Brien, Sharon</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Professional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Translation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>ErgoTrans_presentation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ergonomics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>150: Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>418.02: Translationswissenschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In most commercial and institutional settings, professional translation has become a form of complex human-computer interaction. While a reasonable level of attention has been given to the impact of technology on the translation process and product, the potential cognitive ergonomic issues that extend beyond the application of language technology tools remain underexplored. We aim to address this gap in research by focusing on the cognitive ergonomic issues facing translators in various workplace settings. This paper builds on an ongoing study of in-house translators in Switzerland by including data from freelance translators working in Ireland. We have identified indicators of cognitive dissonance that might be attributable to the ergonomics of human-computer interfaces, suggesting that tools and other aids at the professional translation workplace may need additional fine tuning before they can optimally enhance performance.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-02-14T15:55:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-02-14T15:55:14Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/2828</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/2828</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/2828</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>XI International ABRAPT Conference, Florianópolis, Brazil, 23-26 September 2013</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12642</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-12-17T12:34:12Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Internationales Management und gesellschaftliche Verantwortung im Zeitalter der Globalisierung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Scherer, Andreas Georg</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Butz, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Internationales Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Globalisierung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.1: Organisation und Finanzen</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-11-07T15:25:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-07T15:25:46Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12642</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12642</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12642</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7910-2424-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Internationales Management : Forschung, Lehre, Praxis</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schäffer-Poeschel</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10838</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:39:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Energieversorger im Wandel</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cometta, Claudio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Blumer, Yann</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Innovation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Paradigmenwechsel</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Anbieter</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333.79: Energie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Eine neue Studie zeigt, dass Energiefirmen in Dienstleistungen ausserhalb des Versorgergeschäfts noch Entwicklungspotenzial sehen.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-09-20T09:39:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-09-20T09:39:10Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016-05-19</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10838</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10838</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10838</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1422-8971</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Handelszeitung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Ringier Axel Springer</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/3633</identifier>
        <datestamp>2018-11-06T18:24:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Vom guten Leben im Dazwischen : Plädoyer für eine Stadt mit verdichteten Grünräumen und wohnlichen Gartenzimmern</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hodgson, Petra</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Stadtentwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Freiräume</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Verdichtung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Grüräume</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>711: Raumplanung (Städtebau)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-03-09T08:02:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-09T08:02:52Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/3633</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/3633</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/3633</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-86859-384-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>WeiterWohnen : zukunftsfähige Architektur in enger werdenden Städten</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Jovis</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/16005</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-04T12:56:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Unlocking the potential of intra-company networks : the effect of complexity</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Scherrer, Maike</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Manufacturing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Coordination</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Complexity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Network</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.5: Produktionssteuerung</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Objectives: The objective of this paper is to analyse what complexity drivers exist in manufacturing networks, how they affect strategic goal fulfilment and how the complexity drivers can be reduced by manufacturing network configuration and coordination measures. &#13;
Prior Work: Supply chain complexity has been studied on supply network, a two-stage supply chain or a single manufacturing plant (de Leeuw et al., 2013). Various literatures highlight the items defining manufacturing networks but do not link it to complexity. &#13;
Approach: Using data from a single case study, we first introduce a framework enabling the analysis of the multi-dimensional characteristic of complexity in manufacturing networks. We then use the introduced framework to analyse the case study data and derive hypotheses, serving as basis for further research.&#13;
Results: Manufacturing networks are influenced by internal and external complexity drivers. To reduce these complexity drivers, mainly manufacturing network coordination measures, such as a higher degree of standardisation, a lower degree of centralisation, or increased flows of resources, information and knowledge can be implemented. We also found some manufacturing network configuration measures, such as a higher proximity to suppliers, but since a change in the network configuration requires time and big changes in the network, configuration measures are only useful in a long time perspective. &#13;
Implications: Internal complexity drivers can be reduced by changes in the manufacturing network configuration and coordination, while external complexity drivers cannot be reduced by changes in the network. The analysis which complexity drivers influence which strategic goals and the corresponding values help to decide which measures need to be implemented first do reach the highest possible complexity decrease. &#13;
Value: A higher level of transparency allows better managing complexity. For academics, the results show how strategic goals, complexity drivers and manufacturing network configuration and coordination are linked and influence each other. For practitioners, the provided transparency shows where complexity can be reduced by manufacturing network configuration and coordination and with which measures additional complexity can be avoided.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2019-03-13T13:12:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-03-13T13:12:00Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/16005</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/16005</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/16005</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Institute for Small Business and Entrepreneurship (ISBE) Conference, Manchester, United Kingdom, 5-6 November 2014</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12403</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-02-18T07:15:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Identifikation in der Supply Chain</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fleisch, Elgar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Christ, Oliver</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Beschaffung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Supply Chain Management</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>658.5: Produktionssteuerung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-11-01T10:01:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-11-01T10:01:09Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12403</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12403</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12403</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-446-21821-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Handbuch Beschaffung : Strategien - Methoden - Umsetzung</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Hanser</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/10040</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-06-24T10:53:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1068</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1069</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Figuras da Dança : Sobre a Constitição Metafóeica do Movimento em Textos - Schiller, Kleist, Heine, Nietzsche</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller Farguell, Roger W.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Molder, Maria Filomena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Justo, J. M. Miranda</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Rhetorik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Philosophie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Ästhetik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Tanz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>100: Philosophie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>808: Rhetorik und Schreiben</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Übersetzung der deutschsprachigen Dissertation ins Portugiesische</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-30T10:50:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-30T10:50:36Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2001</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buch</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/10040</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/10040</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/10040</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:972-31-0912-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-9-723-10912-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>other</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>477 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Fundação Calouste Gulbenkian</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/19654</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T14:07:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Additive Fertigung von Keramik : Stand der Technik und Perspektiven</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Penner, Dirk</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>670: Industrielle und handwerkliche Fertigung</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2020-03-05T14:07:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-03-05T14:07:24Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-09-03</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Sonstiges</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/19654</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/19654</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/19654</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Tagung Angewandte F&amp;E in der additiven Fertigung, Winterthur, 3. September 2019</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/12120</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T14:53:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Mobile Anwendungen mit GeoTags</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hutter, Hans-Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Geotag</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Tagging</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Mobil</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>005: Computerprogrammierung, Programme und Daten</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2018-10-24T14:12:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-10-24T14:12:29Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Konferenz: Paper</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/12120</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/12120</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/12120</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>WinLink Fachtagung, Winterthur, 2006</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/8802</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-21T13:39:51Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Evaluationsbericht "Zürich isst : der Erlebnismonat rund um Ernährung, Umwelt und Genuss"</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Urs</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bättig-Frey, Petra</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Nachhaltige Ernährung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Wirkung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Kampagne</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>333: Bodenwirtschaft und Ressourcen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Zum ersten Mal fand im September 2015 in der Stadt Zürich ein Erlebnismonat rund um Ernährung, Umwelt und Genuss statt. «Zürich isst» wurde gemeinsam von der Stiftung Mercator Schweiz und dem Umwelt- und Gesundheitsschutz Zürich (UGZ), einer Dienstabteilung der Stadt Zürich, organisiert. Mit der Evaluation der Wirkung des Erlebnismonats wurde die Forschungsgruppe Nachhaltigkeitskommunikation der Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften ZHAW beauftragt. Die Evaluation zeigt, dass die angestrebten Ziele und Wirkungen erreicht werden konnten. Die erste Durchführung des Erlebnismonats war ein Erfolg.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-08-02T13:40:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-08-02T13:40:16Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2016</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Working Paper – Gutachten – Studie</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/8802</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/8802</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/8802</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>88 S.</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>ZHAW Zürcher Hochschule für Angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/18147</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-27T13:35:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Haftpflichtrecht</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Roger</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>346: Privatrecht (CH)</dc:subject>
          <dc:date>2019-09-12T08:31:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2019-09-12T08:31:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2013</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Buchbeitrag</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/18147</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/18147</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/18147</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:isbn:978-3-7255-6838-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Basiswissen Recht : ein praxisorientierter Leitfaden</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>Kleiner Merkur</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Schulthess</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4383</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-07T13:39:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Analysis of phase-resolved partial discharge patterns of voids based on a stochastic process approach</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Altenburger, Ruprecht</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Heitz, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Timmer, Jens</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Data analysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Statistical analysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Stochastic modelling</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>510: Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>621.3: Elektrotechnik und Elektronik</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>A method is presented for the determination of physical discharge parameters for partial discharges (PD) of voids in solid insulation. Based on a recently developed stochastic theory of PD processes, a statistical analysis of a measured Phase-Resolved Partial Discharge (PRPD) pattern allows the determination of the relevant physical parameters like first electron availability or decay time constants for deployed charge carriers. These parameters can be estimated directly from the measured patterns without the need of performing simulations. Furthermore, error bounds for the parameter values can be given.
The parameter estimation algorithm is based on the analysis of a contiguous region of the PRPD pattern where this region can be chosen nearly arbitrarily. Thus, even patterns with several active PD defects or patterns which are corrupted by noise can be analyzed.
The method is applied to a sequence of patterns of a void in epoxy resin. The change in first electron availability in the course of a day can be determined quantitatively from the data while the other physical parameters remain constant.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T09:26:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T09:26:55Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1894</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1088/0022-3727/35/11/309</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1894</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1088/0022-3727/35/11/309</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4383</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4383</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4383</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0022-3727</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1361-6463</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Journal of Physics D: Applied Physics</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Institute of Physics Publishing</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/13905</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-16T07:27:04Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1089</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_6</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1090</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Fuzzy classification with restricted Boltzman machines and echo-state networks for predicting potential railway door system failures</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fink, Olga</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zio, Enrico</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Weidmann, Ulrich</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>004: Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>620: Ingenieurwesen</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>In this paper, a fuzzy classification approach applying a combination of Echo-State Networks (ESNs) and a Restricted Boltzmann Machine (RBM) is proposed for predicting potential railway rolling stock system failures using discrete-event diagnostic data. The approach is demonstrated on a case study of a railway door system with real data. Fuzzy classification enables the use of linguistic variables for the definition of the time intervals in which the failures are predicted to occur. It provides a more intuitive way to handle the predictions by the users, and increases the acceptance of the proposed approach. The research results confirm the suitability of the proposed combination of algorithms for use in predicting railway rolling stock system failures. The proposed combination of algorithms shows good performance in terms of prediction accuracy on the railway door system case study.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-12-17T09:07:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-12-17T09:07:30Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.1109/TR.2015.2424213</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.1109/TR.2015.2424213</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/13905</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/13905</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/13905</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0018-9529</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:1558-1721</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>en</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>IEEE Transactions on Reliability</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>IEEE</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/4253</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T11:52:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1083</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_4</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1084</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Wie beliebt sind Bio-Erdbeer-Joghurts?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bongartz, Annette</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cezanne, Marie-Louise</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>Preference mapping</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Joghurt</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Sensorik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bio</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>664: Lebensmitteltechnologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Ziel und Zweck des EU-Forschungsprojekts Ecropolis ist es, dem Geschmack von Biolebensmitteln mit wissenschaftlichen Methoden auf den Grund zu gehen - so zum Beispiel bei Schweizer Erdbeerjoghurts.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2018-03-26T14:01:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2018-03-26T14:01:59Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2011-03-15</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in Magazin oder Zeitung</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.21256/zhaw-1861</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:doi/10.21256/zhaw-1861</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/4253</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/4253</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/4253</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0256-6575</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Lebensmittel-Technologie</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:publisher>Binkert Medien</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:digitalcollection.zhaw.ch:11475/20387</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-24T09:07:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>com_11475_1092</setSpec>
        <setSpec>com_11475_7</setSpec>
        <setSpec>col_11475_1093</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title>Die Praxis zu den Mitwirkungspflichten im Verwaltungsverfahren</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Meyer, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject>342: Öffentliches Recht (CH), Staats- und Verwaltungsrecht</dc:subject>
          <dc:description>Die Mitwirkungspflichten der Parteien sind das wichtigste Untersuchungsmittel der Verwaltungsbehörden. In der Regel sind die verwaltungsrechtlichen Mitwirkungspflichten prozessuale Lasten, deren Verletzung lediglich zu einer prozessualen Schlechterstellung führt. Der vorliegende Beitrag zeigt anhand der Praxis auf, in welchen Verwaltungsverfahren Mitwirkungspflichten bestehen, unter welchen Voraussetzungen diese als verletzt gelten und wie sich die prozessuale Schlechterstellung der säumigen Partei auf den Prozess der Sachverhaltsfeststellung – und damit den Verwaltungsentscheid – auswirkt.</dc:description>
          <dc:date>2020-08-24T09:07:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020-08-24T09:07:35Z</dc:date>
          <dc:date>2020</dc:date>
          <dc:type>Beitrag in wissenschaftlicher Zeitschrift</dc:type>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
          <dc:identifier>https://hdl.handle.net/11475/20387</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://digitalcollection.zhaw.ch/handle/11475/20387</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>info:hdl/11475/20387</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:issn:0253-9810</dc:identifier>
          <dc:language>de</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>Recht - Zeitschrift für juristische Weiterbildung und Praxis</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights>Licence according to publishing contract</dc:rights>
          <dc:publisher>Stämpfli</dc:publisher>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken completeListSize="24863" cursor="121">oai_dc////12200</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
